<div n="1" type="story">
    <head rend="italics"><lb n="01000"/>The Sisters</head>
<lb n="01001"/> <p>There was no hope for him this time: it was the third stroke.
<lb n="01002"/> Night after night I had passed the house (it was vacation time)
<lb n="01003"/> and studied the lighted square of window: and night after night
<lb n="01004"/> I had found it lighted in the same way, faintly and evenly. If he
<lb n="01005"/> was dead, I thought, I would see the reflection of candles on the
<lb n="01006"/> darkened blind for I knew that two candles must be set at the
<lb n="01007"/> head of a corpse. He had often said to me: <emph>I am not long for
<lb n="01008"/> this world</emph>, and I had thought his words idle. Now I knew they
<lb n="01009"/> were true. Every night as I gazed up at the window I said softly
<lb n="01010"/> to myself the word <emph>paralysis</emph>. It had always sounded strangely
<lb n="01011"/> in my ears like the word <emph>gnomon</emph> in the Euclid and the word
<lb n="01012"/> <emph>simony</emph> in the catechism. But now it sounded to me like the
<lb n="01013"/> name of some maleficent and sinful being. It filled me with fear
<lb n="01014"/> and yet I longed to be nearer to it and to look upon its deadly
<lb n="01015"/> work.</p>
<lb n="01016"/> <p>Old Cotter was sitting at the fire, smoking, when I came
<lb n="01017"/> downstairs to supper. While my aunt was ladling out my
<lb n="01018"/> stirabout he said as if returning to some former remark of his:
<lb n="01019"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―No, I wouldn't say he was exactly ...... but there was some=
<lb n="01020"/> thing queer ..... there was something uncanny about him. I'll
<lb n="01021"/> tell you my opinion. ...</said></p>
<lb n="01022"/> <p>He began to puff at his pipe, no doubt arranging his opinion
<lb n="01023"/> in his mind. Tiresome old fool! When we knew him first he
<lb n="01024"/> used to be rather interesting, talking of faints and worms; but I
<lb n="01025"/> soon grew tired of him and his endless stories about the
<lb n="01026"/> distillery.
<lb n="01027"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―I have my own theory about it, he said. I think it was one of
<lb n="01028"/> those ... peculiar cases. ... But it's hard to say. ...</said></p>
<lb n="01029"/> <p>He began to puff again at his pipe without giving us his
<lb n="01030"/> theory. My uncle saw me staring and said to me:
<lb n="01031"/> <said who="narrator's uncle">―Well, so your old friend is gone, you'll be sorry to hear.</said>
<lb n="01032"/> <said who="narrator">―Who? said I.</said>
<lb n="01033"/> <said who="narrator's uncle">―Father Flynn.</said>
<lb n="01034"/> <said who="narrartor">―Is he dead?</said>
<lb n="01035"/> <said who="narrator's uncle">―Mr Cotter here has just told us. He was passing by the
<lb n="01036"/> house.</said></p>
<lb n="01037"/> <p>I knew that I was under observation so I continued eating as
<lb n="01038"/> if the news had not interested me. My uncle explained to old
<lb n="01039"/> Cotter:
<lb n="01040"/> <said who="narrator's uncle">―The youngster and he were great friends. The old chap
<lb n="01041"/> taught him a great deal, mind you; and they say he had a great
<lb n="01042"/> wish for him.</said>
<lb n="01043"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―God have mercy on his soul, said my aunt piously.</said></p>
<lb n="01044"/> <p>Old Cotter looked at me for a while. I felt that his little
<lb n="01045"/> beady black eyes were examining me but I would not satisfy
<lb n="01046"/> him by looking up from my plate. He returned to his pipe and
<lb n="01047"/> finally spat rudely into the grate.
<lb n="01048"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―I wouldn't like children of mine,</said> he said, <said who="Old Cotter">to have too much
<lb n="01049"/> to say to a man like that.</said>
<lb n="01050"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―How do you mean, Mr Cotter?</said> asked my aunt.
<lb n="01051"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―What I mean is,</said> said old Cotter, <said who="Old Cotter">it's bad for children. My
<lb n="01052"/> idea is: let a young lad run about and play with young lads of
<lb n="01053"/> his own age and not be. ... Am I right, Jack?</said>
<lb n="01054"/> <said who="narrator's uncle">―That's my principle too,</said> said my uncle. <said who="narrator's uncle">Let him learn to box
<lb n="01055"/> his corner. That's what I'm always saying to that rosicrucian
<lb n="01056"/> there: take exercise. Why, when I was a nipper every morning
<lb n="01057"/> of my life I had a cold bath, winter and summer. And that's
<lb n="01058"/> what stands to me now. Education is all very fine and large. ....
<lb n="01059"/> Mr Cotter might take a pick of that leg of mutton,</said> he added to
<lb n="01060"/> my aunt.
<lb n="01061"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―No, no, not for me, said old Cotter.</said></p>
<lb n="01062"/> <p>My aunt brought the dish from the safe and laid it on the
<lb n="01063"/> table.
<lb n="01064"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―But why do you think it's not good for children, Mr Cotter?</said>
<lb n="01065"/> she asked.
<lb n="01066"/> <said who="Old Cotter">―It's bad for children,</said> said old Cotter, <said who="Old Cotter">because their minds are
<lb n="01067"/> so impressionable. When children see things like that, you
<lb n="01068"/> know, it has an effect. .....</said></p>
<lb n="01069"/> <p>I crammed my mouth with stirabout for fear I might give
<lb n="01070"/> utterance to my anger. Tiresome old rednosed imbecile!</p>
<lb n="01071"/> <p>It was late when I fell asleep. Though I was angry with old
<lb n="01072"/> Cotter for alluding to me as a child I puzzled my head to
<lb n="01073"/> extract meaning from his unfinished sentences. In the dark of
<lb n="01074"/> my room I imagined that I saw again the heavy grey face of the
<lb n="01075"/> paralytic. I drew the blankets over my head and tried to think
<lb n="01076"/> of Christmas. But the grey face still followed me. It murmured
<lb n="01077"/> and I understood that it desired to confess something. I felt my
<lb n="01078"/> soul receding into some pleasant and vicious region and there
<lb n="01079"/> again I found it waiting for me. It began to confess to me in a
<lb n="01080"/> murmuring voice and I wondered why it smiled continually and
<lb n="01081"/> why the lips were so moist with spittle. But then I remembered
<lb n="01082"/> that it had died of paralysis and I felt that I too was smiling
<lb n="01083"/> feebly as if to absolve the simoniac of his sin.</p>
<lb n="01084"/> <p>The next morning after breakfast I went down to look at the
<lb n="01085"/> little house in Great Britain Street. It was an unassuming shop,
<lb n="01086"/> registered under the vague name of <name type="shop">Drapery</name>. The drapery
<lb n="01087"/> consisted mainly of children's bootees and umbrellas and on
<lb n="01088"/> ordinary days a notice used to hang in the window, saying
<lb n="01089"/> <emph>Umbrellas Recovered</emph>. No notice was visible now for the
<lb n="01090"/> shutters were up. A crape bouquet was tied to the doorknocker
<lb n="01091"/> with ribbon. Two poor women and a telegram boy were
<lb n="01092"/> reading the card pinned on the crape. I also approached and
<lb n="01093"/> read:</p>
<lg rend="center">
<lb n="01094"/> <l>July 1st 1895</l>
<lb n="01095"/> <l>The Rev. James Flynn (formerly of S. Catherine's
<lb n="01096"/> Church, Meath Street) aged sixty-five years.</l>
<lb n="01097"/> <l>R.I.P.</l>
</lg>
<lb n="01098"/> <p>The reading of the card persuaded me that he was dead and
<lb n="01099"/> I was disturbed to find myself at check. Had he not been dead I
<lb n="01100"/> would have gone into the little dark room behind the shop to
<lb n="01101"/> find him sitting in his armchair by the fire, nearly smothered in
<lb n="01102"/> his greatcoat. Perhaps my aunt would have given me a packet
<lb n="01103"/> of high toast for him and this present would have roused him
<lb n="01104"/> from his stupefied doze. It was always I who emptied the
<lb n="01105"/> packet into his black snuffbox for his hands trembled too much
<lb n="01106"/> to allow him to do this without spilling half the snuff about the
<lb n="01107"/> floor. Even as he raised his large trembling hand to his nose
<lb n="01108"/> little clouds of smoke dribbled through his fingers over the
<lb n="01109"/> front of his coat. It may have been these constant showers of
<lb n="01110"/> snuff which gave his ancient priestly garments their green faded
<lb n="01111"/> look for the red handkerchief, blackened as it always was with
<lb n="01112"/> the snuffstains of a week, with which he tried to brush away
<lb n="01113"/> the fallen grains was quite inefficacious.</p>
<lb n="01114"/> <p>I wished to go in and look at him but I had not the courage
<lb n="01115"/> to knock. I walked away slowly along the sunny side of the
<lb n="01116"/> street, reading all the theatrical advertisements in the shopwin=
<lb n="01117"/> dows as I went. I found it strange that neither I nor the day
<lb n="01118"/> seemed in a mourning mood and I felt even annoyed at
<lb n="01119"/> discovering in myself a sensation of freedom as if I had been
<lb n="01120"/> freed from something by his death. I wondered at this for, as
<lb n="01121"/> my uncle had said the night before, he had taught me a great
<lb n="01122"/> deal. He had studied in the Irish college in Rome and he had
<lb n="01123"/> taught me to pronounce Latin properly. He had told me stories
<lb n="01124"/> about the catacombs and about Napoleon Bonaparte and he
<lb n="01125"/> had explained to me the meaning of the different ceremonies of
<lb n="01126"/> the mass and of the different vestments worn by the priest.
<lb n="01127"/> Sometimes he had amused himself by putting difficult questions
<lb n="01128"/> to me, asking me what one should do in certain circumstances
<lb n="01129"/> or whether such and such sins were mortal or venial or only
<lb n="01130"/> imperfections. His questions showed me how complex and
<lb n="01131"/> mysterious were certain institutions of the church which I had
<lb n="01132"/> always regarded as the simplest acts. The duties of the priest
<lb n="01133"/> towards the eucharist and towards the secrecy of the con=
<lb n="01134"/> fessional seemed so grave to me that I wondered how anybody
<lb n="01135"/> had ever found in himself the courage to undertake them: and I
<lb n="01136"/> was not surprised when he told me that the fathers of the
<lb n="01137"/> church had written books as thick as the post office directory
<lb n="01138"/> and as closely printed as the law notices in the newspaper
<lb n="01139"/> elucidating all these intricate questions. Often when I thought
<lb n="01140"/> of this I could make no answer or only a very foolish and
<lb n="01141"/> halting one upon which he used to smile and nod his head
<lb n="01142"/> twice or thrice. Sometimes he used to put me through the re=
<lb n="01143"/> sponses of the mass which he had made me learn by heart: and
<lb n="01144"/> as I pattered he used to smile pensively and nod his head, now
<lb n="01145"/> and then pushing huge pinches of snuff up each nostril alter=
<lb n="01146"/> nately. When he smiled he used to uncover his big discoloured
<lb n="01147"/> teeth and let his tongue lie upon his lower lip - a habit which
<lb n="01148"/> had made me feel uneasy in the beginning of our acquaintance
<lb n="01149"/> before I knew him well.</p>
<lb n="01150"/> <p>As I walked along in the sun I remembered old Cotter's
<lb n="01151"/> words and tried to remember what had happened afterwards in
<lb n="01152"/> the dream. I remembered that I had noticed long velvet curtains
<lb n="01153"/> and a swinging lamp of antique fashion. I felt that I had been
<lb n="01154"/> very far away, in some land where the customs were strange, in
<lb n="01155"/> Persia, I thought. ...... But I could not remember the end of the
<lb n="01156"/> dream.</p>
<lb n="01157"/> <p>In the evening my aunt took me with her to visit the house of
<lb n="01158"/> mourning. It was after sunset but the window panes of the
<lb n="01159"/> houses that looked to the west reflected the tawny gold of a
<lb n="01160"/> great bank of clouds. Nannie received us in the hall and, as it
<lb n="01161"/> would have been unseemly to have shouted at her, my aunt
<lb n="01162"/> shook hands with her for all. The old woman pointed upwards
<lb n="01163"/> interrogatively and, on my aunt's nodding, proceeded to toil up
<lb n="01164"/> the narrow staircase before us, her bowed head being scarcely
<lb n="01165"/> above the level of the banister rail. At the first landing she
<lb n="01166"/> stopped and beckoned us forward encouragingly towards the
<lb n="01167"/> open door of the deadroom. My aunt went in and the old
<lb n="01168"/> woman, seeing that I hesitated to enter, began to beckon to me
<lb n="01169"/> again repeatedly with her hand.</p>
<lb n="01170"/> <p>I went in on tiptoe. The room through the lace end of the
<lb n="01171"/> blind was suffused with dusky golden light amid which the
<lb n="01172"/> candles looked like pale thin flames. He had been coffined.
<lb n="01173"/> Nannie gave the lead and we three knelt down at the foot of
<lb n="01174"/> the bed. I pretended to pray but I could not gather my thoughts
<lb n="01175"/> because the old woman's mutterings distracted me. I noticed
<lb n="01176"/> how clumsily her skirt was hooked at the back and how the
<lb n="01177"/> heels of her cloth boots were trodden down all to one side. The
<lb n="01178"/> fancy came to me that the old priest was smiling as he lay there
<lb n="01179"/> in his coffin.</p>
<lb n="01180"/> <p>But no. When we rose and went up to the head of the bed I
<lb n="01181"/> saw that he was not smiling. There he lay, solemn and copious,
<lb n="01182"/> vested as for the altar, his large hands loosely retaining a
<lb n="01183"/> chalice. His face was very truculent, grey and massive, with
<lb n="01184"/> black cavernous nostrils and circled by a scanty white fur.
<lb n="01185"/> There was a heavy odour in the room, the flowers.</p>
<lb n="01186"/> <p>We blessed ourselves and came away. In the little room
<lb n="01187"/> downstairs we found Eliza seated in his armchair in state. I
<lb n="01188"/> groped my way towards my usual chair in the corner while
<lb n="01189"/> Nannie went to the sideboard and brought out a decanter of
<lb n="01190"/> sherry and some wineglasses. She set these on the table and
<lb n="01191"/> invited us to take a little glass of wine. Then, at her sister's
<lb n="01192"/> bidding, she poured out the sherry into the glasses and passed
<lb n="01193"/> them to us. She pressed me to take some cream crackers also
<lb n="01194"/> but I declined because I thought I would make too much noise
<lb n="01195"/> eating them. She seemed to be somewhat disappointed at my
<lb n="01196"/> refusal and went over quietly to the sofa where she sat down
<lb n="01197"/> behind her sister. No-one spoke: we all gazed at the empty
<lb n="01198"/> fireplace.</p>
<lb n="01199"/> <p>My aunt waited until Eliza sighed and then said:
<lb n="01200"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Ah, well, he's gone to a better world.</said></p>
<lb n="01201"/> <p>Eliza sighed again and bowed her head in assent. My aunt
<lb n="01202"/> fingered the stem of her wineglass before sipping a little.
<lb n="01203"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Did he ..... peacefully?</said> she asked.
<lb n="01204"/> <said who="Eliza">―O, quite peacefully, ma'am,</said> said Eliza. <said who="Eliza">You couldn't tell
<lb n="01205"/> when the breath went out of him. He had a beautiful death,
<lb n="01206"/> God be praised.</said>
<lb n="01207"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―And everything .... ?</said>
<lb n="01208"/> <said who="Eliza">―Father O'Rourke was in with him a-Tuesday and anointed
<lb n="01209"/> him and prepared him and all.</said>
<lb n="01210"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―He knew then?</said>
<lb n="01211"/> <said who="Eliza">―He was quite resigned.</said>
<lb n="01212"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―He looks quite resigned, said my aunt.</said>
<lb n="01213"/> <said who="Eliza">―That's what the woman we had in to wash him said. She
<lb n="01214"/> said he just looked as if he was asleep, he looked that peaceful
<lb n="01215"/> and resigned. No-one would think he'd make such a beautiful
<lb n="01216"/> corpse.</said>
<lb n="01217"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Yes, indeed, said my aunt.</said></p>
<lb n="01218"/> <p>She sipped a little more from her glass and said:
    <lb n="01219"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Well, Miss Flynn, at any rate it must be a great comfort for
<lb n="01220"/> you to know that you did all you could for him. You were both
<lb n="01221"/> very kind to him, I must say.</said></p>
<lb n="01222"/> <p>Eliza smoothed her dress over her knees.
<lb n="01223"/> <said who="Eliza">―Ah, poor James! she said. God knows we done all we could
<lb n="01224"/> as poor as we are. We wouldn't see him want anything while he
<lb n="01225"/> was in it.</said></p>
<lb n="01226"/> <p>Nannie had leaned her head against the sofa pillow and
<lb n="01227"/> seemed about to fall asleep.
<lb n="01228"/> <said who="Eliza">―There's poor Nannie, said Eliza looking at her, she's wore
<lb n="01229"/> out. All the work we had, she and me, getting in the woman to
<lb n="01230"/> wash him and then laying him out and then the coffin and then
<lb n="01231"/> arranging about the mass in the chapel! Only for Father
<lb n="01232"/> O'Rourke I don't know what we'd have done at all. It was him
<lb n="01233"/> brought us all them flowers and them two candlesticks out of
<lb n="01234"/> the chapel and wrote out the notice for the <title type="newspaper">Freeman's General</title>
<lb n="01235"/> and took charge of all the papers for the cemetery and poor
<lb n="01236"/> James's insurance.</said>
<lb n="01237"/> <said who="narrartor's aunt">―Wasn't that good of him? said my aunt.</said></p>
<lb n="01238"/> <p>Eliza closed her eyes and shook her head slowly.
<lb n="01239"/> <said who="Eliza">―Ah, there's no friends like the old friends, she said, when all
<lb n="01240"/> is said and done, no friends that a body can trust.</said>
<lb n="01241"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Indeed, that's true, said my aunt. And I'm sure now that he's
<lb n="01242"/> gone to his eternal reward he won't forget you and all your
<lb n="01243"/> kindness to him.</said>
<lb n="01244"/> <said who="Eliza">―Ah, poor James!</said> said Eliza. <said who="Eliza">He was no great trouble to us.
<lb n="01245"/> You wouldn't hear him in the house any more than now. Still, I
<lb n="01246"/> know he's gone and all that ....</said>
<lb n="01247"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―It's when it's all over that you'll miss him,</said> said my aunt.
<lb n="01248"/> <said who="Eliza">―I know that,</said> said Eliza. <said who="Eliza">I won't be bringing him in his cup of
<lb n="01249"/> beeftea any more nor you, ma'am, sending him his snuff. Ah,
<lb n="01250"/> poor James!</said></p>
<lb n="01251"/> <p>She stopped, as if she were communing with the past, and
<lb n="01252"/> then said shrewdly:
<lb n="01253"/> <said who="Eliza">―Mind you, I noticed there was something queer coming over
<lb n="01254"/> him latterly. Whenever I'd bring in his soup to him there I'd
<lb n="01255"/> find him with his breviary fallen on the floor, lying back in the
<lb n="01256"/> chair and his mouth open.</said></p>
<lb n="01257"/> <p>She laid a finger against her nose and frowned: then she
<lb n="01258"/> continued:
<lb n="01259"/> <said who="Eliza">―But still and all he kept on saying that before the summer
<lb n="01260"/> was over he'd go out for a drive one fine day just to see the old
<lb n="01261"/> house again where we were all born down in Irishtown and
<lb n="01262"/> take me and Nannie with him. If we could only get one of them
<lb n="01263"/> newfangled carriages that makes no noise that Father
<lb n="01264"/> O'Rourke told him about - them with the rheumatic wheels -
<lb n="01265"/> for the day cheap, he said, at Johnny Rush's over the way there
<lb n="01266"/> and drive out the three of us together of a Sunday evening. He
<lb n="01267"/> had his mind set on that. ... Poor James!</said>
<lb n="01268"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―The Lord have mercy on his soul!</said> said my aunt.</p>
<lb n="01269"/> <p>Eliza took out her handkerchief and wiped her eyes with it.
<lb n="01270"/> Then she put it back again in her pocket and gazed into the
<lb n="01271"/> empty grate for some time without speaking.
<lb n="01272"/> <said who="Eliza">―He was too scrupulous always,</said> she said. <said who="Eliza">The duties of the
<lb n="01273"/> priesthood was too much for him. And then his life was, you
<lb n="01274"/> might say, crossed.</said>
<lb n="01275"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―Yes,</said> said my aunt, <said who="narrator's aunt">he was a disappointed man. You could
<lb n="01276"/> see that.</said></p>
<lb n="01277"/> <p>A silence took possession of the little room and under cover
<lb n="01278"/> of it I approached the table and tasted my sherry and then
<lb n="01279"/> returned quietly to my chair in the corner. Eliza seemed to have
<lb n="01280"/> fallen into a deep revery. We waited respectfully for her to
<lb n="01281"/> break the silence: and after a long pause she said slowly:
<lb n="01282"/> <said who="Eliza">―It was that chalice he broke. ... That was what was the
<lb n="01283"/> beginning of it. Of course, they say it was all right, that it
<lb n="01284"/> contained nothing, I mean. But still ....... They say it was the
<lb n="01285"/> boy's fault. But poor James was so nervous, God be merciful to
<lb n="01286"/> him!</said>
<lb n="01287"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―And was that it? said my aunt. I heard something. .......</said></p>
<lb n="01288"/> <p>Eliza nodded.
<lb n="01289"/> <said who="narrator's aunt">―That affected his mind,</said> she said. <said who="narrator's aunt">After that he began to
<lb n="01290"/> mope by himself, talking to no-one and wandering about by
<lb n="01291"/> himself. So one night he was wanted for to go on a call and
<lb n="01292"/> they couldn't find him anywhere. They looked high up and low
<lb n="01293"/> down and still they couldn't see a sight of him anywhere. So
<lb n="01294"/> then the clerk suggested to try the chapel. So then they got the
<lb n="01295"/> keys and opened the chapel and the clerk and Father O'Rourke
<lb n="01296"/> and another priest that was there brought in a light for to look
<lb n="01297"/> for him. .... And what do you think but there he was, sitting up
<lb n="01298"/> by himself in the dark in his confession box, wideawake and
<lb n="01299"/> laughing-like softly to himself?</said></p>
<lb n="01300"/> <p>She stopped suddenly as if to listen. I too listened but there
<lb n="01301"/> was no sound in the house and I knew that the old priest was
<lb n="01302"/> lying still in his coffin as we had seen him, solemn and
<lb n="01303"/> truculent in death, an idle chalice on his breast.</p>
<lb n="01304"/> <p>Eliza resumed:
<lb n="01305"/> <said who="Eliza">―Wideawake and laughing-like to himself. ... So then of
<lb n="01306"/> course when they saw that that made them think that there was
<lb n="01307"/> something gone wrong with him. ....</said></p>
</div>
