<div n="02" type="story"><lb n="02000"/> <head rend="italics">An Encounter</head>
  <lb n="02001"/> <p>It was <persName xml:id="jd">Joe Dillon</persName> who introduced the wild west to us. He had
<lb n="02002"/> a little library made up of old numbers of <emph>The Union Jack</emph>,
<lb n="02003"/> <emph>Pluck</emph> and <emph>The Halfpenny Marvel.</emph> Every evening after school
<lb n="02004"/> we met in his back garden and arranged Indian battles. He and
  <lb n="02005"/> his fat young brother <persName xml:id="ld">Leo</persName>, the idler, held the loft of the stable
<lb n="02006"/> while we tried to carry it by storm; or we fought a pitched
<lb n="02007"/> battle on the grass. But, however well we fought, we never won
<lb n="02008"/> siege or battle and all our bouts ended with <persName xml:id="jd">Joe Dillon</persName>'s
<lb n="02009"/> wardance of victory. His parents went to eight-o'clock mass
<lb n="02010"/> every morning in Gardiner Street and the peaceful odour of
  <lb n="02011"/> <persName xml:id="md">Mrs Dillon</persName> was prevalent in the hall of the house. But he
<lb n="02012"/> played too fiercely for us who were younger and more timid.
<lb n="02013"/> He looked like some kind of an Indian when he capered round
<lb n="02014"/> the garden, an old teacosy on his head, beating a tin with his
<lb n="02015"/> fist and yelling:
<lb n="02016"/> <said who="Joe Dillon">―Ya! Yaka, yaka, yaka!</said></p>
<lb n="02017"/> <p>Everyone was incredulous when it was reported that he had
<lb n="02018"/> a vocation for the priesthood. Nevertheless it was true.</p>
<lb n="02019"/> <p>A spirit of unruliness diffused itself among us and, under its
<lb n="02020"/> influence, differences of culture and constitution were waived.
<lb n="02021"/> We banded ourselves together, some boldly, some in jest and
<lb n="02022"/> some almost in fear: and of the number of these latter, the
<lb n="02023"/> reluctant Indians who were afraid to seem studious or lacking
<lb n="02024"/> in robustness, I was one. The adventures related in the litera=
<lb n="02025"/> ture of the wild west were remote from my nature but, at least,
<lb n="02026"/> they opened doors of escape. I liked better some American
<lb n="02027"/> detective stories which were traversed from time to time by
<lb n="02028"/> unkempt fierce and beautiful girls. Though there was nothing
<lb n="02029"/> wrong in these stories and though their intention was some=
<lb n="02030"/> times literary they were circulated secretly at school. One day
  <lb n="02031"/> when <persName xml:id="fb">Father Butler</persName> was hearing the four pages of Roman
  <lb n="02032"/> history clumsy <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> was discovered with a copy of <emph>The
<lb n="02033"/> Halfpenny Marvel.</emph>
<lb n="02034"/> <said who="Father Butler">―This page or this page? This page? Now, <persName xml:id="ld">Dillon</persName>, up! <emph>Hardly
<lb n="02035"/> had the day</emph> .... Go on! What day? <emph>Hardly had the day dawned</emph>
<lb n="02036"/> ..... Have you studied it? What have you there in your pocket?</said></p>
  <lb n="02037"/> <p>Everyone's heart palpitated as <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> handed up the
<lb n="02038"/> paper and everyone assumed an innocent face. <persName xml:id="fb">Father Butler</persName>
<lb n="02039"/> turned over the pages, frowning.
<lb n="02040"/> <said who="Father Butler">―What is this rubbish?</said> he said. <said who="Father Butler"><emph>The Apache Chief!</emph> Is this
<lb n="02041"/> what you read instead of studying your Roman history? Let me
<lb n="02042"/> not find any more of this wretched stuff in this college. The
<lb n="02043"/> man who wrote it, I suppose, was some wretched scribbler that
<lb n="02044"/> writes these things for a drink. I'm surprised at boys like you,
<lb n="02045"/> educated, reading such stuff. I could understand it if you
  <lb n="02046"/> were ..... national school boys. Now, <persName xml:id="ld">Dillon</persName>, I advise you
  <lb n="02047"/> strongly, get at your work or .....</said></p>
<lb n="02048"/> <p>This rebuke during the sober hours of school paled much of
<lb n="02049"/> the glory of the wild west for me and the confused puffy face of
  <lb n="02050"/> <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> awakened one of my consciences. But when the
<lb n="02051"/> restraining influence of the school was at a distance I began to
<lb n="02052"/> hunger again for wild sensations, for the escape which those
<lb n="02053"/> chronicles of disorder alone seemed to offer me. The mimic
<lb n="02054"/> warfare of the evening became at last as wearisome to me as
<lb n="02055"/> the routine of school in the morning because I wanted real
<lb n="02056"/> adventures to happen to myself. But real adventures, I reflected,
<lb n="02057"/> do not happen to people who remain at home: they must be
<lb n="02058"/> sought abroad.</p>
<lb n="02059"/> <p>The summer holidays were near at hand when I made up my
<lb n="02060"/> mind to break out of the weariness of school life for one day at
  <lb n="02061"/> least. With <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> and a boy named <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> I planned a
<lb n="02062"/> day's miching. Each of us saved up sixpence. We were to meet
  <lb n="02063"/> at ten in the morning on the canal bridge. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>'s big sister
  <lb n="02064"/> was to write an excuse for him and <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> was to tell his
<lb n="02065"/> brother to say he was sick. We arranged to go along the Wharf
<lb n="02066"/> Road until we came to the ships, then to cross in the ferryboat
  <lb n="02067"/> and walk out to see the Pigeon House. <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> was afraid
<lb n="02068"/> we might meet <persName xml:id="fb">Father Butler</persName> or someone out of the college, but
  <lb n="02069"/> <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> asked, very sensibly, what would <persName xml:id="fb">Father Butler</persName> be
<lb n="02070"/> doing out at the Pigeon House. We were reassured: and I
<lb n="02071"/> brought the first stage of the plot to an end by collecting
<lb n="02072"/> sixpence from the other two, at the same time showing them
<lb n="02073"/> my own sixpence. When we were making the last arrangements
<lb n="02074"/> on the eve we were all vaguely excited. We shook hands,
  <lb n="02075"/> laughing, and <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> said:
<lb n="02076"/> <said who="Mahony">―Till tomorrow, mates!</said></p>
<lb n="02077"/> <p>That night I slept badly. In the morning I was firstcomer to
<lb n="02078"/> the bridge as I lived nearest. I hid my books in the long grass
<lb n="02079"/> near the ashpit at the end of the garden where nobody ever
<lb n="02080"/> came and hurried along the canal bank. It was a mild sunny
<lb n="02081"/> morning in the first week of June. I sat up on the coping of the
<lb n="02082"/> bridge admiring my frail canvas shoes which I had diligently
<lb n="02083"/> pipeclayed overnight and watching the docile horses pulling a
<lb n="02084"/> tramload of business people up the hill. All the branches of the
<lb n="02085"/> tall trees which lined the mall were gay with little light green
<lb n="02086"/> leaves and the sunlight slanted through them on to the water.
<lb n="02087"/> The granite stone of the bridge was beginning to be warm and I
<lb n="02088"/> began to pat it with my hands in time to an air in my head. I
<lb n="02089"/> was very happy.</p>
<lb n="02090"/> <p>When I had been sitting there for five or ten minutes I saw
  <lb n="02091"/> <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>'s grey suit approaching. He came up the hill, smiling,
<lb n="02092"/> and clambered up beside me on the bridge. While we were
<lb n="02093"/> waiting he brought out the catapult which bulged from his
<lb n="02094"/> inner pocket and explained some improvements which he had
<lb n="02095"/> made in it. I asked him why he had brought it and he told me
<lb n="02096"/> he had brought it to have some gas with the birds. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>
  <lb n="02097"/> used slang freely and spoke of <persName xml:id="fb">Father Butler</persName> as <persName xml:id="fb">Bunsen Burner</persName>.
<lb n="02098"/> We waited on for a quarter of an hour more but still there was
  <lb n="02099"/> no sign of <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName>. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>, at last, jumped down and said:
  <lb n="02100"/> <said who="Mahony">―Come along. I knew Fatty'd funk it.</said>
  <lb n="02101"/> <said who="narrator">―And his sixpence ... ? </said>I said.
  <lb n="02102"/> <said who="Mahony">―That's forfeit</said>, said <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>. <said who="Mahony">And so much the better for us
  <lb n="02103"/> - a bob and a tanner instead of a bob.</said></p>
<lb n="02104"/> <p>We walked along the North Strand Road till we came to the
<lb n="02105"/> vitriol works and then turned to the right along the Wharf
  <lb n="02106"/> Road. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> began to play the Indian as soon as we were out
<lb n="02107"/> of public sight. He chased a crowd of ragged girls, brandishing
<lb n="02108"/> his unloaded catapult and, when two ragged boys began, out of
<lb n="02109"/> chivalry, to fling stones at us, he proposed that we should
<lb n="02110"/> charge them. I objected that the boys were too small and so we
<lb n="02111"/> walked on, the ragged troop screaming after us <emph>Swaddlers!
<lb n="02112"/> Swaddlers!</emph>, thinking that we were protestants because <persName xml:id="mh">Ma=
  <lb n="02113"/> hony</persName>, who was dark complexioned, wore the silver badge of a
<lb n="02114"/> cricket club in his cap. When we came to the Smoothing Iron
<lb n="02115"/> we arranged a siege but it was a failure because you must have
  <lb n="02116"/> at least three. We revenged ourselves on <persName xml:id="ld">Leo Dillon</persName> by saying
<lb n="02117"/> what a funk he was and guessing how many he would get at
  <lb n="02118"/> three o'clock from <persName xml:id="mr">Mr Ryan</persName>.</p>
<lb n="02119"/> <p>We came then near the river. We spent a long time walking
<lb n="02120"/> about the noisy streets flanked by high stone walls, watching
<lb n="02121"/> the working of cranes and engines and often being shouted at
<lb n="02122"/> for our immobility by the drivers of groaning carts. It was noon
<lb n="02123"/> when we reached the quays and, as all the labourers seemed to
<lb n="02124"/> be eating their lunches, we bought two big currant buns and sat
<lb n="02125"/> down to eat them on some metal piping beside the river. We
<lb n="02126"/> pleased ourselves with the spectacle of Dublin's commerce -
<lb n="02127"/> the barges signalled from far away by their curls of woolly
<lb n="02128"/> smoke, the brown fishing fleet beyond Ringsend, the big white
<lb n="02129"/> sailing-vessel which was being discharged on the opposite
  <lb n="02130"/> quay. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> said <said who="Mahony">it would be right skit to run away to sea on
  <lb n="02131"/> one of those big ships</said> and even I, looking at the high masts,
<lb n="02132"/> saw or imagined the geography which had been scantily dosed
<lb n="02133"/> to me at school gradually taking substance under my eyes.
<lb n="02134"/> School and home seemed to recede from us and their influences
<lb n="02135"/> upon us seemed to wane.</p>
<lb n="02136"/> <p>We crossed the Liffey in the ferryboat, paying our toll to be
<lb n="02137"/> transported in the company of two labourers and a little Jew
<lb n="02138"/> with a bag. We were serious to the point of solemnity but once
<lb n="02139"/> during the short voyage our eyes met and we laughed. When
<lb n="02140"/> we landed we watched the discharging of the graceful three=
<lb n="02141"/> master which we had observed from the other quay. Some
  <lb n="02142"/> bystander said <said who="bystander">that she was a Norwegian vessel</said>. I went to the
<lb n="02143"/> stern and tried to decipher the legend upon it but, failing to do
<lb n="02144"/> so, I came back and examined the foreign sailors to see had any
<lb n="02145"/> of them green eyes for I had some confused notion ......... The
<lb n="02146"/> sailors' eyes were blue and grey and even black. The only sailor
<lb n="02147"/> whose eyes could have been called green was a tall man who
<lb n="02148"/> amused the crowd on the quay by calling out cheerfully every
<lb n="02149"/> time the planks fell:
<lb n="02150"/> <said who="sailor">―All right! All right!</said></p>
<lb n="02151"/> <p>When we were tired of this sight we wandered slowly into
<lb n="02152"/> Ringsend. The day had grown sultry and in the windows of the
<lb n="02153"/> grocers' shops musty biscuits lay bleaching. We bought some
<lb n="02154"/> biscuits and chocolate which we ate sedulously as we wandered
<lb n="02155"/> through the squalid streets where the families of the fishermen
<lb n="02156"/> live. We could find no dairy and so we went into a huckster's
<lb n="02157"/> shop and bought a bottle of raspberry lemonade each. Re=
  <lb n="02158"/> freshed by this <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> chased a cat down a lane but the cat
<lb n="02159"/> escaped into a wide field. We both felt rather tired and when
<lb n="02160"/> we reached the field we made at once for a sloping bank over
<lb n="02161"/> the ridge of which we could see the Dodder.</p>
<lb n="02162"/> <p>It was too late and we were too tired to carry out our project
<lb n="02163"/> of visiting the Pigeon House. We had to be home before four
<lb n="02164"/> o'clock lest our adventure should be discovered. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>
<lb n="02165"/> looked regretfully at his catapult and I had to suggest going
<lb n="02166"/> home by train before he regained any cheerfulness. The sun
<lb n="02167"/> went in behind some clouds and left us to our jaded thoughts
<lb n="02168"/> and the crumbs of our provisions.</p>
<lb n="02169"/> <p>There was nobody but ourselves in the field. When we had
<lb n="02170"/> lain on the bank for some time without speaking I saw a man
<lb n="02171"/> approaching from the far end of the field. I watched him lazily
<lb n="02172"/> as I chewed one of those green stems on which girls tell
<lb n="02173"/> fortunes. He came along by the bank slowly. He walked with
<lb n="02174"/> one hand upon his hip and in the other hand he held a stick
<lb n="02175"/> with which he tapped the turf lightly. He was shabbily dressed
<lb n="02176"/> in a suit of greenish black and wore what we used to call a jerry
<lb n="02177"/> hat with a very high crown. He seemed to be fairly old for his
<lb n="02178"/> moustache was ashen grey. When he passed at our feet he
<lb n="02179"/> glanced up at us quickly and then continued his way. We
<lb n="02180"/> followed him with our eyes and saw that when he had gone on
<lb n="02181"/> for perhaps fifty paces he turned about and began to retrace his
<lb n="02182"/> steps. He walked towards us very slowly, always tapping the
<lb n="02183"/> ground with his stick, so slowly that I thought he was looking
<lb n="02184"/> for something in the grass.</p>
<lb n="02185"/> <p>He stopped when he came level with us and bade us good
<lb n="02186"/> day. We answered him and he sat down beside us on the slope
<lb n="02187"/> slowly and with great care. He began to talk of the weather,
<lb n="02188"/> saying that it would be a very hot summer and adding that the
<lb n="02189"/> seasons had changed greatly since he was a boy - a long time
<lb n="02190"/> ago. He said that <said who="the old man" direct= "false">the happiest time of one's life was un=
<lb n="02191"/> doubtedly one's schoolboy days and that he would give any=
  <lb n="02192"/> thing to be young again.</said> While he expressed these sentiments,
<lb n="02193"/> which bored us a little, we kept silent. Then he began to talk of
<lb n="02194"/> school and of books. He asked us whether we had read the
  <lb n="02195"/> poetry of <persName xml:id="tm">Thomas Moore</persName> or the works of <persName xml:id="ws">Sir Walter Scott</persName> and
  <lb n="02196"/> <persName xml:id="ll">Lord Lytton</persName>. I pretended that I had read every book he
<lb n="02197"/> mentioned so that in the end he said:
  <lb n="02198"/> <said who="the old man">―Ah, I can see you are a bookworm like myself. Now, </said>he
  <lb n="02199"/> added, pointing to <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> who was regarding us with open
<lb n="02200"/> eyes, <said who="the old man">he is different. He goes in for games.</said></p>
  <lb n="02201"/> <p>He said <said who="the old man" direct="false">he had all <persName xml:id="ws">Sir Walter Scott</persName>'s works and all <persName xml:id="ll">Lord
  <lb n="02202"/> Lytton</persName>'s works at home and never tired of reading them.</said> <said who="the old man">Of
  <lb n="02203"/> course, </said>he said, <said who="the old man">there were some of <persName xml:id="ll">Lord Lytton</persName>'s works which
  <lb n="02204"/> boys couldn't read.</said> <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> asked why couldn't boys read
<lb n="02205"/> them - a question which agitated and pained me because I was
<lb n="02206"/> afraid the man would think I was as stupid as <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName>. The
<lb n="02207"/> man, however, only smiled. I saw that he had great gaps in his
<lb n="02208"/> mouth between his yellow teeth. Then he asked us which of us
  <lb n="02209"/> had the most sweethearts. <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> mentioned lightly that he
<lb n="02210"/> had three totties. The man asked me how many had I. I
<lb n="02211"/> answered that I had none. He did not believe me and said he
<lb n="02212"/> was sure I must have one. I was silent.
  <lb n="02213"/> <said who="Mahony">―Tell us, </said>said <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> pertly to the man, <said who="Mahony">how many have you
<lb n="02214"/> yourself?</said></p>
<lb n="02215"/> <p>The man smiled as before and said that<said who="the old man" direct="false"> when he was our age
  <lb n="02216"/> he had lots of sweethearts.</said> <said who="the old man">Every boy, </said>he said, <said who="the old man">has a little
  <lb n="02217"/> sweetheart.</said></p>
<lb n="02218"/> <p>His attitude on this point struck me as strangely liberal in a
<lb n="02219"/> man of his age. In my heart I thought that what he said about
<lb n="02220"/> boys and sweethearts was reasonable. But I disliked the words
<lb n="02221"/> in his mouth and I wondered why he shivered once or twice as
<lb n="02222"/> if he feared something or felt a sudden chill. As he proceeded I
<lb n="02223"/> noticed that his accent was good. He began to speak to us
<lb n="02224"/> about girls, saying what nice soft hair they had and how soft
<lb n="02225"/> their hands were and how all girls were not so good as they
<lb n="02226"/> seemed to be if one only knew. <said who="the old man">There was nothing he liked, </said>he
<lb n="02227"/> said, <said who="the old man">so much as looking at a nice young girl, at her nice white
  <lb n="02228"/> hands and her beautiful soft hair.</said> He gave me the impression
<lb n="02229"/> that he was repeating something which he had learned by heart
<lb n="02230"/> or that, magnetised by some words of his own speech, his mind
<lb n="02231"/> was slowly circling round and round in the same orbit. At
<lb n="02232"/> times he spoke as if he were simply alluding to some fact that
<lb n="02233"/> everybody knew and at times he lowered his voice and spoke
<lb n="02234"/> mysteriously as if he were telling us something secret which he
<lb n="02235"/> did not wish others to overhear. He repeated his phrases over
<lb n="02236"/> and over again, varying them and surrounding them with his
<lb n="02237"/> monotonous voice. I continued to gaze towards the foot of the
<lb n="02238"/> slope, listening to him.</p>
<lb n="02239"/> <p>After a long while his monologue paused. He stood up
<lb n="02240"/> slowly, saying that he had to leave us for a minute or so, a few
<lb n="02241"/> minutes, and, without changing the direction of my gaze, I saw
<lb n="02242"/> him walking slowly away from us towards the near end of the
<lb n="02243"/> field. We remained silent when he had gone. After a silence of a
  <lb n="02244"/> few minutes I heard <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> exclaim:
<lb n="02245"/> <said who="Mahony">―I say! Look what he's doing!</said></p>
  <lb n="02246"/> <p>As I neither answered nor raised my eyes <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> exclaimed
<lb n="02247"/> again:
<lb n="02248"/> <said who="Mahony">―I say ..... He's a queer old josser!</said>
  <lb n="02249"/> <said who="narrator">―In case he asks us for our names, </said>I said, <said who="narrator">let you be <persName xml:id="mh">Murphy</persName>
  <lb n="02250"/> and I'll be <persName xml:id="sm">Smith</persName>.</said></p>
<lb n="02251"/> <p>We said nothing further to each other. I was still considering
<lb n="02252"/> whether I would go away or not when the man came back and
<lb n="02253"/> sat down beside us again. Hardly had he sat down when <persName xml:id="mh">Ma=
  <lb n="02254"/> hony</persName>, catching sight of the cat which had escaped him, sprang
<lb n="02255"/> up and pursued her across the field. The man and I watched the
  <lb n="02256"/> chase. The cat escaped once more and <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> began to throw
<lb n="02257"/> stones at the wall she had escaladed. Desisting from this, he
<lb n="02258"/> began to wander about the far end of the field, aimlessly.</p>
<lb n="02259"/> <p>After an interval the man spoke to me. He said that <said who="the old man" direct="false">my
  <lb n="02260"/> friend was a very rough boy </said>and asked <said who="the old man" direct="false">did he get whipped
  <lb n="02261"/> often at school.</said> I was going to reply indignantly that we were
<lb n="02262"/> not national school boys to be <emph>whipped</emph>, as he called it; but I
<lb n="02263"/> remained silent. He began to speak on the subject of chastising
<lb n="02264"/> boys. His mind, as if magnetised again by his speech, seemed to
<lb n="02265"/> circle slowly round and round its new centre. He said <said who="the old man" direct="false">that
<lb n="02266"/> when boys were that kind they ought to be whipped and well
  <lb n="02267"/> whipped.</said> When a boy was rough and unruly there was nothing
<lb n="02268"/> would do him any good but a good sound whipping. A slap on
<lb n="02269"/> the hand or a box on the ear was no good: what he wanted was
<lb n="02270"/> to get a nice warm whipping. I was surprised at this sentiment
<lb n="02271"/> and involuntarily glanced up at his face. As I did so I met the
<lb n="02272"/> gaze of a pair of bottlegreen eyes peering at me from under a
<lb n="02273"/> twitching forehead. I turned my eyes away again.</p>
<lb n="02274"/> <p>The man continued his monologue. He seemed to have
<lb n="02275"/> forgotten his recent liberalism. He said that <said who="the old man" direct="false">if ever he found a
<lb n="02276"/> boy talking to girls or having a girl for a sweetheart he would
<lb n="02277"/> whip him and whip him: and that would teach him not to be
<lb n="02278"/> talking to girls. And if a boy had a girl for a sweetheart and
<lb n="02279"/> told lies about it then he would give him such a whipping as no
  <lb n="02280"/> boy ever got in this world. </said>He said that <said who="the old man" direct="false">there was nothing in
  <lb n="02281"/> this world he would like so well as that. </said>He described to me
<lb n="02282"/> how he would whip such a boy as if he were unfolding some
<lb n="02283"/> elaborate mystery. <said who="the old man" direct="false">He would love that, </said>he said, <said who="the old man" direct="false">better than
  <lb n="02284"/> anything in this world:</said> and his voice, as he led me monot=
<lb n="02285"/> onously through the mystery, grew almost affectionate and
<lb n="02286"/> seemed to plead with me that I should understand him.</p>
<lb n="02287"/> <p>I waited till his monologue paused again. Then I stood up
<lb n="02288"/> abruptly. Lest I should betray my agitation I delayed a few
<lb n="02289"/> moments pretending to fix my shoe properly and then, saying
<lb n="02290"/> that I was obliged to go, I bade him good day. I went up the
<lb n="02291"/> slope calmly but my heart was beating quickly with fear that he
<lb n="02292"/> would seize me by the ankles. When I reached the top of the
<lb n="02293"/> slope I turned round and, without looking at him, called loudly
<lb n="02294"/> across the field:
  <lb n="02295"/> <said who="narrator">―<persName xml:id="mh">Murphy</persName>!</said></p>
<lb n="02296"/> <p>My voice had an accent of forced bravery in it and I was
<lb n="02297"/> ashamed of my paltry stratagem. I had to call the name again
  <lb n="02298"/> before <persName xml:id="mh">Mahony</persName> saw me and hallooed in answer. How my heart
<lb n="02299"/> beat as he came running across the field to me! He ran as if to
<lb n="02300"/> bring me aid. And I was penitent for in my heart I had always
<lb n="02301"/> despised him a little.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
