<div n="05" type="story"><lb n="05000"/> <head rend="italics">After the Race</head>
<lb n="05001"/> <p>The cars came scudding in towards Dublin, running evenly
<lb n="05002"/> like pellets in the groove of the Naas Road. At the crest of the
<lb n="05003"/> hill at Inchicore sightseers had gathered in clumps to watch the
<lb n="05004"/> cars careering homeward and through this channel of poverty
<lb n="05005"/> and inaction the continent sped its wealth and industry. Now
<lb n="05006"/> and again the clumps of people raised the cheer of the grate=
<lb n="05007"/> fully oppressed. Their sympathy, however was for the blue
<lb n="05008"/> cars - the cars of their friends, the French.</p>
<lb n="05009"/> <p>The French, moreover, were virtual victors. Their team had
<lb n="05010"/> finished solidly; they had been placed second and third and the
<lb n="05011"/> driver of the winning German car was reported a Belgian. Each
<lb n="05012"/> blue car, therefore, received a double round of welcome as it
<lb n="05013"/> topped the crest of the hill and each cheer of welcome was
<lb n="05014"/> acknowledged with smiles and nods by those in the car. In one
<lb n="05015"/> of these trimly built cars was a party of four young men whose
<lb n="05016"/> spirits seemed to be at present well above the level of successful
<lb n="05017"/> Gallicism: in fact, these four young men were almost hilarious.
<lb n="05018"/> They were Charles Ségouin, the owner of the car; André
<lb n="05019"/> Rivière, a young electrician of Canadian birth; a huge Hungar=
<lb n="05020"/> ian named Villona and a neatly groomed young man named
<lb n="05021"/> Doyle. Ségouin was in good humour because he had unex=
<lb n="05022"/> pectedly received some orders in advance (he was about to start
<lb n="05023"/> a motor establishment in Paris) and Rivière was in good hu=
<lb n="05024"/> mour because he was to be appointed manager of the establish=
<lb n="05025"/> ment; these two young men (who were cousins) were also in
<lb n="05026"/> good humour because of the success of the French cars. Villona
<lb n="05027"/> was in good humour because he had had a very satisfactory
<lb n="05028"/> luncheon, and besides he was an optimist by nature. The fourth
<lb n="05029"/> member of the party, however, was too excited to be genuinely
<lb n="05030"/> happy.</p>
<lb n="05031"/> <p>He was about twenty-six years of age, with a soft, light
<lb n="05032"/> brown moustache and rather innocent looking grey eyes. His
<lb n="05033"/> father, who had begun life as an advanced nationalist, had
<lb n="05034"/> modified his views early. He had made his money as a butcher
<lb n="05035"/> in Kingstown and by opening shops in Dublin and in the
<lb n="05036"/> suburbs he had made his money many times over. He had also
<lb n="05037"/> been fortunate enough to secure some of the police contracts
<lb n="05038"/> and in the end he had become rich enough to be alluded to in
<lb n="05039"/> the Dublin newspapers as a merchant prince. He had sent his
<lb n="05040"/> son to England to be educated in a big catholic college and had
<lb n="05041"/> afterwards sent him to Dublin university to study law. Jimmy
<lb n="05042"/> did not study very earnestly and took to bad courses for a
<lb n="05043"/> while. He had money and he was popular and he divided his
<lb n="05044"/> time curiously between musical and motoring circles. Then he
<lb n="05045"/> had been sent for a term to Cambridge to see a little life. His
<lb n="05046"/> father, remonstrative but covertly proud of the excess, had paid
<lb n="05047"/> his bills and brought him home. It was at Cambridge that he
<lb n="05048"/> had met Ségouin. They were not much more than acquaint=
<lb n="05049"/> ances as yet but Jimmy found great pleasure in the society of
<lb n="05050"/> one who had seen so much of the world and was reputed to
<lb n="05051"/> own some of the biggest hotels in France. Such a person (as his
<lb n="05052"/> father agreed) was well worth knowing, even if he had not been
<lb n="05053"/> the charming companion he was. Villona was entertaining also
<lb n="05054"/> - a brilliant pianist - but, unfortunately, very poor.</p>
<lb n="05055"/> <p>The car ran on merrily with its cargo of hilarious youth. The
<lb n="05056"/> two cousins sat on the front seat; Jimmy and his Hungarian
<lb n="05057"/> friend sat behind. Decidedly Villona was in excellent spirits; he
<lb n="05058"/> kept up a deep bass hum of melody for miles of the road. The
<lb n="05059"/> Frenchmen flung their laughter and light words over their
<lb n="05060"/> shoulders and often Jimmy had to strain forward to catch the
<lb n="05061"/> quick phrase. This was not altogether pleasant for him as he
<lb n="05062"/> had nearly always to make a deft guess at the meaning and
<lb n="05063"/> shout back a suitable answer in the teeth of a high wind.
<lb n="05064"/> Besides, Villona's humming would confuse anybody: the noise
<lb n="05065"/> of the car, too.</p>
<lb n="05066"/> <p>Rapid motion through space elates one; so does notoriety; so
<lb n="05067"/> does the possession of money. These were three good reasons
<lb n="05068"/> for Jimmy's excitement. He had been seen by many of his
<lb n="05069"/> friends that day in the company of these continentals. At the
<lb n="05070"/> control Ségouin had presented him to one of the French
<lb n="05071"/> competitors and, in answer to his confused murmur of compli=
<lb n="05072"/> ment, the swarthy face of the driver had disclosed a line of
<lb n="05073"/> shining white teeth. It was pleasant after that honour to return
<lb n="05074"/> to the profane world of spectators amid nudges and significant
<lb n="05075"/> looks. Then as to money - he really had a great sum under his
<lb n="05076"/> control. Ségouin, perhaps, would not think it a great sum but
<lb n="05077"/> Jimmy who, in spite of temporary errors, was at heart the
<lb n="05078"/> inheritor of solid instincts knew well with what difficulty it had
<lb n="05079"/> been got together. This knowledge had previously kept his bills
<lb n="05080"/> within the limits of reasonable recklessness and, if he had been
<lb n="05081"/> so conscious of the labour latent in money when there had been
<lb n="05082"/> question merely of some freak of the higher intelligence, how
<lb n="05083"/> much more so now when he was about to stake the greater part
<lb n="05084"/> of his substance! It was a serious thing for him.</p>
<lb n="05085"/> <p>Of course, the investment was a good one and Ségouin had
<lb n="05086"/> managed to give the impression that it was by a favour of
<lb n="05087"/> friendship the mite of Irish money was to be included in the
<lb n="05088"/> capital of the concern. Jimmy had a respect for his father's
<lb n="05089"/> shrewdness in business matters and in this case it had been his
<lb n="05090"/> father who had first suggested the investment; money to be
<lb n="05091"/> made in the motor business, pots of money. Moreover, Ségouin
<lb n="05092"/> had the unmistakable air of wealth. Jimmy set out to translate
<lb n="05093"/> into days' work that lordly car on which he sat. How smoothly
<lb n="05094"/> it ran! In what style they had come careering along the country
<lb n="05095"/> roads! The journey laid a magical finger on the genuine pulse
<lb n="05096"/> of life and gallantly the machinery of human nerves strove to
<lb n="05097"/> answer the bounding courses of the swift blue animal.</p>
<lb n="05098"/> <p>They drove down Dame Street. The street was busy with
<lb n="05099"/> unusual traffic, loud with the horns of motorists and the gongs
<lb n="05100"/> of impatient tramdrivers. Near the bank Ségouin drew up and
<lb n="05101"/> Jimmy and his friend alighted. A little knot of people collected
<lb n="05102"/> on the footpath to pay homage to the snorting motor. The
<lb n="05103"/> party was to dine together that evening in Ségouin's hotel and
<lb n="05104"/> meanwhile Jimmy and his friend, who was staying with him,
<lb n="05105"/> were to go home to dress. The car steered out slowly for
<lb n="05106"/> Grafton Street while the two young men pushed their way
<lb n="05107"/> through the knot of gazers. They walked northward with a
<lb n="05108"/> curious feeling of disappointment in the exercise while the city
<lb n="05109"/> hung its pale globes of light above them in a haze of summer
<lb n="05110"/> evening.</p>
<lb n="05111"/> <p>In Jimmy's house this dinner had been pronounced an
<lb n="05112"/> occasion. A certain pride mingled with his parents' trepidation,
<lb n="05113"/> a certain eagerness, also, to play fast and loose for the names of
<lb n="05114"/> great foreign cities have at least this virtue. Jimmy, too, looked
<lb n="05115"/> very well when he was dressed and, as he stood in the hall
<lb n="05116"/> giving a last equation to the bows of his dress tie, his father
<lb n="05117"/> may have felt even commercially satisfied at having secured for
<lb n="05118"/> his son qualities often unpurchasable. His father, therefore,
<lb n="05119"/> was unusually friendly with Villona and his manner expressed
<lb n="05120"/> a real respect for foreign accomplishments but this subtlety of
<lb n="05121"/> his host was probably lost upon the Hungarian who was
<lb n="05122"/> beginning to have a sharp desire for his dinner.</p>
<lb n="05123"/> <p>The dinner was excellent, exquisite. Ségouin, Jimmy de=
<lb n="05124"/> cided, had a very refined taste. The party was increased by a
<lb n="05125"/> young Englishman named Routh whom Jimmy had seen with
<lb n="05126"/> Ségouin at Cambridge. The young men supped in a snug room
<lb n="05127"/> lit by electric candle lamps. They talked volubly and with little
<lb n="05128"/> reserve. Jimmy, whose imagination was kindling, conceived the
<lb n="05129"/> lively youth of the Frenchmen twined elegantly upon the firm
<lb n="05130"/> framework of the Englishman's manner. A graceful image of
<lb n="05131"/> his, he thought, and a just one. He admired the dexterity with
<lb n="05132"/> which their host directed the conversation. The five young men
<lb n="05133"/> had various tastes and their tongues had been loosened. Vil=
<lb n="05134"/> lona, with immense respect, began to discover to the mildly
<lb n="05135"/> surprised Englishman the beauties of the English madrigal,
<lb n="05136"/> deploring the loss of old instruments. Rivière, not wholly
<lb n="05137"/> ingenuously, undertook to explain to Jimmy the triumph of the
<lb n="05138"/> French mechanicians. The resonant voice of the Hungarian was
<lb n="05139"/> about to prevail in ridicule of the spurious lutes of the romantic
<lb n="05140"/> painters when Ségouin shepherded his party into politics. Here
<lb n="05141"/> was congenial ground for all. Jimmy, under generous influ=
<lb n="05142"/> ences, felt the buried zeal of his father wake to life within him:
<lb n="05143"/> he aroused the torpid Routh at last. The room grew doubly hot
<lb n="05144"/> and Ségouin's task grew harder each moment: there was even
<lb n="05145"/> danger of personal spite. The alert host at an opportunity lifted
<lb n="05146"/> his glass to humanity and, when the toast had been drunk, he
<lb n="05147"/> threw open a window significantly.</p>
<lb n="05148"/> <p>That night the city wore the mask of a capital. The five
<lb n="05149"/> young men strolled along Stephen's Green in a faint cloud of
<lb n="05150"/> aromatic smoke. They talked loudly and gaily and their cloaks
<lb n="05151"/> dangled from their shoulders. The people made way for them.
<lb n="05152"/> At the corner of Grafton Street a short fat man was putting two
<lb n="05153"/> handsome ladies on a car in charge of another fat man. The car
<lb n="05154"/> drove off and the short fat man caught sight of the party.
<lb n="05155"/> <said who="">―</said>André!
<lb n="05156"/> <said who="">―</said>It's Farley!</p>
<lb n="05157"/> <p>A torrent of talk followed. Farley was an American. No one
<lb n="05158"/> knew very well what the talk was about. Villona and Rivière
<lb n="05159"/> were the noisiest but all the men were excited. They got up on
<lb n="05160"/> a car, squeezing themselves together amid much laughter. They
<lb n="05161"/> drove by the crowd, blended now into soft colours, to a music
<lb n="05162"/> of merry bells. They took the train at Westland Row and in a
<lb n="05163"/> few seconds, as it seemed to Jimmy, they were walking out of
<lb n="05164"/> Kingstown station. The ticket collector saluted Jimmy; he was
<lb n="05165"/> an old man.
<lb n="05166"/> <said who="">―</said>Fine night, sir!</p>
<lb n="05167"/> <p>It was a serene summer night; the harbour lay like a
<lb n="05168"/> darkened mirror at their feet. They proceeded towards it with
<lb n="05169"/> linked arms, singing <emph>Cadet Roussel</emph> in chorus, stamping their
<lb n="05170"/> feet at every:</p>
<lb n="05171"/> <p><emph>Ho! Ho! Hohé, vraiment!</emph></p>
<lb n="05172"/> <p>They got into a rowboat at the slip and made out for the
<lb n="05173"/> American's yacht. There was to be supper, music, cards. Vil=
<lb n="05174"/> lona said with conviction:
<lb n="05175"/> <said who="">―</said>It is beautiful!</p>
<lb n="05176"/> <p>There was a yacht piano in the cabin. Villona played a waltz
<lb n="05177"/> for Farley and Rivière, Farley acting as cavalier and Rivière as
<lb n="05178"/> lady. Then an impromptu square dance, the men devising
<lb n="05179"/> original figures. What merriment! Jimmy took his part with a
<lb n="05180"/> will; this was seeing life, at least. Then Farley got out of breath
<lb n="05181"/> and cried <emph>Stop!</emph> A man brought in a light supper and the young
<lb n="05182"/> men sat down to it for form' sake. They drank, however: it was
<lb n="05183"/> bohemian. They drank Ireland, England, France, Hungary, the
<lb n="05184"/> United States of America. Jimmy made a speech, a long speech,
<lb n="05185"/> Villona saying: <emph>Hear! hear!</emph> whenever there was a pause. There
<lb n="05186"/> was a great clapping of hands when he sat down. It must have
<lb n="05187"/> been a good speech. Farley clapped him on the back and
<lb n="05188"/> laughed loudly. What jovial fellows! What good company they
<lb n="05189"/> were!</p>
<lb n="05190"/> <p>Cards! cards! The table was cleared. Villona returned quietly
<lb n="05191"/> to his piano and played voluntaries for them. The other men
<lb n="05192"/> played game after game, flinging themselves boldly into the
<lb n="05193"/> adventure. They drank the health of the queen of hearts and of
<lb n="05194"/> the queen of diamonds. Jimmy felt obscurely the lack of an
<lb n="05195"/> audience: the wit was flashing. Play ran very high and paper
<lb n="05196"/> began to pass. Jimmy did not know exactly who was winning
<lb n="05197"/> but he knew that he was losing. But it was his own fault for he
<lb n="05198"/> frequently mistook his cards and the other men had to calculate
<lb n="05199"/> his I.O.U's for him. They were devils of fellows but he wished
<lb n="05200"/> they would stop: it was getting late. Someone gave the toast of
<lb n="05201"/> the yacht <emph>The Belle of Newport</emph> and then someone proposed
<lb n="05202"/> one great game for a finish.</p>
<lb n="05203"/> <p>The piano had stopped; Villona must have gone up on deck.
<lb n="05204"/> It was a terrible game. They stopped just before the end of it to
<lb n="05205"/> drink for luck. Jimmy understood that the game lay between
<lb n="05206"/> Routh and Ségouin. What excitement! Jimmy was excited too;
<lb n="05207"/> he would lose, of course. How much had he written away? The
<lb n="05208"/> men rose to their feet to play the last tricks, talking and
<lb n="05209"/> gesticulating. Routh won. The cabin shook with the young
<lb n="05210"/> men's cheering and the cards were bundled together. They be=
<lb n="05211"/> gan then to gather in what they had won. Farley and Jimmy
<lb n="05212"/> were the heaviest losers.</p>
<lb n="05213"/> <p>He knew that he would regret in the morning but at present
<lb n="05214"/> he was glad of the rest, glad of the dark stupor that would
<lb n="05215"/> cover up his folly. He leaned his elbows on the table and rested
<lb n="05216"/> his head between his hands, counting the beats of his temples.
<lb n="05217"/> The cabin door opened and he saw the Hungarian standing in a
<lb n="05218"/> shaft of grey light:
<lb n="05219"/> <said who="">―</said>Daybreak, gentlemen!</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->