<div n="06" type="story"><lb n="06000"/> <head rend="italics">Two Gallants</head>
<lb n="06001"/> <p>The grey warm evening of August had descended upon the
<lb n="06002"/> city and a mild warm air, a memory of summer, circulated in
<lb n="06003"/> the streets. The streets, shuttered for the repose of Sunday,
<lb n="06004"/> swarmed with a gaily coloured crowd. Like illumined pearls
<lb n="06005"/> the lamps shone from the summits of their tall poles upon the
<lb n="06006"/> living texture below which, changing shape and hue unceas=
<lb n="06007"/> ingly, sent up into the warm grey evening air an unchanging
<lb n="06008"/> unceasing murmur.</p>
<lb n="06009"/> <p>Two young men came down the hill of Rutland Square. One
<lb n="06010"/> of them was just bringing a long monologue to a close. The
<lb n="06011"/> other, who walked on the verge of the path and was at times
<lb n="06012"/> obliged to step on to the road owing to his companion's
<lb n="06013"/> rudeness, wore an amused listening face. He was squat and
<lb n="06014"/> ruddy. A yachting cap was shoved far back from his forehead
<lb n="06015"/> and the narrative to which he listened made constant waves of
<lb n="06016"/> expression break forth over his face from the corners of his
<lb n="06017"/> nose and eyes and mouth. Little jets of wheezing laughter
<lb n="06018"/> followed one another out of his convulsed body. His eyes,
<lb n="06019"/> twinkling with cunning enjoyment, glanced at every moment
<lb n="06020"/> towards his companion's face. Once or twice he rearranged the
<lb n="06021"/> light waterproof which he had slung over one shoulder in
<lb n="06022"/> toreador fashion. His breeches, his white rubber shoes and his
<lb n="06023"/> jauntily slung waterproof expressed youth. But his figure fell
<lb n="06024"/> into rotundity at the waist, his hair was scant and grey and his
<lb n="06025"/> face, when the waves of expression had passed over it, had a
<lb n="06026"/> ravaged look.</p>
<lb n="06027"/> <p>When he was quite sure that the narrative had ended he
<lb n="06028"/> laughed noiselessly for fully half a minute. Then he said:
  <lb n="06029"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Well! ... That takes the biscuit!</said></p>
<lb n="06030"/> <p>His voice seemed winnowed of vigour; and to enforce his
<lb n="06031"/> words he added with humour:
<lb n="06032"/> <said who="Lenehan">―That takes the solitary, unique and, if I may so call it,
<lb n="06033"/> <emph>recherché</emph> biscuit!</said></p>
<lb n="06034"/> <p>He became serious and silent when he had said this. His
<lb n="06035"/> tongue was tired for he had been talking all the afternoon in a
<lb n="06036"/> publichouse in Dorset Street. Most people considered <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>
<lb n="06037"/> a leech but in spite of this reputation his adroitness and elo=
<lb n="06038"/> quence had always prevented his friends from forming any
<lb n="06039"/> general policy against him. He had a brave manner of coming
<lb n="06040"/> up to a party of them in a bar and of holding himself nimbly at
<lb n="06041"/> the borders of the company until he was included in a round.
<lb n="06042"/> He was a sporting vagrant armed with a vast stock of stories,
<lb n="06043"/> limericks and riddles. He was insensitive to all kinds of dis=
<lb n="06044"/> courtesy. No-one knew how he achieved the stern task of living
<lb n="06045"/> but his name was vaguely associated with racing tissues.
<lb n="06046"/> <said who="Lenehan">―And where did you pick her up, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>? </said>he asked.</p>
  <lb n="06047"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> ran his tongue swiftly along his upper lip.
<lb n="06048"/> <said who="Corley">―One night, man, he said, I was going along Dame Street and
<lb n="06049"/> I spotted a fine tart under Waterhouse's clock and said good=
<lb n="06050"/> night, you know. So we went for a walk round by the canal
<lb n="06051"/> and she told me she was a slavey in a house in Baggot Street. I
<lb n="06052"/> put my arm round her and squeezed her a bit that night. Then
<lb n="06053"/> next Sunday, man, I met her by appointment. We went out to
<lb n="06054"/> Donnybrook and I brought her into a field there. She told me
<lb n="06055"/> she used to go with a dairyman. ... It was fine, man. Cigarettes
<lb n="06056"/> every night she'd bring me and paying the tram out and back.
<lb n="06057"/> And one night she brought me two bloody fine cigars - O, the
<lb n="06058"/> real cheese, you know, that the old fellow used to smoke. ... I
<lb n="06059"/> was afraid, man, she'd get in the family way. But she's up to
<lb n="06060"/> the dodge.</said>
<lb n="06061"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Maybe she thinks you'll marry her, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>.
  <lb n="06062"/> <said who="Corley">―I told her I was out of a job,</said> said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>. <said who="Corley">I told her I was in
<lb n="06063"/> Pim's. She doesn't know my name. I was too hairy to tell her
<lb n="06064"/> that. But she thinks I'm a bit of class, you know.</said></p>
  <lb n="06065"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> laughed again noiselessly.
  <lb n="06066"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Of all the good ones ever I heard,</said> he said,<said who="Lenehan"> that emphatically
<lb n="06067"/> takes the biscuit.</said></p>
  <lb n="06068"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s stride acknowledged the compliment. The swing of
<lb n="06069"/> his burly body made his friend execute a few light skips from
  <lb n="06070"/> the path to the roadway and back again. <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> was the son of
<lb n="06071"/> an inspector of police and he had inherited his father's frame
<lb n="06072"/> and gait. He walked with his hands by his sides, holding him=
<lb n="06073"/> self erect and swaying his head from side to side. His head was
<lb n="06074"/> large, globular and oily, it sweated in all weathers and his large
<lb n="06075"/> round hat, set upon it sideways, looked like a bulb which had
<lb n="06076"/> grown out of another. He always stared straight before him as
<lb n="06077"/> if he were on parade and when he wished to gaze after someone
<lb n="06078"/> in the street it was necessary for him to move his body from the
<lb n="06079"/> hips. At present he was about town. Whenever any job was
<lb n="06080"/> vacant a friend was always ready to give him the hard word.
<lb n="06081"/> He was often to be seen walking with policemen in plain
<lb n="06082"/> clothes, talking earnestly. He knew the inner side of all affairs
<lb n="06083"/> and was fond of delivering final judgments. He spoke without
<lb n="06084"/> listening to the speech of his companions. His conversation was
<lb n="06085"/> mainly about himself: what he had said to such a person and
<lb n="06086"/> what such a person had said to him and what he had said to
<lb n="06087"/> settle the matter. When he reported these dialogues he aspir=
<lb n="06088"/> ated the first letter of his name after the manner of Florentines.</p>
  <lb n="06089"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> offered his friend a cigarette. As the two young men
  <lb n="06090"/> walked on through the crowd <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> occasionally turned to
  <lb n="06091"/> smile at some of the passing girls but <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>'s gaze was fixed
<lb n="06092"/> on the large faint moon circled with a double halo. He watched
<lb n="06093"/> earnestly the passing of the grey web of twilight across its face.
<lb n="06094"/> At length he said:
  <lb n="06095"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Well, ... tell me, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, I suppose you'll be able to pull it off
<lb n="06096"/> all right, eh?</said></p>
<lb n="06097"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> closed one eye expressively as an answer.
  <lb n="06098"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Is she game for that? </said>asked <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> dubiously.<said who="Lenehan"> You never
<lb n="06099"/> can know women.</said>
  <lb n="06100"/> <said who="Corley">―She's all right, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>. <said who="Corley">I know the way to get around
<lb n="06101"/> her, man. She's a bit gone on me.</said>
  <lb n="06102"/> <said who="Lenehan">―You're what I call a gay Lothario, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>. <said who="Lenehan">And the
<lb n="06103"/> proper kind of a Lothario, too!</said></p>
<lb n="06104"/> <p>A shade of mockery relieved the servility of his manner. To
<lb n="06105"/> save himself he had the habit of leaving his flattery open to the
  <lb n="06106"/> interpretation of raillery. But <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> had not a subtle mind.
  <lb n="06107"/> <said who="Corley">―There's nothing to touch a good slavey,</said> he affirmed. <said who="Corley">Take
<lb n="06108"/> my tip for it.</said>
  <lb n="06109"/> <said who="Lenehan">―By one who has tried them all, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>.
  <lb n="06110"/> <said who="Corley">―First I used to go with girls, you know, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> un=
<lb n="06111"/> bosoming, <said who="Corley">girls off the South Circular. I used to take them out,
<lb n="06112"/> man, on the tram somewhere and pay the tram or take them to
<lb n="06113"/> a band or a play at the theatre or buy them chocolate and
<lb n="06114"/> sweets or something that way. I used to spend money on them
  <lb n="06115"/> right enough, </said>he added in a convincing tone, as if he were
<lb n="06116"/> conscious of being disbelieved.</p>
  <lb n="06117"/> <p>But <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> could well believe it; he nodded gravely.
  <lb n="06118"/> <said who="Lenehan">―I know that game, </said>he said, <said who="Lenehan">and it's a mug's game.</said>
  <lb n="06119"/> <said who="Corley">―And damn the thing I ever got out of it, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>.
  <lb n="06120"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Ditto here, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>.
  <lb n="06121"/> <said who="Corley">―Only off of one of them, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>.</p>
<lb n="06122"/> <p>He moistened his upper lip by running his tongue along it.
<lb n="06123"/> The recollection brightened his eyes. He too gazed at the pale
<lb n="06124"/> disc of the moon, now nearly veiled, and seemed to meditate.
  <lb n="06125"/> <said who="Corley">―She was ... a bit of all right, </said>he said regretfully.</p>
<lb n="06126"/> <p>He was silent again. Then he added:
<lb n="06127"/> <said who="Corley">―She's on the turf now. I saw her driving down Earl Street
<lb n="06128"/> one night with two fellows with her on a car.</said>
  <lb n="06129"/> <said who="Lenehan">―I suppose that's your doing, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>.
  <lb n="06130"/> <said who="Corley">―There was others at her before me, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> philosophi=
<lb n="06131"/> cally.</p>
  <lb n="06132"/> <p>This time <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> was inclined to disbelieve. He shook his
<lb n="06133"/> head to and fro and smiled.
  <lb n="06134"/> <said who="Lenehan">―You know you can't kid me, </said><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, he said.
  <lb n="06135"/> <said who="Corley">―Honest to God! </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>. <said who="Corley">Didn't she tell me herself?</said></p>
  <lb n="06136"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> made a tragic gesture.
  <lb n="06137"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Base betrayer! </said>he said.</p>
<lb n="06138"/> <p>As they passed along by the railings of Trinity College
  <lb n="06139"/> <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> skipped out into the road and peered up at the clock:
  <lb n="06140"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Twenty after, </said>he said.
  <lb n="06141"/> <said who="Corley">―Time enough, </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>. <said who="Corley">She'll be there all right. I always
<lb n="06142"/> let her wait a bit.</said></p>
  <lb n="06143"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> laughed quietly.
<lb n="06144"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Ecod, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, you know how to take them, </said。he said.
  <lb n="06145"/> <said who="Corley">―I'm up to all their little tricks, </said><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> confessed.
  <lb n="06146"/> <said who="Lenehan">―But tell me, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> again, <said who="Lenehan">are you sure you can bring
<lb n="06147"/> it off all right? You know it's a ticklish job. They're damn close
<lb n="06148"/> on that point. Eh? ... What?</said></p>
<lb n="06149"/> <p>His bright small eyes searched his companion's face for
  <lb n="06150"/> reassurance. <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> swung his head to and fro as if to toss aside
<lb n="06151"/> an insistent insect, and his brows gathered.
  <lb n="06152"/> <said who="Corley">―I'll pull it off, </said>he said. <said who="Corley">Leave it to me, can't you?</said></p>
  <lb n="06153"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> said no more. He did not wish to ruffle his friend's
<lb n="06154"/> temper, to be sent to the devil and told that his advice was not
  <lb n="06155"/> wanted. A little tact was necessary. But <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s brow was
<lb n="06156"/> soon smooth again. His thoughts were running another way.
  <lb n="06157"/> <said who="Corley">―She's a fine decent tart, </said>he said with appreciation, <said who="Corley">that's
<lb n="06158"/> what she is.</said></p>
<lb n="06159"/> <p>They walked along Nassau Street and then turned into
<lb n="06160"/> Kildare Street. Not far from the porch of the club a harpist
<lb n="06161"/> stood in the roadway playing to a little ring of listeners. He
<lb n="06162"/> plucked at the wires heedlessly, glancing quickly from time to
<lb n="06163"/> time at the face of each newcomer and from time to time,
<lb n="06164"/> wearily also, at the sky. His harp too, heedless that her
<lb n="06165"/> coverings had fallen about her knees, seemed weary alike of the
<lb n="06166"/> eyes of strangers and of her master's hands. One hand played in
<lb n="06167"/> the bass the melody of <emph>Silent, O Moyle</emph> while the other hand
<lb n="06168"/> careered in the treble after each group of notes. The notes of
<lb n="06169"/> the air throbbed deep and full.</p>
<lb n="06170"/> <p>The two young men walked up the street without speaking,
<lb n="06171"/> the mournful music following them. When they reached Ste=
<lb n="06172"/> phen's Green they crossed the road. Here the noise of trams,
<lb n="06173"/> the lights and the crowd released them from their silence.
  <lb n="06174"/> <said who="Corley">―There she is! </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>.</p>
<lb n="06175"/> <p>At the corner of Hume Street a young woman was standing.
<lb n="06176"/> She wore a blue dress and a white sailor hat. She stood on the
  <lb n="06177"/> curbstone swinging a sunshade in one hand. <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> grew
<lb n="06178"/> lively:
<lb n="06179"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Let's have a squint at her, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, </said>he said.</p>
  <lb n="06180"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> glanced sideways at his friend and an unpleasant grin
<lb n="06181"/> appeared on his face.
  <lb n="06182"/> <said who="Corley">―Are you trying to get inside me? </said>he asked.
  <lb n="06183"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Damn it! </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> boldly, <said who="Lenehan">I don't want an introduction.
<lb n="06184"/> All I want is to have a look at her. I'm not going to eat her.</said>
  <lb n="06185"/> <said who="Corley">―O ... A look at her? </said>said <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, more amiably. <said who="Corley">Well. ... I'll
<lb n="06186"/> tell you what. I'll go over and talk to her and you can pass by.</said>
  <lb n="06187"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Right! </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="06188"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> had already thrown one leg over the chains when
  <lb n="06189"/> <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> called out:
<lb n="06190"/> <said who="Lenehan">―And after? Where will we meet?</said>
  <lb n="06191"/> <said who="Corley">―Half ten, </said>answered <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>, bringing over his other leg.
<lb n="06192"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Where?</said>
<lb n="06193"/> <said who="Corley">―Corner of Merrion Street. We'll be coming back.</said>
  <lb n="06194"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Work it all right now, </said>said <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> in farewell.</p>
  <lb n="06195"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> did not answer. He sauntered across the road sway=
<lb n="06196"/> ing his head from side to side. His bulk, his easy pace and the
<lb n="06197"/> solid sound of his boots had something of the conqueror in
<lb n="06198"/> them. He approached the young woman and, without saluting,
<lb n="06199"/> began at once to converse with her. She swung her sunshade
<lb n="06200"/> more quickly and executed half turns on her heels. Once or
<lb n="06201"/> twice when he spoke to her at close quarters she laughed and
<lb n="06202"/> bent her head.</p>
  <lb n="06203"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> observed them for a few minutes. Then he walked
<lb n="06204"/> rapidly along beside the chains to some distance and crossed
<lb n="06205"/> the road obliquely. As he approached Hume Street corner he
<lb n="06206"/> found the air heavily scented and his eyes made a swift anxious
<lb n="06207"/> scrutiny of the young woman's appearance. She had her Sun=
<lb n="06208"/> day finery on. Her blue serge skirt was held at the waist by a
<lb n="06209"/> belt of black leather. The great silver buckle of her belt seemed
<lb n="06210"/> to depress the centre of her body, catching the light stuff of her
<lb n="06211"/> white blouse like a clip. She wore a short black jacket with
<lb n="06212"/> mother-of-pearl buttons and a ragged black boa. The ends of
<lb n="06213"/> her tulle collarette had been carefully disordered and a big
<lb n="06214"/> bunch of red flowers was pinned in her bosom, stems upwards.
  <lb n="06215"/> <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName>'s eyes noted approvingly her stout short muscular
<lb n="06216"/> body. Frank rude health glowed in her face, on her fat red
<lb n="06217"/> cheeks and in her unabashed blue eyes. Her features were
<lb n="06218"/> blunt. She had broad nostrils, a straggling mouth which lay
<lb n="06219"/> open in a contented leer and two projecting front teeth. As he
  <lb n="06220"/> passed <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> took off his cap and after about ten seconds
  <lb n="06221"/> <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> returned a salute to the air. This he did by raising his
<lb n="06222"/> hand vaguely and pensively changing the angle of position of
<lb n="06223"/> his hat.</p>
  <lb n="06224"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> walked as far as the Shelbourne Hotel where he
<lb n="06225"/> halted and waited. After waiting for a little time he saw them
<lb n="06226"/> coming towards him and when they turned to the right he
<lb n="06227"/> followed them, stepping lightly in his white shoes, down one
<lb n="06228"/> side of Merrion Square. As he walked on slowly, timing his
  <lb n="06229"/> pace to theirs, he watched <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s head which turned at every
<lb n="06230"/> moment towards the young woman's face like a big ball
<lb n="06231"/> revolving on a pivot. He kept the pair in view until he had seen
<lb n="06232"/> them climbing the stairs of the Donnybrook tram; then he
<lb n="06233"/> turned about and went back the way he had come.</p>
<lb n="06234"/> <p>Now that he was alone his face looked older. His gaiety
<lb n="06235"/> seemed to forsake him and, as he came by the railings of the
<lb n="06236"/> Duke's Lawn, he allowed his hand to run along them. The air
<lb n="06237"/> which the harpist had played began to control his movements.
<lb n="06238"/> His softly padded feet played the melody while his fingers
<lb n="06239"/> swept a scale of variations idly along the railings after each
<lb n="06240"/> group of notes.</p>
<lb n="06241"/> <p>He walked listlessly round Stephen's Green and then down
<lb n="06242"/> Grafton Street. Though his eyes took note of many elements of
<lb n="06243"/> the crowd through which he passed they did so morosely. He
<lb n="06244"/> found trivial all that was meant to charm him and did not
<lb n="06245"/> answer the glances which invited him to be bold. He knew that
<lb n="06246"/> he would have to speak a great deal, to invent and to amuse,
<lb n="06247"/> and his brain and throat were too dry for such a task. The
<lb n="06248"/> problem of how he could pass the hours till he met <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>
<lb n="06249"/> again troubled him a little. He could think of no way of passing
<lb n="06250"/> them but to keep on walking. He turned to the left when he
<lb n="06251"/> came to the corner of Rutland Square and felt more at ease in
<lb n="06252"/> the dark quiet street, the sombre look of which suited his
<lb n="06253"/> mood. He paused at last before the window of a poorlooking
<lb n="06254"/> shop over which the words <emph>Refreshment Bar</emph> were printed in
<lb n="06255"/> white letters. On the glass of the window were two flying
<lb n="06256"/> inscriptions: <emph>Ginger Beer</emph> and <emph>Ginger Ale.</emph> A cut ham was
<lb n="06257"/> exposed on a great blue dish while near it on a plate lay a
<lb n="06258"/> segment of very light plumpudding. He eyed this food earnestly
<lb n="06259"/> for some time and then, after glancing warily up and down the
<lb n="06260"/> street, went into the shop quickly.</p>
<lb n="06261"/> <p>He was hungry for, except some biscuits which he had asked
<lb n="06262"/> two grudging curates to bring him, he had eaten nothing since
<lb n="06263"/> breakfast-time. He sat down at an uncovered wooden table
<lb n="06264"/> opposite two work girls and a mechanic. A slatternly girl
<lb n="06265"/> waited on him.
  <lb n="06266"/> <said who="Lenehan">―How much is a plate of peas? </said>he asked.
  <lb n="06267"/> <said who="waitress">―Three halfpence, sir, </said>said the girl.
  <lb n="06268"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Bring me a plate of peas, </said>he said, <said who="Lenehan">and a bottle of ginger beer.</said></p>
<lb n="06269"/> <p>He spoke roughly in order to belie his air of gentility for his
<lb n="06270"/> entry had been followed by a pause of talk. His face was
<lb n="06271"/> heated. To appear natural he pushed his cap back on his head
<lb n="06272"/> and planted his elbows on the table. The mechanic and the two
<lb n="06273"/> work girls examined him point by point before resuming their
<lb n="06274"/> conversation in a subdued voice. The girl brought him a plate
<lb n="06275"/> of hot grocer's peas seasoned with pepper and vinegar, a fork
<lb n="06276"/> and his ginger beer. He ate his food greedily and found it so
<lb n="06277"/> good that he made a note of the shop mentally. When he had
<lb n="06278"/> eaten all the peas he sipped his ginger beer and sat for some
  <lb n="06279"/> time thinking of <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s adventure. In his imagination he
<lb n="06280"/> beheld the pair of lovers walking along some dark road, he
  <lb n="06281"/> heard <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s voice in deep energetic gallantries and saw again
<lb n="06282"/> the leer of the young woman's mouth. This vision made him
<lb n="06283"/> feel keenly his own poverty of purse and spirit. He was tired of
<lb n="06284"/> knocking about, of pulling the devil by the tail, of shifts and
<lb n="06285"/> intrigues. <said who="Lenehan" aloud="false" direct="false">He would be thirty-one in November. Would he
<lb n="06286"/> never get a good job? Would he never have a home of his own?
<lb n="06287"/> He thought how pleasant it would be to have a warm fire to sit
<lb n="06288"/> by and a good dinner to sit down to. He had walked the streets
<lb n="06289"/> long enough with friends and with girls. He knew what those
  <lb n="06290"/> friends were worth: he knew the girls too.</said> Experience had
<lb n="06291"/> embittered his heart against the world. But all hope had not left
<lb n="06292"/> him. He felt better after having eaten than he had felt before,
<lb n="06293"/> less weary of his life, less vanquished in spirit. He might yet be
<lb n="06294"/> able to settle down in some snug corner and live happily if he
<lb n="06295"/> could only come across some good simpleminded girl with a
<lb n="06296"/> little of the ready.</p>
<lb n="06297"/> <p>He paid twopence halfpenny to the slatternly girl and went
<lb n="06298"/> out of the shop to begin his wandering again. He went into
<lb n="06299"/> Capel Street and walked along towards the City Hall. Then he
<lb n="06300"/> turned into Dame Street. At the corner of George's Street he
<lb n="06301"/> met two friends of his and stopped to converse with them. He
<lb n="06302"/> was glad that he could rest from all his walking. His friends
  <lb n="06303"/> asked him <said who ="Lenehan's friends" direct="false">had he seen <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> and what was the latest.</said> He
  <lb n="06304"/> replied that he had spent the day with <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>. His friends
<lb n="06305"/> talked very little. They looked vacantly after some figures in
<lb n="06306"/> the crowd and sometimes made a critical remark. One said that<said who ="Lenehan's friend" direct="false">
  <lb n="06307"/> he had seen <persName xml:id="mc">Mac</persName> an hour before in Westmoreland Street.</said> At
<lb n="06308"/> this <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> said that <said who ="Lenehan" direct="false">he had been with <persName xml:id="mc">Mac</persName> the night before
  <lb n="06309"/> in Egan's.</said> The young man who had seen <persName xml:id="mc">Mac</persName> in Westmoreland
  <lb n="06310"/> Street asked <said who ="Lenehan's friend" direct="false">was it true that <persName xml:id="mc">Mac</persName> had won a bit over a billiard
  <lb n="06311"/> match.</said> <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> did not know: he said that <said who ="Lenehan" direct="false">Holohan had stood
  <lb n="06312"/> them drinks in Egan's.</said></p>
<lb n="06313"/> <p>He left his friends at a quarter to ten and went up George's
<lb n="06314"/> Street. He turned to the left at the City Markets and walked on
<lb n="06315"/> into Grafton Street. The crowd of girls and young men had
<lb n="06316"/> thinned and on his way up the street he heard many groups and
<lb n="06317"/> couples bidding one another goodnight. He went as far as the
<lb n="06318"/> clock of the College of Surgeons: it was on the stroke of ten. He
<lb n="06319"/> set off briskly along the northern side of the Green, hurrying
  <lb n="06320"/> for fear <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> should return too soon. When he reached the
<lb n="06321"/> corner of Merrion Street he took his stand in the shadow of a
<lb n="06322"/> lamp and brought out one of the cigarettes which he had
<lb n="06323"/> reserved and lit it. He leaned against the lamppost and kept his
<lb n="06324"/> gaze fixed on the part from which he expected to see <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>
<lb n="06325"/> and the young woman return.</p>
<lb n="06326"/> <p>His mind became active again. He wondered had <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>
<lb n="06327"/> managed it successfully. He wondered if he had asked her yet
<lb n="06328"/> or if he would leave it to the last. He suffered all the pangs and
<lb n="06329"/> thrills of his friend's situation as well as those of his own. But
  <lb n="06330"/> the memory of <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>'s slowly revolving head calmed him
  <lb n="06331"/> somewhat: he was sure <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> would pull it off all right. All at
  <lb n="06332"/> once the idea struck him that perhaps <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> had seen her
<lb n="06333"/> home by another way and given him the slip. His eyes searched
<lb n="06334"/> the street: there was no sign of them. Yet it was surely half an
<lb n="06335"/> hour since he had seen the clock of the College of Surgeons.
  <lb n="06336"/> <said who ="Lenehan" aloud="false">Would <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> do a thing like that? </said>He lit his last cigarette and
<lb n="06337"/> began to smoke it nervously. He strained his eyes as each tram
<lb n="06338"/> stopped at the far corner of the square. They must have gone
<lb n="06339"/> home by another way. The paper of his cigarette broke and he
<lb n="06340"/> flung it into the road with a curse.</p>
<lb n="06341"/> <p>Suddenly he saw them coming towards him. He started with
<lb n="06342"/> delight and, keeping close to his lamppost, tried to read the
<lb n="06343"/> result in their walk. They were walking quickly, the young
  <lb n="06344"/> woman taking quick short steps while <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> kept beside her
<lb n="06345"/> with his long stride. They did not seem to be speaking. An
<lb n="06346"/> intimation of the result pricked him like the point of a sharp
  <lb n="06347"/> instrument. He knew <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> would fail: he knew it was no go.</p>
<lb n="06348"/> <p>They turned down Baggot Street and he followed them at
<lb n="06349"/> once, taking the other footpath. When they stopped he stopped
<lb n="06350"/> too. They talked for a few moments and then the young
<lb n="06351"/> woman went down the steps into the area of a house. <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>
<lb n="06352"/> remained standing at the edge of the path, a little distance from
<lb n="06353"/> the front steps. Some minutes passed. Then the halldoor was
<lb n="06354"/> opened slowly and cautiously. A woman came running down
  <lb n="06355"/> the front steps and coughed. <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> turned and went towards
<lb n="06356"/> her. His broad figure hid hers from view for a few seconds and
<lb n="06357"/> then she reappeared running up the steps. The door closed on
  <lb n="06358"/> her and <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> began to walk swiftly towards Stephen's Green.</p>
  <lb n="06359"/> <p><persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> hurried on in the same direction. Some drops of
<lb n="06360"/> light rain fell. He took them as a warning and, glancing back
<lb n="06361"/> towards the house which the young woman had entered to see
<lb n="06362"/> that he was not observed, he ran eagerly across the road.
<lb n="06363"/> Anxiety and his swift run made him pant. He called out:
  <lb n="06364"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Hello, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>!</said></p>
  <lb n="06365"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> turned his head to see who had called him and then
  <lb n="06366"/> continued walking as before. <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> ran after him, settling
<lb n="06367"/> the waterproof on his shoulders with one hand.
  <lb n="06368"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Hello, <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName>! </said>he cried again.</p>
<lb n="06369"/> <p>He came level with his friend and looked keenly in his face.
<lb n="06370"/> He could see nothing there.
<lb n="06371"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Well?</said> he said. <said who="Lenehan">Did it come off?</said></p>
<lb n="06372"/> <p>They had reached the corner of Ely Place. Still without
  <lb n="06373"/> answering <persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> swerved to the left and went up the side
<lb n="06374"/> street. His features were composed in stern calm. <persName xml:id="len">Lenehan</persName> kept
<lb n="06375"/> up with his friend, breathing uneasily. He was baffled and a
<lb n="06376"/> note of menace pierced through his voice.
  <lb n="06377"/> <said who="Lenehan">―Can't you tell us? </said>he said. <said who="Lenehan">Did you try her?</said></p>
  <lb n="06378"/> <p><persName xml:id="cy">Corley</persName> halted at the first lamp and stared grimly before him.
<lb n="06379"/> Then with a grave gesture he extended a hand towards the light
<lb n="06380"/> and, smiling, opened it slowly to the gaze of his disciple. A
<lb n="06381"/> small gold coin shone in the palm.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
