<div n="07" type="story"><lb n="07000"/> <head rend="italics">The Boarding House</head>
  <lb n="07001"/> <p><persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> was a butcher's daughter. She was a woman
<lb n="07002"/> who was quite able to keep things to herself: a determined
<lb n="07003"/> woman. She had married her father's foreman and opened a
<lb n="07004"/> butcher's shop near Spring Gardens. But as soon as his father=
  <lb n="07005"/> in=law was dead <persName xml:id="mmy">Mr Mooney</persName> began to go to the devil. He
<lb n="07006"/> drank, plundered the till, ran headlong into debt. It was no use
<lb n="07007"/> making him take the pledge: he was sure to break out again a
<lb n="07008"/> few days after. By fighting his wife in the presence of customers
<lb n="07009"/> and by buying bad meat he ruined his business. One night he
<lb n="07010"/> went for his wife with the cleaver and she had to sleep in a
<lb n="07011"/> neighbour's house.</p>
<lb n="07012"/> <p>After that they lived apart. She went to the priests and got a
<lb n="07013"/> separation from him with care of the children. She would give
<lb n="07014"/> him neither money nor food nor houseroom and so he was
<lb n="07015"/> obliged to enlist himself as a sheriff's man. He was a shabby
<lb n="07016"/> stooped little drunkard with a white face and a white mous=
<lb n="07017"/> tache and white eyebrows, pencilled above his little eyes, which
<lb n="07018"/> were pinkveined and raw; and all day long he sat in the bailiffs'
  <lb n="07019"/> room waiting to be put on a job. <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName>, who had taken
<lb n="07020"/> what remained of her money out of the butcher business and
<lb n="07021"/> set up a boarding house in Hardwicke Street, was a big
<lb n="07022"/> imposing woman. Her house had a floating population made
<lb n="07023"/> up of tourists from Liverpool and the Isle of Man and occa=
<lb n="07024"/> sionally <emph>artistes</emph> from the musichalls. Its resident population
<lb n="07025"/> was made up of clerks from the city. She governed her house
<lb n="07026"/> cunningly and firmly, knew when to give credit, when to be
<lb n="07027"/> stern and when to let things pass. All the resident young men
<lb n="07028"/> spoke of her as <emph>The Madam</emph>.</p>
  <lb n="07029"/> <p><persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName>'s young men paid fifteen shillings a week for
<lb n="07030"/> board and lodgings (beer or stout at dinner excluded). They
<lb n="07031"/> shared in common tastes and occupations and for this reason
<lb n="07032"/> they were very chummy with one another. They discussed with
<lb n="07033"/> one another the chances of favourites and outsiders. <persName xml:id="jmo">Jack
  <lb n="07034"/> Mooney</persName>, the Madam's son, who was clerk to a commission
<lb n="07035"/> agent in Fleet Street, had the reputation of being a hard case.
<lb n="07036"/> He was fond of using soldiers' obscenities: usually he came
<lb n="07037"/> home in the small hours. When he met his friends he had
<lb n="07038"/> always a good one to tell them and he was always sure to be on
<lb n="07039"/> to a good thing, that is to say, a likely horse or a likely <emph>artiste.</emph>
<lb n="07040"/> He was also handy with the mits and sang comic songs. On
<lb n="07041"/> Sunday nights there would often be a reunion in <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName>'s
<lb n="07042"/> front drawingroom. The musichall <emph>artistes</emph> would oblige; and
  <lb n="07043"/> <persName xml:id="ms">Sheridan</persName> played waltzes and polkas and vamped accompani=
  <lb n="07044"/> ments. <persName xml:id="pm">Polly Mooney</persName>, the Madam's daughter, would also sing.
<lb n="07045"/> She sang:</p>
<lb n="07046"/> <p><emph>I'm a .... naughty girl.
<lb n="07047"/> You needn't sham:
<lb n="07048"/> You know I am.</emph></p>
  <lb n="07049"/> <p><persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> was a slim girl of nineteen; she had light soft hair and
<lb n="07050"/> a small full mouth. Her eyes, which were grey with a shade of
<lb n="07051"/> green through them, had a habit of glancing upwards when she
<lb n="07052"/> spoke with anyone, which made her look like a little perverse
  <lb n="07053"/> madonna. <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> had first sent her daughter to be a
<lb n="07054"/> typewriter in a cornfactor's office but, as a disreputable sher=
<lb n="07055"/> iff's man used to come every other day to the office asking to
<lb n="07056"/> be allowed to say a word to his daughter, she had taken her
<lb n="07057"/> daughter home again and set her to do housework. As <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>
<lb n="07058"/> was very lively the intention was to give her the run of the
<lb n="07059"/> young men. Besides, young men like to feel that there is a
  <lb n="07060"/> young woman not very far away. <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>, of course, flirted with
  <lb n="07061"/> the young men but <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName>, who was a shrewd judge,
<lb n="07062"/> knew that the young men were only passing the time away:
<lb n="07063"/> none of them meant business. Things went on so for a long
  <lb n="07064"/> time and <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> began to think of sending <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> back to
<lb n="07065"/> typewriting when she noticed that something was going on be=
<lb n="07066"/> tween Polly and one of the young men. She watched the pair
<lb n="07067"/> and kept her own counsel.</p>
  <lb n="07068"/> <p><persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> knew that she was being watched but still her mother's
<lb n="07069"/> persistent silence could not be misunderstood. There had been
<lb n="07070"/> no open complicity between mother and daughter, no open
<lb n="07071"/> understanding but, though people in the house began to talk of
  <lb n="07072"/> the affair, still <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> did not intervene. <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> began to
<lb n="07073"/> grow a little strange in her manner and the young man was
<lb n="07074"/> evidently perturbed. At last, when she judged it to be the right
  <lb n="07075"/> moment, <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> intervened. She dealt with moral prob=
<lb n="07076"/> lems as a cleaver deals with meat: and in this case she had made
<lb n="07077"/> up her mind.</p>
<lb n="07078"/> <p>It was a bright Sunday morning of early summer, promising
<lb n="07079"/> heat, but with a fresh breeze blowing. All the windows of the
<lb n="07080"/> boarding house were open and the lace curtains ballooned
<lb n="07081"/> gently towards the street beneath the raised sashes. The belfry
<lb n="07082"/> of George's church sent out constant peals and worshippers,
<lb n="07083"/> singly or in groups, traversed the little circus before the church,
<lb n="07084"/> revealing their purpose by their self-contained demeanour no
<lb n="07085"/> less than by the little volumes in their gloved hands. Breakfast
<lb n="07086"/> was over in the boarding house and the table of the breakfast
<lb n="07087"/> room was covered with plates on which lay yellow streaks of
<lb n="07088"/> eggs with morsels of bacon fat and bacon rind. <persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName>
<lb n="07089"/> sat in the straw armchair and watched the servant, <persName xml:id="ma">Mary</persName>,
  <lb n="07090"/> remove the breakfast things. She made <persName xml:id="ma">Mary</persName> collect the crusts
<lb n="07091"/> and pieces of broken bread to help to make Tuesday's bread
<lb n="07092"/> pudding. When the table was cleared, the broken bread col=
<lb n="07093"/> lected, the sugar and butter safe under lock and key, she began
<lb n="07094"/> to reconstruct the interview which she had had the night before
  <lb n="07095"/> with <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>. Things were as she had suspected: she had been
  <lb n="07096"/> frank in her questions and <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> had been frank in her answers.
<lb n="07097"/> Both had been somewhat awkward, of course. She had been
<lb n="07098"/> made awkward by her not wishing to receive the news in too
<lb n="07099"/> cavalier a fashion or to seem to have connived and <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> had
<lb n="07100"/> been made awkward not merely because allusions of that kind
<lb n="07101"/> always made her awkward but also because she did not wish it
<lb n="07102"/> to be thought that in her wise innocence she had divined the
<lb n="07103"/> intention behind her mother's tolerance.</p>
  <lb n="07104"/> <p><persName xml:id="my">Mrs Mooney</persName> glanced instinctively at the little gilt clock on
<lb n="07105"/> the mantelpiece as soon as she had become aware through her
<lb n="07106"/> revery that the bells of George's church had stopped ringing. It
<lb n="07107"/> was seventeen minutes past eleven: she would have lots of time
  <lb n="07108"/> to have the matter out with <persName xml:id="bd">Mr Doran</persName> and then catch short
<lb n="07109"/> twelve at Marlborough Street. She was sure she would win. To
<lb n="07110"/> begin with she had all the weight of social opinion on her side:
<lb n="07111"/> she was an outraged mother. She had allowed him to live
<lb n="07112"/> beneath her roof, assuming that he was a man of honour, and
<lb n="07113"/> he had simply abused her hospitality. He was thirty-four or
<lb n="07114"/> thirty-five years of age so that youth could not be pleaded as
<lb n="07115"/> his excuse; nor could ignorance be his excuse since he was a
<lb n="07116"/> man who had seen something of the world. He had simply
  <lb n="07117"/> taken advantage of <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>'s youth and inexperience: that was
<lb n="07118"/> evident. The question was: What reparation would he make?</p>
<lb n="07119"/> <p>There must be reparation made in such cases. It is all very
<lb n="07120"/> well for the man: he can go his ways as if nothing had
<lb n="07121"/> happened, having had his moment of pleasure, but the girl has
<lb n="07122"/> to bear the brunt. Some mothers would be content to patch up
<lb n="07123"/> such an affair for a sum of money: she had known cases of it.
<lb n="07124"/> But she would not do so. For her only one reparation could
<lb n="07125"/> make up for the loss of her daughter's honour: marriage.</p>
<lb n="07126"/> <p>She counted all her cards again before sending <persName xml:id="ma">Mary</persName> up to
  <lb n="07127"/> <persName xml:id="bd">Mr Doran</persName>'s room to say that she wished to speak with him.
<lb n="07128"/> She felt sure she would win. He was a serious young man, not
<lb n="07129"/> rakish or loudvoiced like the others. If it had been <persName xml:id="ms">Mr Sheri=
  <lb n="07130"/> dan</persName> or <persName xml:id="me">Mr Meade</persName> or <persName xml:id="bl">Bantam Lyons</persName> her task would have been
<lb n="07131"/> much harder. She did not think he would face publicity.
<lb n="07132"/> All the lodgers in the house knew something of the affair;
<lb n="07133"/> details had been invented by some. Besides, he had been em=
<lb n="07134"/> ployed for thirteen years in a great catholic winemerchant's
<lb n="07135"/> office and publicity would mean for him, perhaps, the loss of
<lb n="07136"/> his sit. Whereas if he agreed all might be well. She knew he had
<lb n="07137"/> a good screw for one thing and she suspected he had a bit of
<lb n="07138"/> stuff put by.</p>
<lb n="07139"/> <p>Nearly the half-hour! She stood up and surveyed herself in
<lb n="07140"/> the pierglass. The decisive expression of her great florid face
<lb n="07141"/> satisfied her and she thought of some mothers she knew who
<lb n="07142"/> could not get their daughters off their hands.</p>
<lb n="07143"/> <p><persName xml:id="bd">Mr Doran</persName> was very anxious indeed this Sunday morning. He
<lb n="07144"/> had made two attempts to shave but his hand had been so
<lb n="07145"/> unsteady that he had been obliged to desist. Three days'
<lb n="07146"/> reddish beard fringed his jaws and every two or three minutes a
<lb n="07147"/> mist gathered on his glasses so that he had to take them off and
<lb n="07148"/> polish them with his pocket-handkerchief. The recollection of
<lb n="07149"/> his confession of the night before was a cause of acute pain to
<lb n="07150"/> him: the priest had drawn out every ridiculous detail of the
<lb n="07151"/> affair and in the end had so magnified his sin that he was
<lb n="07152"/> almost thankful at being afforded a loophole of reparation.
<lb n="07153"/> The harm was done. <said who="Mr Doran" direct="false" aloud="false">What could he do now but marry her or
<lb n="07154"/> run away? He could not brazen it out: the affair would be sure
<lb n="07155"/> to be talked of. His employer would be certain to hear of it.
<lb n="07156"/> Dublin is such a small city - everyone knows everyone else's
  <lb n="07157"/> business.</said> He felt his heart leap warmly in his throat as he heard
  <lb n="07158"/> in his excited imagination old <persName xml:id="ml">Mr Leonard</persName> calling out in his
  <lb n="07159"/> rasping voice <emph>Send <persName xml:id="bd">Mr Doran</persName> here, please.</emph></p>
<lb n="07160"/> <p><said who="Mr Doran" direct="false" aloud="false">All his long years of service gone for nothing! All his
<lb n="07161"/> industry and diligence thrown away! As a young man he had
<lb n="07162"/> sown his wild oats, of course; he had boasted of his freethink=
<lb n="07163"/> ing and denied the existence of God to his companions in
  <lb n="07164"/> publichouses. But that was all past and done with .... nearly.</said>
<lb n="07165"/> He still bought a copy of <emph>Reynolds's Newspaper</emph> every week
<lb n="07166"/> but he attended to his religious duties and for nine tenths of the
<lb n="07167"/> year lived a regular life. He had money enough to settle down
<lb n="07168"/> on: it was not that. But the family would look down on her.
<lb n="07169"/> First of all there was her disreputable father and then her
<lb n="07170"/> mother's boarding house was beginning to get a certain fame.
<lb n="07171"/> He had a notion that he was being had. He could imagine his
<lb n="07172"/> friends talking of the affair and laughing. <said who="Mr Doran" direct="false" aloud="false">She <emph>was</emph> a little
<lb n="07173"/> vulgar; sometimes she said <emph>I seen</emph> and <emph>If I had've known.</emph> But
  <lb n="07174"/> what would grammar matter if he really loved her?</said> He could
<lb n="07175"/> not make up his mind whether to like her or despise her for
<lb n="07176"/> what she had done. Of course, he had done it too. His instinct
<lb n="07177"/> urged him to remain free, not to marry. Once you are married
<lb n="07178"/> you are done for, it said.</p>
<lb n="07179"/> <p>While he was sitting helplessly on the side of the bed in shirt
<lb n="07180"/> and trousers she tapped lightly at his door and entered. She told
<lb n="07181"/> him all, that <said who="Polly Mooney" direct="false">she had made a clean breast of it to her mother</said>
<lb n="07182"/> and that <said who="Polly Mooney" direct="false">her mother would speak with him that morning.</said> She
<lb n="07183"/> cried and threw her arms round his neck, saying:
<lb n="07184"/> <said who="Polly Mooney">―O Bob! Bob! What am I to do? what am I to do at all?</said></p>
  <lb n="07185"/> <p><said who="Polly Mooney" direct="false">She would put an end to herself,</said> she said. He comforted her
<lb n="07186"/> feebly, telling her not to cry, that it would be all right, never
<lb n="07187"/> fear. He felt against his shirt the agitation of her bosom.</p>
<lb n="07188"/> <p>It was not altogether his fault that it had happened. He
<lb n="07189"/> remembered well, with the curious patient memory of the
<lb n="07190"/> celibate, the first casual caresses her dress, her breath, her
<lb n="07191"/> fingers had given him. Then late one night as he was undress=
<lb n="07192"/> ing for bed she had tapped at his door, timidly. She wanted to
<lb n="07193"/> relight her candle at his for hers had been blown out by a gust.
<lb n="07194"/> It was her bath night. She wore a loose open combing jacket of
<lb n="07195"/> printed flannel. Her white instep shone in the opening of her
<lb n="07196"/> furry slippers and the blood glowed warmly behind her per=
<lb n="07197"/> fumed skin. From her hands and wrists too as she lit and
<lb n="07198"/> steadied her candle a faint perfume arose.</p>
<lb n="07199"/> <p>On nights when he came in very late it was she who warmed
<lb n="07200"/> up his dinner. He scarcely knew what he was eating, feeling her
<lb n="07201"/> beside him alone, at night, in the sleeping house. <said who="Mr Doran" direct="false" aloud="false">And her
<lb n="07202"/> thoughtfulness! If the night was anyway cold or wet or windy
<lb n="07203"/> there was sure to be a little tumbler of punch ready for him.
  <lb n="07204"/> Perhaps they could be happy together ......</said></p>
<lb n="07205"/> <p>They used to go upstairs together on tiptoe, each with a
<lb n="07206"/> candle, and on the third landing exchange reluctant good=
<lb n="07207"/> nights. They used to kiss. He remembered well her eyes, the
<lb n="07208"/> touch of her hand and his delirium ......</p>
<lb n="07209"/> <p>But delirium passes. He echoed her phrase, applying it to
  <lb n="07210"/> himself: <said who="Mr Doran" aloud="false"><emph>What am I to do?</emph></said> The instinct of the celibate warned
<lb n="07211"/> him to hold back. But the sin was there: even his sense of
<lb n="07212"/> honour told him that reparation must be made for such a sin.</p>
<lb n="07213"/> <p>While he was sitting with her on the side of the bed <persName xml:id="ma">Mary</persName>
<lb n="07214"/> came to the door and said that <said who="Mary" direct="false">the missus wanted to see him in
  <lb n="07215"/> the parlour.</said> He stood up to put on his coat and waistcoat,
<lb n="07216"/> more helpless than ever. When he was dressed he went over to
<lb n="07217"/> her to comfort her. It would be all right, never fear. He left her
<lb n="07218"/> crying on the bed and moaning softly: <said who="Polly Mooney" direct="false"><emph>O my God!</emph></said></p>
<lb n="07219"/> <p>Going down the stairs his glasses became so dimmed with
<lb n="07220"/> moisture that he had to take them off and polish them. He
<lb n="07221"/> longed to ascend through the roof and fly away to another
<lb n="07222"/> country where he would never hear again of his trouble and yet
<lb n="07223"/> a force pushed him downstairs step by step. The implacable
<lb n="07224"/> faces of his employer and of the Madam stared upon his
<lb n="07225"/> discomfiture. On the last flight of stairs he passed <persName xml:id="jmo">Jack Mooney</persName>
<lb n="07226"/> who was coming up from the pantry nursing two bottles of
<lb n="07227"/> <emph>Bass.</emph> They saluted coldly and the lover's eyes rested for a
<lb n="07228"/> second or two on a thick bulldog face and a pair of thick short
<lb n="07229"/> arms. When he reached the foot of the stairs he glanced up and
  <lb n="07230"/> saw <persName xml:id="jm">Jack</persName> regarding him from the door of the return room.</p>
<lb n="07231"/> <p>Suddenly he remembered the night when one of the music=
<lb n="07232"/> hall <emph>artistes</emph>, a little blond Londoner, had made a rather free
<lb n="07233"/> allusion to Polly. The reunion had been almost broken up on
  <lb n="07234"/> account of <persName xml:id="jm">Jack</persName>'s violence. Everyone tried to quieten him. The
<lb n="07235"/> musichall <emph>artiste</emph>, a little paler than usual, kept smiling and
  <lb n="07236"/> saying that there was no harm meant but <persName xml:id="jm">Jack</persName> kept shouting at
<lb n="07237"/> him that if any fellow tried that sort of a game on with <emph>his</emph>
<lb n="07238"/> sister he'd bloody well put his teeth down his throat, so he
<lb n="07239"/> would.</p>
<lb /> *  *  *
  <lb n="07240"/> <p><persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName> sat for a little time on the side of the bed, crying. Then
<lb n="07241"/> she dried her eyes and went over to the lookingglass. She
<lb n="07242"/> dipped the end of the towel in the waterjug and refreshed her
<lb n="07243"/> eyes with the cool water. She looked at herself in profile and
<lb n="07244"/> readjusted a hairpin above her ear. Then she went back to the
<lb n="07245"/> bed again and sat at the foot. She regarded the pillows for a
<lb n="07246"/> long time and the sight of them awoke in her mind secret
<lb n="07247"/> amiable memories. She rested the nape of her neck against the
<lb n="07248"/> cool iron bedrail and fell into a revery. There was no longer
<lb n="07249"/> any perturbation visible on her face.</p>
<lb n="07250"/> <p>She waited on patiently, almost cheerfully, without alarm,
<lb n="07251"/> her memories gradually giving place to hopes and visions of the
<lb n="07252"/> future. Her hopes and visions were so intricate that she no
<lb n="07253"/> longer saw the white pillows on which her gaze was fixed or
<lb n="07254"/> remembered that she was waiting for anything.</p>
<lb n="07255"/> <p>At last she heard her mother calling. She started to her feet
<lb n="07256"/> and ran to the banisters.
  <lb n="07257"/> <said who="Mrs.Mooney">―<persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>! <persName xml:id="pm">Polly</persName>!</said>
<lb n="07258"/> <said who="Polly Mooney">―Yes, mamma?</said>
  <lb n="07259"/> <said who="Mrs.Mooney">―Come down, dear. <persName xml:id="bd">Mr Doran</persName> wants to speak to you.</said></p>
<lb n="07260"/> <p>Then she remembered what she had been waiting for.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
