<div n="08" type="story">
    <lb n="08000"/> <head rend="italics">A Little Cloud</head>
<lb n="08001"/> <p>Eight years before he had seen his friend off at the North
    <lb n="08002"/> Wall and wished him godspeed. <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> had got on. You could
<lb n="08003"/> tell that at once by his travelled air, his well-cut tweed suit and
<lb n="08004"/> fearless accent. Few fellows had talents like his and fewer still
    <lb n="08005"/> could remain unspoiled by such success. <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s heart was in
<lb n="08006"/> the right place and he had deserved to win. It was something to
<lb n="08007"/> have a friend like that.</p>
    <lb n="08008"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>'s thoughts ever since lunchtime had been of
    <lb n="08009"/> his meeting with <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>, of <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s invitation and of the
    <lb n="08010"/> great city London where <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> lived. He was called <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08011"/> Chandler</persName> because, though he was but slightly under the average
<lb n="08012"/> stature, he gave one the idea of being a little man. His hands
<lb n="08013"/> were white and small, his frame was fragile, his voice was quiet
<lb n="08014"/> and his manners were refined. He took the greatest care of his
<lb n="08015"/> fair silken hair and moustache and used perfume discreetly on
<lb n="08016"/> his handkerchief. The half moons of his nails were perfect and
<lb n="08017"/> when he smiled you caught a glimpse of a row of childish white
<lb n="08018"/> teeth.</p>
<lb n="08019"/> <p>As he sat at his desk in the King's Inns he thought what
<lb n="08020"/> changes those eight years had brought. The friend whom he
<lb n="08021"/> had known under a shabby and necessitous guise had become a
<lb n="08022"/> brilliant figure on the London press. He turned often from his
<lb n="08023"/> tiresome writing to gaze out of the office window. The glow of
<lb n="08024"/> a late autumn sunset covered the grass plots and walks. It cast a
<lb n="08025"/> shower of kindly golden dust on the untidy nurses and decrepit
<lb n="08026"/> old men who drowsed on the benches; it flickered upon all the
<lb n="08027"/> moving figures - on the children who ran screaming along the
<lb n="08028"/> gravel paths and on everyone who passed through the gardens.
<lb n="08029"/> He watched the scene and thought of life; and (as always
<lb n="08030"/> happened when he thought of life) he became sad. A gentle
<lb n="08031"/> melancholy took possession of him. He felt how useless it was
<lb n="08032"/> to struggle against fortune, this being the burden of wisdom
<lb n="08033"/> which the ages had bequeathed to him.</p>
<lb n="08034"/> <p>He remembered the books of poetry upon his shelves at
<lb n="08035"/> home. He had bought them in his bachelor days and many an
<lb n="08036"/> evening, as he sat in the little room off the hall, he had been
<lb n="08037"/> tempted to take one down from the bookshelf and read out
<lb n="08038"/> something to his wife. But shyness had always held him back,
<lb n="08039"/> and so the books had remained on their shelves. At times he
<lb n="08040"/> repeated lines to himself and this consoled him.</p>
<lb n="08041"/> <p>When his hour had struck he stood up and took leave of his
<lb n="08042"/> desk and of his fellow clerks punctiliously. He emerged from
<lb n="08043"/> under the feudal arch of the King's Inns, a neat modest figure,
<lb n="08044"/> and walked swiftly down Henrietta Street. The golden sunset
<lb n="08045"/> was waning and the air had grown sharp. A horde of grimy
<lb n="08046"/> children populated the street. They stood or ran in the roadway
<lb n="08047"/> or crawled up the steps before the gaping doors or squatted like
    <lb n="08048"/> mice upon the thresholds. <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> gave them no
<lb n="08049"/> thought. He picked his way deftly through all that minute
<lb n="08050"/> verminlike life and under the shadow of the gaunt spectral
<lb n="08051"/> mansions in which the old nobility of Dublin had roistered. No
<lb n="08052"/> memory of the past touched him, for his mind was full of a
<lb n="08053"/> present joy.</p>
<lb n="08054"/> <p>He had never been in Corless's but he knew the value of the
<lb n="08055"/> name. He knew that people went there after the theatre to eat
<lb n="08056"/> oysters and drink liqueurs; and he had heard that the waiters
<lb n="08057"/> there spoke French and German. Walking swiftly by at night he
<lb n="08058"/> had seen cabs drawn up before the door and richly dressed
<lb n="08059"/> ladies, escorted by cavaliers, alight and enter quickly. They
<lb n="08060"/> wore noisy dresses and many wraps. Their faces were pow=
<lb n="08061"/> dered and they caught up their dresses, when they touched
<lb n="08062"/> earth, like alarmed Atalantas. He had always passed without
<lb n="08063"/> turning his head to look. It was his habit to walk swiftly in the
<lb n="08064"/> street even by day and whenever he found himself in the city
<lb n="08065"/> late at night he hurried on his way apprehensively and ex=
<lb n="08066"/> citedly. Sometimes, however, he courted the causes of his fear.
<lb n="08067"/> He chose the darkest and narrowest streets and, as he walked
<lb n="08068"/> boldly forward, the silence that was spread about his footsteps
<lb n="08069"/> troubled him, the wandering silent figures troubled him, and at
<lb n="08070"/> times a sound of low fugitive laughter made him tremble like a
<lb n="08071"/> leaf.</p>
<lb n="08072"/> <p>He turned to the right towards Capel Street. <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Galla=
    <lb n="08073"/> her</persName> on the London press! Who would have thought it possible
<lb n="08074"/> eight years before? Still, now that he reviewed the past, <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08075"/> Chandler</persName> could remember many signs of future greatness in his
    <lb n="08076"/> friend. People used to say that <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> was wild. Of
<lb n="08077"/> course, he did mix with a rakish set of fellows at that time,
<lb n="08078"/> drank freely and borrowed money on all sides. In the end he
<lb n="08079"/> had got mixed up in some shady affair, some money transac=
<lb n="08080"/> tion: at least, that was one version of his flight. But nobody
<lb n="08081"/> denied him talent. There was always a certain ... something in
    <lb n="08082"/> <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> that impressed you in spite of yourself. Even
<lb n="08083"/> when he was out at elbows and at his wits' end for money he
    <lb n="08084"/> kept up a bold face. <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> remembered (and the
<lb n="08085"/> remembrance brought a slight flush of pride to his cheek) one
    <lb n="08086"/> of <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>'s sayings when he was in a tight corner:
<lb n="08087"/> <said who="">―</said>Half time now, boys, he used to say lightheartedly. Where's
<lb n="08088"/> my considering cap?</p>
    <lb n="08089"/> <p>That was <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> all out; and, damn it, you
<lb n="08090"/> couldn't but admire him for it.</p>
    <lb n="08091"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> quickened his pace. For the first time in his
<lb n="08092"/> life he felt himself superior to the people he passed. For the first
<lb n="08093"/> time his soul revolted against the dull inelegance of Capel
<lb n="08094"/> Street. There was no doubt about it: if you wanted to succeed
<lb n="08095"/> you had to go away. You could do nothing in Dublin. As he
<lb n="08096"/> crossed Grattan Bridge he looked down the river towards the
<lb n="08097"/> lower quays and pitied the poor stunted houses. They seemed
<lb n="08098"/> to him a band of tramps huddled together along the river
<lb n="08099"/> banks, their old coats covered with dust and soot, stupefied by
<lb n="08100"/> the panorama of sunset and waiting for the first chill of night
<lb n="08101"/> to bid them arise, shake themselves and begone. He wondered
<lb n="08102"/> whether he could write a poem to express his idea. Perhaps
    <lb n="08103"/> <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> might be able to get it into some London paper for
<lb n="08104"/> him. Could he write something original? He was not sure what
<lb n="08105"/> idea he wished to express but the thought that a poetic moment
<lb n="08106"/> had touched him took life within him like an infant hope. He
<lb n="08107"/> stepped onward bravely.</p>
<lb n="08108"/> <p>Every step brought him nearer to London, farther from his
<lb n="08109"/> own sober inartistic life. A light began to tremble on the
<lb n="08110"/> horizon of his mind. He was not so old - thirty-two. His
<lb n="08111"/> temperament might be said to be just at the point of maturity.
<lb n="08112"/> There were so many different moods and impressions that he
<lb n="08113"/> wished to express in verse. He felt them within him. He tried to
<lb n="08114"/> weigh his soul to see if it was a poet's soul. Melancholy was the
<lb n="08115"/> dominant note of his temperament, he thought, but it was a
<lb n="08116"/> melancholy tempered by recurrences of faith and resignation
<lb n="08117"/> and simple joy. If he could give expression to it in a book of
<lb n="08118"/> poems perhaps men would listen. He would never be popular:
<lb n="08119"/> he saw that. He could not sway the crowd but he might appeal
<lb n="08120"/> to a little circle of kindred minds. The English critics perhaps
<lb n="08121"/> would recognise him as one of the Celtic school by reason of
<lb n="08122"/> the melancholy tone of his poems; besides that, he would put in
<lb n="08123"/> allusions. He began to invent sentences and phrases from the
    <lb n="08124"/> notices which his book would get. <emph><persName xml:id="lc">Mr Chandler</persName> has the gift of
<lb n="08125"/> easy and graceful verse. ... A wistful sadness pervades these
<lb n="08126"/> poems. ... The Celtic note.</emph> It was a pity his name was not more
<lb n="08127"/> Irish looking. Perhaps it would be better to insert his mother's
    <lb n="08128"/> name before the surname: <persName xml:id="lc">Thomas Malone Chandler</persName>, or better
    <lb n="08129"/> still: <persName xml:id="lc">T Malone Chandler</persName>. He would speak to <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> about it.</p>
<lb n="08130"/> <p>He pursued his revery so ardently that he passed his street
<lb n="08131"/> and had to turn back. As he came near Corless's his former
<lb n="08132"/> agitation began to overmaster him and he halted before the
<lb n="08133"/> door in indecision. Finally he opened the door and entered.</p>
<lb n="08134"/> <p>The light and noise of the bar held him at the doorway for a
<lb n="08135"/> few moments. He looked about him but his sight was confused
<lb n="08136"/> by the shining of many red and green wineglasses. The bar
<lb n="08137"/> seemed to him to be full of people and he felt that the people
<lb n="08138"/> were observing him curiously. He glanced quickly to right and
<lb n="08139"/> left (frowning slightly to make his errand appear serious) but
<lb n="08140"/> when his sight cleared a little he saw that nobody had turned to
<lb n="08141"/> look at him: and there, sure enough, was <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>
<lb n="08142"/> leaning with his back against the counter and his feet planted
<lb n="08143"/> far apart.
    <lb n="08144"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Hello, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>, old hero, here you are! What is it to be?
<lb n="08145"/> What will you have? I'm taking whisky: better stuff than we get
<lb n="08146"/> across the water. Soda? Lithia? No mineral? I'm the same.
<lb n="08147"/> Spoils the flavour. ... Here, <emph>garçon</emph>, bring us two halves of malt
<lb n="08148"/> whisky like a good fellow. ... Well, and how have you been
<lb n="08149"/> pulling along ever since I saw you last? Dear God, how old
<lb n="08150"/> we're getting! Do you see any signs of aging in me - eh, what? A
<lb n="08151"/> little grey and thin on the top - what?</said></p>
    <lb n="08152"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> took off his hat and displayed a large
<lb n="08153"/> closely cropped head. His face was heavy, pale and clean=
<lb n="08154"/> shaven. His eyes, which were of bluish slate colour, relieved his
<lb n="08155"/> unhealthy pallor and shone out plainly above the vivid orange
<lb n="08156"/> tie he wore. Between these rival features the lips appeared very
<lb n="08157"/> long and shapeless and colourless. He bent his head and felt
<lb n="08158"/> with two sympathetic fingers the thin hair at the crown. <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08159"/> Chandler</persNae> shook his head as a denial. <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> put on
<lb n="08160"/> his hat again.
<lb n="08161"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―It pulls you down, he said, press life. Always hurry and
<lb n="08162"/> scurry, looking for copy and sometimes not finding it: and then
<lb n="08163"/> always to have something new in your stuff. Damn proofs and
<lb n="08164"/> printers, I say, for a few days. I'm deuced glad, I can tell you, to
<lb n="08165"/> get back to the old country. Does a fellow good, a bit of a
<lb n="08166"/> holiday. I feel a ton better since I landed again in dear dirty
    <lb n="08167"/> Dublin ... Here you are, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>. Water? Say when.</said></p>
    <lb n="08168"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> allowed his whisky to be very much diluted.
<lb n="08169"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―You don't know what's good for you, my boy, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius
    <lb n="08170"/> Gallaher</persName>. I drink mine neat.</said>
<lb n="08171"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―I drink very little as a rule, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> modestly. An
<lb n="08172"/> odd half one or so when I meet any of the old crowd: that's all.</said>
<lb n="08173"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Ah well, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> cheerfully, here's to us and
<lb n="08174"/> to old times and old acquaintance.</said></p>
<lb n="08175"/> <p>They clinked glasses and drank the toast.
<lb n="08176"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I met some of the old gang today, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>.
    <lb n="08177"/> <persName xml:id="oh">O'Hara</persName> seems to be in a bad way. What's he doing?</said>
<lb n="08178"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Nothing, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>. He's gone to the dogs.</said>
    <lb n="08179"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―But <persName xml:id="hg">Hogan</persName> has a good sit, hasn't he?</said>
<lb n="08180"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Yes; he's in the Land Commission.</said>
<lb n="08181"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I met him one night in London and he seemed to be very
    <lb n="08182"/> flush. ... Poor <persName xml:id="oh">O'Hara</persName>! Boose, I suppose?</said>
<lb n="08183"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Other things, too, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> shortly.</said></p>
    <lb n="08184"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> laughed.
    <lb n="08185"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―<persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>, he said, I see you haven't changed an atom. You're
<lb n="08186"/> the very same serious person that used to lecture me on Sunday
<lb n="08187"/> mornings when I had a sore head and a fur on my tongue.
<lb n="08188"/> You'd want to knock about a bit in the world. Have you never
<lb n="08189"/> been anywhere, even for a trip?</said>
<lb n="08190"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―I've been to the Isle of Man, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08191"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> laughed.
<lb n="08192"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―The Isle of Man! he said. Go to London or Paris: Paris, for
<lb n="08193"/> choice. That'd do you good.</said>
<lb n="08194"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Have you seen Paris?</said>
<lb n="08195"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I should think I have! I've knocked about there a little.</said>
<lb n="08196"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―And is it really so beautiful as they say? asked <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08197"/> Chandler</persName>.</said></p>
<lb n="08198"/> <p>He sipped a little of his drink while <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>
<lb n="08199"/> finished his boldly.
<lb n="08200"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Beautiful? said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, pausing on the word and
<lb n="08201"/> on the flavour of his drink. It's not so beautiful, you know. Of
<lb n="08202"/> course, it is beautiful. ... But it's the life of Paris: that's the
<lb n="08203"/> thing. Ah, there's no city like Paris for gaiety, movement,
<lb n="08204"/> excitement. ...</said></p>
    <lb n="08205"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> finished his whisky and after some trouble
<lb n="08206"/> succeeded in catching the barman's eye. He ordered the same
<lb n="08207"/> again.
<lb n="08208"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I've been to the Moulin Rouge, <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> continued
<lb n="08209"/> when the barman had removed their glasses, and I've been to
<lb n="08210"/> all the bohemian cafés. Hot stuff! Not for a pious chap like
    <lb n="08211"/> you, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08212"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> said nothing until the barman returned with
<lb n="08213"/> the two glasses: then he touched his friend's glass lightly and
<lb n="08214"/> reciprocated the former toast. He was beginning to feel some=
    <lb n="08215"/> hwhat disillusioned. <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s accent and way of expressing
<lb n="08216"/> himself did not please him. There was something vulgar in his
<lb n="08217"/> friend which he had not observed before. But perhaps it was
<lb n="08218"/> only the result of living in London amid the bustle and
<lb n="08219"/> competition of the press. The old personal charm was still there
<lb n="08220"/> under this new gaudy manner. And, after all, <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> had
    <lb n="08221"/> lived, he had seen the world. <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> looked at his
<lb n="08222"/> friend enviously.
<lb n="08223"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallahe">―Everything in Paris is gay, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher.</persName> They
<lb n="08224"/> believe in enjoying life and don't you think they're right? If you
<lb n="08225"/> want to enjoy yourself properly you must go to Paris. And,
<lb n="08226"/> mind you, they've a great feeling for the Irish there. When they
<lb n="08227"/> heard I was from Ireland they were ready to eat me, man.</said></p>
    <lb n="08228"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> took four or five sips from his glass.
<lb n="08229"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Tell me, he said, is it true that Paris is so ... immoral as they
<lb n="08230"/> say?</said></p>
    <lb n="08231"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> made a catholic gesture with his right arm.
<lb n="08232"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Every place is immoral, he said. Of course you do find spicy
<lb n="08233"/> bits in Paris. Go to one of the students' balls, for instance.
<lb n="08234"/> That's lively, if you like, when the <emph>cocottes</emph> begin to let them=
<lb n="08235"/> selves loose. You know what they are, I suppose?</said
<lb n="08236"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―I've heard of them, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08237"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> drank off his whisky and shook his head.
<lb n="08238"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Ah, he said, you may say what you like. There's no woman
<lb n="08239"/> like the Parisienne for style, for go.</said>
<lb n="08240"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Then it is an immoral city, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> with timid
<lb n="08241"/> insistence, I mean, compared with London or Dublin?</said>
    <lb n="08242"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―London! said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>. It's six of one and half a
    <lb n="08243"/> dozen of the other. You ask <persName xml:id="hg">Hogan</persName>, my boy. I showed him a bit
<lb n="08244"/> about London when he was over there. He'd open your eye. ...
    <lb n="08245"/> I say, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>, don't make punch of that whisky: liquor up.</said>
<lb n="08246"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―No, really. ...</said>
<lb n="08247"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―O, come on, another one won't do you any harm. What is
<lb n="08248"/> it? The same again, I suppose?</said>
<lb n="08249"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Well ... all right.</said>
<lb n="08250"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―<emph>François</emph>, the same again. ... Will you smoke, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>?</said></p>
    <lb n="08251"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> produced his cigar case. The two friends
<lb n="08252"/> lit their cigars and puffed at them in silence until their drinks
<lb n="08253"/> were served.
<lb n="08254"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I'll tell you my opinion, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, emerging
<lb n="08255"/> after some time from the clouds of smoke in which he had
<lb n="08256"/> taken refuge, it's a rum world. Talk of immorality! I've heard
<lb n="08257"/> of cases - what am I saying - I've known them: cases of ...
<lb n="08258"/> immorality ....</said></p>
    <lb n="08259"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> puffed thoughtfully at his cigar and then,
<lb n="08260"/> in a calm historian's tone, he proceeded to sketch for his friend
<lb n="08261"/> some pictures of the corruption which was rife abroad. He
<lb n="08262"/> summarised the vices of many capitals and seemed inclined to
<lb n="08263"/> award the palm to Berlin. Some things he could not vouch for
<lb n="08264"/> (his friends had told him) but of others he had had personal
<lb n="08265"/> experience. He spared neither rank nor caste. He revealed
<lb n="08266"/> many of the secrets of religious houses on the continent and
<lb n="08267"/> described some of the practices which were fashionable in high
<lb n="08268"/> society: and ended by telling, with details, a story about an
<lb n="08269"/> English duchess - a story which he knew to be true. <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08270"/> Chandler</persName> was astonished.
<lb n="08271"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Ah, well, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, here we are in old jogalong
<lb n="08272"/> Dublin where nothing is known of such things.</said>
<lb n="08273"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―How dull you must find it, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>, after all the
<lb n="08274"/> other places you've seen!</said>
    <lb n="08275"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Well, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, it's a relaxation to come over
<lb n="08276"/> here, you know. And, after all, it's the old country, as they say,
<lb n="08277"/> isn't it? You can't help having a certain feeling for it. That's
<lb n="08278"/> human nature. ... But tell me something about yourself. <persName xml:id="hg">Hogan</persName>
<lb n="08279"/> told me you had ... tasted the joys of connubial bliss. Two years
<lb n="08280"/> ago, wasn't it?</said></p>
    <lb n="08281"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> blushed and smiled.
<lb n="08282"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Yes, he said. I was married last May twelve months.</said>
<lb n="08283"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I hope it's not too late in the day to offer my best wishes,
    <lb n="08284"/> said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>. I didn't know your address or I'd have
<lb n="08285"/> done so at the time.</said></p>
    <lb n="08286"/> <p>He extended his hand which <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> took.
    <lb n="08287"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Well, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>, he said, I wish you and yours every joy in life,
<lb n="08288"/> old chap, and tons of money and may you never die till I shoot
<lb n="08289"/> you. And that's the wish of a sincere friend, an old friend. You
<lb n="08290"/> know that?</said>
<lb n="08291"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―I know that, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>.</said>
<lb n="08292"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Any youngsters? said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08293"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> blushed again.
<lb n="08294"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―We have one child, he said.</said>
<lb n="08295"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Son or daughter?</said>
<lb n="08296"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―A little boy.</said></p>
    <lb n="08297"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> slapped his friend sonorously on the back.
<lb n="08298"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Bravo, he said, I wouldn't doubt you, <persName xml:id="lc">Tommy</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08299"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> smiled, looked confusedly at his glass and bit
<lb n="08300"/> his lower lip with three childishly white front teeth.
<lb n="08301"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―I hope you'll spend an evening with us, he said, before you
<lb n="08302"/> go back. My wife will be delighted to meet you. We can have a
<lb n="08303"/> little music and ...</said>
<lb n="08304"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Thanks awfully, old chap, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, I'm sorry
<lb n="08305"/> we didn't meet earlier. But I must leave tomorrow night.</said>
<lb n="08306"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Tonight, perhaps. ...</said>
<lb n="08307"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―I'm awfully sorry, old man. You see I'm over here with an=
<lb n="08308"/> other fellow, clever young chap he is too, and we arranged to
<lb n="08309"/> go to a little card party. Only for that ....</said>
<lb n="08310"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―O, in that case. ...</said>
<lb n="08311"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―But who knows? said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> considerately. Next
<lb n="08312"/> year I may take a little skip over here now that I've broken the
<lb n="08313"/> ice. It's only a pleasure deferred.</said>
<lb n="08314"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Very well, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>, the next time you come we
<lb n="08315"/> must have an evening together. That's agreed now, isn't it?</said>
<lb n="08316"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Yes, that's agreed, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>. Next year if I
<lb n="08317"/> come, <emph>parole d'honneur.</said></emph>
<lb n="08318"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―And to clinch the bargain, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>, we'll just
<lb n="08319"/> have one more now.</said></p>
    <lb n="08320"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> took out a large gold watch and looked
<lb n="08321"/> at it.
<lb n="08322"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Is it to be the last? he said. Because, you know, I have an a.p.</said>
<lb n="08323"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―O yes, positively, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>.</said>
<lb n="08324"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Very well then, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>, let us have another
<lb n="08325"/> one as a <emph>deoc an doruis</emph> - that's good vernacular for a small
<lb n="08326"/> whisky, I believe.</said></p>
    <lb n="08327"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> ordered the drinks. The blush which had
<lb n="08328"/> risen to his face a few moments before was establishing itself. A
<lb n="08329"/> trifle made him blush at any time: and now he felt warm and
<lb n="08330"/> excited. Three small whiskies had gone to his head and <persName xml:id="ig">Galla=
    <lb n="08331"/> her</persName>'s strong cigar had confused his mind for he was a delicate
<lb n="08332"/> and abstinent person. The adventure of meeting <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> after
    <lb n="08333"/> eight years, of finding himself with <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> in Corless's sur=
<lb n="08334"/> rounded by lights and noise, of listening to <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s stories
    <lb n="08335"/> and of sharing for a brief space <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s vagrant and trium=
<lb n="08336"/> phant life, upset the equipoise of his sensitive nature. He felt
<lb n="08337"/> acutely the contrast between his own life and his friend's and it
    <lb n="08338"/> seemed to him unjust. <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> was his inferior in birth and
<lb n="08339"/> education. He was sure that he could do something better than
<lb n="08340"/> his friend had ever done, or could ever do, something higher
<lb n="08341"/> than mere tawdry journalism if only he got the chance. What
<lb n="08342"/> was it that stood in his way? His unfortunate timidity! He
<lb n="08343"/> wished to vindicate himself in some way, to assert his man=
    <lb n="08344"/> hood. He saw behind <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>'s refusal of his invitation. <persName xml:id="ig">Gal=
    <lb n="08345"/> laher</persName> was only patronising him by his friendliness just as he
<lb n="08346"/> was patronising Ireland by his visit.</p>
    <lb n="08347"/> <p>The barman brought their drinks. <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> pushed
<lb n="08348"/> one glass towards his friend and took up the other boldly.
<lb n="08349"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Who knows? he said as they lifted their glasses. When you
<lb n="08350"/> come next year I may have the pleasure of wishing long life and
    <lb n="08351"/> happiness to Mr and Mrs <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName>.</said></p>
    <lb n="08352"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> in the act of drinking closed one eye
<lb n="08353"/> expressively over the rim of his glass. When he had drunk he
<lb n="08354"/> smacked his lips decisively, set down his glass and said:
<lb n="08355"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―No blooming fear of that, my boy. I'm going to have my
<lb n="08356"/> fling first and see a bit of life and the world before I put my
<lb n="08357"/> head in the sack - if I ever do.</said>
<lb n="08358"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Some day you will, said <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> calmly.</said></p>
    <lb n="08359"/> <p><persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> turned his orange tie and slateblue eyes
<lb n="08360"/> full upon his friend.
<lb n="08361"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―You think so? he said.</said>
<lb n="08362"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―You'll put your head in the sack, repeated <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName>
<lb n="08363"/> stoutly, like everyone else, if you can find the girl.</said></p>
<lb n="08364"/> <p>He had slightly emphasised his tone and he was aware that
<lb n="08365"/> he had betrayed himself; but though the colour had heightened
<lb n="08366"/> in his cheek he did not flinch from his friend's gaze. <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius
    <lb n="08367"/> Gallaher</persName> watched him for a few moments and then said:
<lb n="08368"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―If ever it occurs you may bet your bottom dollar there'll
<lb n="08369"/> be no mooning and spooning about it. I mean to marry money.
<lb n="08370"/> She'll have a good fat account at the bank or she won't do for
<lb n="08371"/> me.</said></p>
    <lb n="08372"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> shook his head.
<lb n="08373"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Why, man alive, said <persName xml:id="ig">Ignatius Gallaher</persName> vehemently, do you
<lb n="08374"/> know what it is? I've only to say the word and tomorrow I can
<lb n="08375"/> have the woman and the cash. You don't believe it? Well, I
<lb n="08376"/> know it. There are hundreds - what am I saying? - thousands of
<lb n="08377"/> rich Germans and Jews, rotten with money, that'd only be too
<lb n="08378"/> glad. ... You wait awhile, my boy. See if I don't play my cards
<lb n="08379"/> properly. When I go about a thing I mean business, I tell you.
<lb n="08380"/> You just wait.</said></p>
<lb n="08381"/> <p>He tossed his glass to his mouth, finished his drink and laughed loudly. Then he looked thoughtfully before him and
<lb n="08382"/> said in a calmer tone:
<lb n="08383"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―But I'm in no hurry. They can wait. I don't fancy tying
<lb n="08384"/> myself up to one woman, you know.</said></p>
<lb n="08385"/> <p>He imitated with his mouth the act of tasting and made a
<lb n="08386"/> wry face.
<lb n="08387"/> <said who="Ignatius Gallaher">―Must get a bit stale, I should think, he said.</said></p>
<lb /> *  *  *
    <lb n="08389"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> sat in the room off the hall, holding a child
<lb n="08390"/> in his arms. To save money they kept no servant but <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName>'s
    <lb n="08391"/> young sister <persName xml:id="mo">Monica</persName> came for an hour or so in the morning and
    <lb n="08392"/> an hour or so in the evening to help. But <persName xml:id="mo">Monica</persName> had gone
<lb n="08393"/> home long ago. It was a quarter to nine. <persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> had
<lb n="08394"/> come home late for tea and, moreover, he had forgotten to
    <lb n="08395"/> bring <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName> home the parcel of coffee from Bewley's. Of course
<lb n="08396"/> she was in a bad humour and gave him short answers. She said
<lb n="08397"/> she would do without any tea but when it came near the time
<lb n="08398"/> at which the shop at the corner closed she decided to go out
<lb n="08399"/> herself for a quarter of a pound of tea and two pounds of
<lb n="08400"/> sugar. She put the sleeping child deftly in his arms and said:
<lb n="08401"/> <said who="Annie">―Here. Don't waken him.</said></p>
<lb n="08402"/> <p>A little lamp with a white china shade stood upon the table
<lb n="08403"/> and its light fell over a photograph which was enclosed in a
    <lb n="08404"/> frame of crumpled horn. It was <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName>'s photograph. <persName xml:id="lc">Little
    <lb n="08405"/> Chandler</persName> looked at it, pausing at the thin tight lips. She wore
<lb n="08406"/> the pale blue summer blouse which he had brought her home as
<lb n="08407"/> a present one Saturday. It had cost him ten and elevenpence;
<lb n="08408"/> but what an agony of nervousness it had cost him! How he had
<lb n="08409"/> suffered that day, waiting at the shopdoor until the shop was
<lb n="08410"/> empty, standing at the counter and trying to appear at his ease
<lb n="08411"/> while the girl piled ladies' blouses before him, paying at the
<lb n="08412"/> desk and forgetting to take up the odd penny of his change,
<lb n="08413"/> being called back by the cashier and, finally, striving to hide his
<lb n="08414"/> blushes as he left the shop by examining the parcel to see if it
<lb n="08415"/> was securely tied. When he brought the blouse home <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName>
<lb n="08416"/> kissed him and said it was very pretty and stylish but when she
<lb n="08417"/> heard the price she threw the blouse on the table and said it
<lb n="08418"/> was a regular swindle to charge ten and elevenpence for that.
<lb n="08419"/> At first she wanted to take it back but when she tried it on she
<lb n="08420"/> was delighted with it, especially with the make of the sleeves,
<lb n="08421"/> and kissed him and said he was very good to think of her.</p>
<lb n="08422"/> <p>Hm! ...</p>
<lb n="08423"/> <p>He looked coldly into the eyes of the photograph and they
<lb n="08424"/> answered coldly. Certainly they were pretty and the face itself
<lb n="08425"/> was pretty. But he found something mean in it. Why was it so
<lb n="08426"/> unconscious and ladylike? The composure of the eyes irritated
<lb n="08427"/> him. They repelled him and defied him: there was no passion in
    <lb n="08428"/> them, no rapture. He thought of what <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName> had said about
<lb n="08429"/> rich Jewesses. Those dark oriental eyes, he thought, how full
<lb n="08430"/> they are of passion, of voluptuous longing! ... Why had he
<lb n="08431"/> married the eyes in the photograph?</p>
<lb n="08432"/> <p>He caught himself up at the question and glanced nervously
<lb n="08433"/> round the room. He found something mean in the pretty
<lb n="08434"/> furniture which he had bought for his house on the hire system.
    <lb n="08435"/> <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName> had chosen it herself and it reminded him of her. It too
<lb n="08436"/> was prim and pretty. A dull resentment against his life awoke
<lb n="08437"/> within him. Could he not escape from his little house? Was it
<lb n="08438"/> too late for him to try to live bravely like <persName xml:id="ig">Gallaher</persName>? Could he
<lb n="08439"/> go to London? There was the furniture still to be paid for. If he
<lb n="08440"/> could only write a book and get it published, that might open
<lb n="08441"/> the way for him.</p>
<lb n="08442"/> <p>A volume of Byron's poems lay before him on the table. He
<lb n="08443"/> opened it cautiously with his left hand lest he should waken the
<lb n="08444"/> child and began to read the first poem in the book:</p>
<lb n="08445"/> <p><emph>Hushed are the winds and still the evening gloom,</p>
<lb n="08446"/> <p>.Not e'en a Zephyr wanders through the grove,</p>
<lb n="08447"/> <p>Whilst I return to view my Margaret's tomb</p>
<lb n="08448"/> <p>.And scatter flowers on the dust I love.</emph></p>
<lb n="08449"/> <p>He paused. He felt the rhythm of the verse about him in the
<lb n="08450"/> room. How melancholy it was! Could he, too, write like that,
<lb n="08451"/> express the melancholy of his soul in verse? There were so
<lb n="08452"/> many things he wanted to describe: his sensation of a few hours
<lb n="08453"/> before on Grattan Bridge, for example. If he could get back
<lb n="08454"/> again into that mood. ...</p>
<lb n="08455"/> <p>The child awoke and began to cry. He turned from the page
<lb n="08456"/> and tried to hush it: but it would not be hushed. He began to
<lb n="08457"/> rock it to and fro in his arms but its wailing cry grew keener.
<lb n="08458"/> He rocked it faster while his eyes began to read the second
<lb n="08459"/> stanza:</p>
<lb n="08460"/> <p><emph>Within this narrow cell reclines her clay,</p>
<lb n="08461"/> <p>.That clay where once ...</emph> </p>
<lb n="08462"/> <p>It was useless. He couldn't read. He couldn't do anything.
<lb n="08463"/> The wailing of the child pierced the drum of his ear. It was
<lb n="08464"/> useless, useless! He was a prisoner for life. His arms trembled
<lb n="08465"/> with anger and suddenly bending to the child's face he shouted:
<lb n="08466"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―Stop!</said></p>
<lb n="08467"/> <p>The child stopped for an instant, had a spasm of fright and
<lb n="08468"/> began to scream. He jumped up from his chair and walked
<lb n="08469"/> hastily up and down the room with the child in his arms. It
<lb n="08470"/> began to sob piteously, losing its breath for four or five seconds
<lb n="08471"/> and then bursting out anew. The thin walls of the room echoed
<lb n="08472"/> the sound. He tried to soothe it but it sobbed more convul=
<lb n="08473"/> sively. He looked at the contracted and quivering face of the
<lb n="08474"/> child and began to be alarmed. He counted seven sobs without
<lb n="08475"/> a break between them and caught the child to his breast in
<lb n="08476"/> in fright. If it died! ...</p>
<lb n="08477"/> <p>The door was burst open and a young woman ran in,
<lb n="08478"/> panting.
<lb n="08479"/> <said who="Annie">―What is it? What is it? she cried.</said></p>
<lb n="08480"/> <p>The child, hearing its mother's voice, broke out into a par=
<lb n="08481"/> oxysm of sobbing.
    <lb n="08482"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―It's nothing, <persName xml:id="ae">Annie</persName> ... it's nothing. ... He began to cry. ...</said></p>
<lb n="08483"/> <p>She flung her parcels on the floor and snatched the child
<lb n="08484"/> from him.
<lb n="08485"/> <said who="Annie">―What have you done to him? she cried, glaring into his face.</said></p>
    <lb n="08486"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> sustained for one moment the gaze of her
<lb n="08487"/> eyes and his heart closed together as he met the hatred in them.
<lb n="08488"/> He began to stammer:
<lb n="08489"/> <said who="Little Chandler">―It's nothing. ... He ... he began to cry. ... I couldn't ... I didn't
<lb n="08490"/> do anything. ... What?</said></p>
<lb n="08491"/> <p>Giving no heed to him she began to walk up and down the
<lb n="08492"/> room, clasping the child tightly in her arms and murmuring:
<lb n="08493"/> <said who="Annie">―My little man! My little mannie! Was 'ou frightened, love? ...
<lb n="08494"/> There now, love! There now! ... Lambabaun! Mamma's little
<lb n="08495"/> lamb of the world! ... There now!</said></p>
    <lb n="08496"/> <p><persName xml:id="lc">Little Chandler</persName> felt his cheeks suffused with shame and he
<lb n="08497"/> stood back out of the lamplight. He listened while the parox=
<lb n="08498"/> ysm of the child's sobbing grew less and less: and tears of
<lb n="08499"/> remorse started to his eyes.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
