<div n="10" type="story"><lb n="10000"/> <head rend="italics">Clay</head>
<lb n="10001"/> <p>The matron had given her leave to go out as soon as the
<lb n="10002"/> women's tea was over and Maria looked forward to her
<lb n="10003"/> evening out. The kitchen was spick and span: the cook said you
<lb n="10004"/> could see yourself in the big copper boilers. The fire was nice
<lb n="10005"/> and bright and on one of the sidetables were four very big
<lb n="10006"/> barmbracks. These barmbracks seemed uncut but, if you went
<lb n="10007"/> closer, you would see that they had been cut into long thick
<lb n="10008"/> even slices and were ready to be handed round at tea. Maria
<lb n="10009"/> had cut them herself.</p>
<lb n="10010"/> <p>Maria was a very, very small person indeed but she had a
<lb n="10011"/> very long nose and a very long chin. She talked a little through
<lb n="10012"/> her nose, always soothingly: <emph>Yes, my dear</emph>, and <emph>No, my dear.</emph>
<lb n="10013"/> She was always sent for when the women quarrelled over their
<lb n="10014"/> tubs and always succeeded in making peace. One day the
<lb n="10015"/> matron had said to her:
<lb n="10016"/> <said who="">―</said>Maria, you are a veritable peacemaker!</p>
<lb n="10017"/> <p>And the submatron and two of the board ladies had heard
<lb n="10018"/> the compliment. And Ginger Mooney was always saying what
<lb n="10019"/> she wouldn't do to the dummy who had charge of the irons if it
<lb n="10020"/> wasn't for Maria. Everyone was so fond of Maria.</p>
<lb n="10021"/> <p>The women would have their tea at six o'clock and she
<lb n="10022"/> would be able to get away before seven. From Ballsbridge to
<lb n="10023"/> the Pillar, twenty minutes; from the Pillar to Drumcondra,
<lb n="10024"/> twenty minutes; and twenty minutes to buy the things. She
<lb n="10025"/> would be there before eight. She took out her purse with the
<lb n="10026"/> silver clasps and read again the words <emph>A Present from Belfast.</emph>
<lb n="10027"/> She was very fond of that purse because Joe had brought it to
<lb n="10028"/> her five years before when he and Alphy had gone to Belfast on
<lb n="10029"/> a Whit Monday trip. In the purse were two half crowns and
<lb n="10030"/> some coppers. She would have five shillings clear after paying
<lb n="10031"/> tram fare. What a nice evening they would have, all the
<lb n="10032"/> children singing! Only she hoped that Joe wouldn't come in
<lb n="10033"/> drunk. He was so different when he took any drink.</p>
<lb n="10034"/> <p>Often he had wanted her to go and live with them; but she
<lb n="10035"/> would have felt herself in the way (though Joe's wife was ever
<lb n="10036"/> so nice with her) and she had become accustomed to the life of
<lb n="10037"/> the laundry. Joe was a good fellow. She had nursed him and
<lb n="10038"/> Alphy too; and Joe used often to say:
<lb n="10039"/> <said who="">―</said>Mamma is mamma but Maria is my proper mother.</p>
<lb n="10040"/> <p>After the breakup at home the boys had got her that position
<lb n="10041"/> in the <emph>Dublin by Lamplight</emph> laundry and she liked it. She used
<lb n="10042"/> to have such a bad opinion of protestants but now she thought
<lb n="10043"/> they were very nice people, a little quiet and serious, but still
<lb n="10044"/> very nice people to live with. Then she had her plants in the
<lb n="10045"/> conservatory and she liked looking after them. She had lovely
<lb n="10046"/> ferns and waxplants and whenever anyone came to visit her she
<lb n="10047"/> always gave the visitor one or two slips from her conservatory.
<lb n="10048"/> There was one thing she didn't like and that was the tracts on
<lb n="10049"/> the walls; but the matron was such a nice person to deal with,
<lb n="10050"/> so genteel.</p>
<lb n="10051"/> <p>When the cook told her everything was ready she went into
<lb n="10052"/> the women's room and began to pull the big bell. In a few
<lb n="10053"/> minutes the women began to come in by twos and threes,
<lb n="10054"/> wiping their steaming hands in their petticoats and pulling
<lb n="10055"/> down the sleeves of their blouses over their red steaming arms.
<lb n="10056"/> They settled down before their huge mugs which the cook and
<lb n="10057"/> the dummy filled up with hot tea, already mixed with milk and
<lb n="10058"/> sugar in huge tin cans. Maria superintended the distribution of
<lb n="10059"/> the barmbrack and saw that every woman got her four slices.
<lb n="10060"/> There was a great deal of laughing and joking during the meal.
<lb n="10061"/> Lizzie Fleming said Maria was sure to get the ring and, though
<lb n="10062"/> Fleming had said that for so many Hallow Eves, Maria had to
<lb n="10063"/> laugh and say she didn't want any ring or man either; and
<lb n="10064"/> when she laughed her greygreen eyes sparkled with disap=
<lb n="10065"/> pointed shyness and the tip of her nose nearly met the tip of her
<lb n="10066"/> chin. Then Ginger Mooney lifted up her mug of tea and
<lb n="10067"/> proposed Maria's health while all the other women clattered
<lb n="10068"/> with their mugs on the table and said she was sorry she hadn't
<lb n="10069"/> a sup of porter to drink it in. And Maria laughed again till the
<lb n="10070"/> tip of her nose nearly met the tip of her chin and till her minute
<lb n="10071"/> body nearly shook itself asunder because she knew that
<lb n="10072"/> Mooney meant well though of course she had the notions of a
<lb n="10073"/> common woman.</p>
<lb n="10074"/> <p>But wasn't Maria glad when the women had finished their
<lb n="10075"/> tea and the cook and the dummy had begun to clear away the
<lb n="10076"/> tea things? She went into her little bedroom and, remembering
<lb n="10077"/> that the next morning was a mass morning, changed the hand
<lb n="10078"/> of the alarm from seven to six. Then she took off her working
<lb n="10079"/> skirt and her houseboots and laid her best skirt out on the bed
<lb n="10080"/> and her tiny dressboots beside the foot of the bed. She changed
<lb n="10081"/> her blouse too and, as she stood before the mirror, she thought
<lb n="10082"/> of how she used to dress for mass on Sunday morning when she
<lb n="10083"/> was a young girl; and she looked with quaint affection at the
<lb n="10084"/> diminutive body which she had so often adorned. In spite of its
<lb n="10085"/> years she found it a nice tidy little body.</p>
<lb n="10086"/> <p>When she got outside the streets were shining with rain
<lb n="10087"/> and she was glad of her old brown raincloak. The tram was
<lb n="10088"/> full and she had to sit on the little stool at the end of the car
<lb n="10089"/> facing all the people, with her toes barely touching the floor.
<lb n="10090"/> She arranged in her mind all she was going to do and
<lb n="10091"/> thought how much better it was to be independent and to have
<lb n="10092"/> your own money in your pocket. She hoped they would have
<lb n="10093"/> a nice evening. She was sure they would but she could not
<lb n="10094"/> help thinking what a pity it was Alphy and Joe were not speak=
<lb n="10095"/> ing. They were always falling out now but when they were
<lb n="10096"/> boys together they used to be the best of friends: but such was
<lb n="10097"/> life.</p>
<lb n="10098"/> <p>She got out of her tram at the Pillar and ferreted her way
<lb n="10099"/> quickly among the crowds. She went into Downes's cakeshop
<lb n="10100"/> but the shop was so full of people that it was a long time before
<lb n="10101"/> she could get herself attended to. She bought a dozen of mixed
<lb n="10102"/> penny cakes and at last came out of the shop laden with a big
<lb n="10103"/> bag. Then she thought what else would she buy: she wanted to
<lb n="10104"/> buy something really nice. They would be sure to have plenty
<lb n="10105"/> of apples and nuts. It was hard to know what to buy and all she
<lb n="10106"/> could think of was cake. She decided to buy some plumcake
<lb n="10107"/> but Downes's plumcake had not enough almond icing on top of
<lb n="10108"/> it so she went over to a shop in Henry Street. Here she was a
<lb n="10109"/> long time in suiting herself and the stylish young lady behind
<lb n="10110"/> the counter, who was evidently a little annoyed by her, asked
<lb n="10111"/> her was it weddingcake she wanted to buy. That made Maria
<lb n="10112"/> blush and smile at the young lady but the young lady took it all
<lb n="10113"/> very seriously and finally cut a thick slice of plumcake, par=
<lb n="10114"/> celled it up and said:
<lb n="10115"/> <said who="">―</said>Two and four, please.</p>
<lb n="10116"/> <p>She thought she would have to stand in the Drumcondra
<lb n="10117"/> tram because none of the young men seemed to notice her but
<lb n="10118"/> an elderly gentleman made room for her. He was a stout
<lb n="10119"/> gentleman and he wore a brown hard hat; he had a square red
<lb n="10120"/> face and a greyish moustache. Maria thought he was a co=
<lb n="10121"/> lonel-looking gentleman and she reflected how much more
<lb n="10122"/> polite he was than the young men who simply stared straight
<lb n="10123"/> before them. The gentleman began to chat with her about
<lb n="10124"/> Hallow Eve and the rainy weather. He supposed the bag was
<lb n="10125"/> full of good things for the little ones and said it was only right
<lb n="10126"/> that the youngsters should enjoy themselves while they were
<lb n="10127"/> young. Maria agreed with him and favoured him with demure
<lb n="10128"/> nods and hems. He was very nice with her and when she was
<lb n="10129"/> getting out at the Canal Bridge she thanked him and bowed
<lb n="10130"/> and he bowed to her and raised his hat and smiled agreeably;
<lb n="10131"/> and while she was going up along the terrace, bending her tiny
<lb n="10132"/> head under the rain, she thought how easy it was to know a
<lb n="10133"/> gentleman even when he has a drop taken.</p>
<lb n="10134"/> <p>Everybody said: <emph>O, here's Maria!</emph> when she came to Joe's
<lb n="10135"/> house. Joe was there, having come home from business, and all
<lb n="10136"/> the children had their Sunday dresses on. There were two big
<lb n="10137"/> girls in from next door and games were going on. Maria gave
<lb n="10138"/> the bag of cakes to the eldest boy, Alphy, to divide and Mrs
<lb n="10139"/> Donnelly said it was too good of her to bring such a big bag of
<lb n="10140"/> cakes and made all the children say:
<lb n="10141"/> <said who="">―</said>Thanks, Maria.</p>
<lb n="10142"/> <p>But Maria said she had brought something special for papa
<lb n="10143"/> and mamma, something they would be sure to like, and she
<lb n="10144"/> began to look for her plumcake. She tried in Downes's bag and
<lb n="10145"/> then in the pockets of her raincloak and then on the hallstand
<lb n="10146"/> but nowhere could she find it. Then she asked all the children
<lb n="10147"/> had any of them eaten it - by mistake, of course - but the
<lb n="10148"/> children all said no and looked as if they did not like to eat
<lb n="10149"/> cakes if they were to be accused of stealing. Everybody had a
<lb n="10150"/> solution for the mystery and Mrs Donnelly said it was plain
<lb n="10151"/> that Maria had left it behind her in the tram. Maria, remem=
<lb n="10152"/> bering how confused the gentleman with the greyish moustache
<lb n="10153"/> had made her, coloured with shame and vexation and disap=
<lb n="10154"/> pointment. At the thought of the failure of her little surprise
<lb n="10155"/> and of the two and fourpence she had thrown away for nothing
<lb n="10156"/> she nearly cried outright.</p>
<lb n="10157"/> <p>But Joe said it didn't matter and made her sit down by the
<lb n="10158"/> fire. He was very nice with her. He told her all that went on in
<lb n="10159"/> his office, repeating for her a smart answer which he had made
<lb n="10160"/> to the manager. Maria did not understand why Joe laughed so
<lb n="10161"/> much over the answer he had made but she said that the
<lb n="10162"/> manager must have been a very overbearing person to deal
<lb n="10163"/> with. Joe said he wasn't so bad when you knew how to take
<lb n="10164"/> him, that he was a decent sort so long as you didn't rub him the
<lb n="10165"/> wrong way. Mrs Donnelly played the piano for the children
<lb n="10166"/> and they danced and sang. Then the two nextdoor girls handed
<lb n="10167"/> round the nuts. Nobody could find the nutcracker and Joe was
<lb n="10168"/> nearly getting cross over it and asked how did they expect
<lb n="10169"/> Maria to crack nuts without a nutcracker. But Maria said she
<lb n="10170"/> didn't like nuts and that they weren't to bother about her.
<lb n="10171"/> Then Joe asked would she take a bottle of stout and Mrs
<lb n="10172"/> Donnelly said there was port wine too in the house if she would
<lb n="10173"/> prefer that. Maria said she would rather they didn't ask her to
<lb n="10174"/> take anything: but Joe insisted.</p>
<lb n="10175"/> <p>So Maria let him have his way and they sat by the fire
<lb n="10176"/> talking over old times and Maria thought she would put in a
<lb n="10177"/> good word for Alphy. But Joe cried that God might strike him
<lb n="10178"/> stone dead if ever he spoke a word to his brother again and
<lb n="10179"/> Maria said she was sorry she had mentioned the matter. Mrs
<lb n="10180"/> Donnelly told her husband it was a great shame for him to
<lb n="10181"/> speak that way of his own flesh and blood but Joe said that
<lb n="10182"/> Alphy was no brother of his and there was nearly being a row
<lb n="10183"/> on the head of it. But Joe said he would not lose his temper on
<lb n="10184"/> account of the night it was and asked his wife to open some
<lb n="10185"/> more stout. The two nextdoor girls had arranged some Hallow
<lb n="10186"/> Eve games and soon everything was merry again. Maria was
<lb n="10187"/> delighted to see the children so merry and Joe and his wife
<lb n="10188"/> in such good spirits. The nextdoor girls put some saucers
<lb n="10189"/> on the table and then led the children up to the table, blind=
<lb n="10190"/> fold. One got the prayerbook and the other three got the water;
<lb n="10191"/> and when one of the nextdoor girls got the ring Mrs Donnelly
<lb n="10192"/> shook her finger at the blushing girl as much as to say: <emph>O, I
<lb n="10193"/> know all about it!</emph> They insisted then on blindfolding Maria
<lb n="10194"/> and leading her up to the table to see what she would get;
<lb n="10195"/> and, while they were putting on the bandage, Maria laughed
<lb n="10196"/> and laughed again till the tip of her nose nearly met the tip of
<lb n="10197"/> her chin.</p>
<lb n="10198"/> <p>They led her up to the table amid laughing and joking and
<lb n="10199"/> she put her hand out in the air as she was told to do. She
<lb n="10200"/> moved her hand about here and there in the air and descended
<lb n="10201"/> on one of the saucers. She felt a soft wet substance with her
<lb n="10202"/> fingers and was surprised that nobody spoke or took off her
<lb n="10203"/> bandage. There was a pause for a few seconds and then a great
<lb n="10204"/> deal of scuffling and whispering. Somebody said something
<lb n="10205"/> about the garden and at last Mrs Donnelly said something very
<lb n="10206"/> cross to one of the nextdoor girls and told her to throw it out
<lb n="10207"/> at once: that was no play. Maria understood that it was wrong
<lb n="10208"/> that time and so she had to do it over again: and this time she
<lb n="10209"/> got the prayerbook.</p>
<lb n="10210"/> <p>After that Mrs Donnelly played Miss McCloud's Reel for
<lb n="10211"/> the children and Joe made Maria take a glass of wine. Soon
<lb n="10212"/> they were all quite merry again and Mrs Donnelly said Maria
<lb n="10213"/> would enter a convent before the year was out because she had
<lb n="10214"/> got the prayerbook. Maria had never seen Joe so nice to her as
<lb n="10215"/> he was that night, so full of pleasant talk and reminiscences.
<lb n="10216"/> She said they were all very good to her.</p>
<lb n="10217"/> <p>At last the children grew tired and sleepy and Joe asked
<lb n="10218"/> Maria would she not sing some little song before she went, one
<lb n="10219"/> of the old songs. Mrs Donnelly said <emph>Do, please, Maria!</emph> and so
<lb n="10220"/> Maria had to get up and stand beside the piano. Mrs Donnelly
<lb n="10221"/> bade the children be quiet and listen to Maria's song. Then she
<lb n="10222"/> played the prelude and said <emph>Now, Maria!</emph> and Maria, blushing
<lb n="10223"/> very much, began to sing in a tiny quavering voice. She sang <emph>I
<lb n="10224"/> dreamt that I dwelt</emph> and when she came to the second verse she
<lb n="10225"/> sang again:</p>
<lb n="10226"/> <p><emph>I dreamt that I dwelt in marble halls
<lb n="10227"/> With vassals and serfs at my side
<lb n="10228"/> And of all who assembled within those walls
<lb n="10229"/> That I was the hope and the pride.
<lb n="10230"/> I had riches too great to count, could boast
<lb n="10231"/> Of a high ancestral name,
<lb n="10232"/> But I also dreamt, which pleased me most,
<lb n="10233"/> That you loved me still the same.</emph></p>
<lb n="10234"/> <p>But no one tried to show her her mistake and, when she had
<lb n="10235"/> ended her song, Joe was very much moved. He said that there
<lb n="10236"/> was no time like the long ago and no music for him like poor
<lb n="10237"/> old Balfe, whatever other people might say; and his eyes filled
<lb n="10238"/> up so much with tears that he could not find what he was
<lb n="10239"/> looking for and in the end he had to ask his wife to tell him
<lb n="10240"/> where the corkscrew was.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->