<div n="11" type="story"><lb n="11000"/> <head rend="italics">A Painful Case</head>
  <lb n="11001"/> <p><persName xml:id="jd">Mr James Duffy</persName> lived in <place> <location> <geo> 53.347271 -6.342888 </geo> </location> <placeName> Chapelizod </placeName> </place> because he wished to
<lb n="11002"/> live as far as possible from the city of which he was a citizen
<lb n="11003"/> and because he found all the other suburbs of Dublin mean,
<lb n="11004"/> modern and pretentious. He lived in an old sombre house and
<lb n="11005"/> from his windows he could look into the disused distillery or
<lb n="11006"/> upwards along the shallow river on which Dublin is built. The
<lb n="11007"/> lofty walls of his uncarpeted room were free from pictures. He
<lb n="11008"/> had himself bought every article of furniture in the room: a
<lb n="11009"/> black iron bedstead, an iron washstand, four cane chairs, a
<lb n="11010"/> clothesrack, a coalscuttle, a fender and irons and a square table
<lb n="11011"/> on which lay a double desk. A bookcase had been made in an
<lb n="11012"/> alcove by means of shelves of white wood. The bed was
<lb n="11013"/> clothed with white bedclothes and a black and scarlet rug
<lb n="11014"/> covered the foot. A little handmirror hung above the washstand
<lb n="11015"/> and during the day a whiteshaded lamp stood as the sole
<lb n="11016"/> ornament of the mantelpiece. The books on the white wooden
<lb n="11017"/> shelves were arranged from below upwards according to bulk.
<lb n="11018"/> A complete Wordsworth stood at one end of the lowest shelf
<lb n="11019"/> and a copy of the Maynooth catechism, sewn into the cloth
<lb n="11020"/> cover of a notebook, stood at one end of the top shelf. Writing
<lb n="11021"/> materials were always on the desk. In the desk lay a manuscript
<lb n="11022"/> translation of Hauptmann's <emph>Michael Kramer</emph>, the stage direc=
<lb n="11023"/> tions of which were written in purple ink, and a little sheaf of
<lb n="11024"/> papers held together by a brass pin. In these sheets a sentence
<lb n="11025"/> was inscribed from time to time and, in an ironical moment,
<lb n="11026"/> the headline of an advertisement for bile beans had been pasted
<lb n="11027"/> on to the first sheet. On lifting the lid of the desk a faint
<lb n="11028"/> fragrance escaped - the fragrance of new cedarwood pencils or
<lb n="11029"/> of a bottle of gum or of an overripe apple which might have
<lb n="11030"/> been left there and forgotten.</p>
<lb n="11031"/> <p>Mr Duffy abhorred anything which betokened physical or
<lb n="11032"/> mental disorder. A medieval doctor would have called him
<lb n="11033"/> saturnine. His face, which carried the entire tale of his years,
<lb n="11034"/> was of the brown tint of Dublin streets. On his long and rather
<lb n="11035"/> large head grew dry black hair and a tawny moustache did not
<lb n="11036"/> quite cover an unamiable mouth. His cheekbones also gave his
<lb n="11037"/> face a harsh character but there was no harshness in the eyes
<lb n="11038"/> which, looking at the world from under their tawny eyebrows,
<lb n="11039"/> gave the impression of a man ever alert to greet a redeeming
<lb n="11040"/> instinct in others but often disappointed. He lived at a little
<lb n="11041"/> distance from his body, regarding his own acts with doubtful
<lb n="11042"/> sideglances. He had an odd autobiographical habit which led
<lb n="11043"/> him to compose in his mind from time to time a short sentence
<lb n="11044"/> about himself containing a subject in the third person and a
<lb n="11045"/> predicate in the past tense. He never gave alms to beggars and
<lb n="11046"/> walked firmly, carrying a stout hazel.</p>
<lb n="11047"/> <p>He had been for many years cashier of a private bank in
<lb n="11048"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.337933 -6.252487 </geo> </location> <placeName> Baggot Street </placeName> </place>. Every morning he came in from <place> <location> <geo> 53.347271 -6.342888 </geo> </location> <placeName> Chapelizod </placeName> </place> by
<lb n="11049"/> tram. At midday he went to <place> <location> <geo> 53.3363 -6.248155 </geo> </location> <placeName> Dan Burke's </placeName> </place> and took his lunch, a
<lb n="11050"/> bottle of lager beer and a small trayful of arrowroot biscuits.
<lb n="11051"/> At four o'clock he was set free. He dined in an eatinghouse in
<lb n="11052"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.34306 -6.264439 </geo> </location> <placeName> George's Street </placeName> </place> where he felt himself safe from the society of
<lb n="11053"/> Dublin's gilded youth and where there was a certain plain
<lb n="11054"/> honesty in the bill of fare. His evenings were spent either before
<lb n="11055"/> his landlady's piano or roaming about the outskirts of the city.
<lb n="11056"/> His liking for Mozart's music brought him sometimes to an
<lb n="11057"/> opera or a concert: these were the only dissipations of his life.</p>
<lb n="11058"/> <p>He had neither companions nor friends, church nor creed.
<lb n="11059"/> He lived his spiritual life without any communion with others,
<lb n="11060"/> visiting his relatives at Christmas and escorting them to the
<lb n="11061"/> cemetery when they died. He performed these two social duties
<lb n="11062"/> for old dignity' sake but conceded nothing further to the
<lb n="11063"/> conventions which regulate the civic life. He allowed himself to
<lb n="11064"/> think that in certain circumstances he would rob his bank but
<lb n="11065"/> as these circumstances never arose his life rolled out evenly -
<lb n="11066"/> an adventureless tale.</p>
<lb n="11067"/> <p>One evening he found himself sitting beside two ladies in the
<lb n="11068"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.352692 -6.262035 </geo> </location> <placeName> Rotunda </placeName> </place>. The house, thinly peopled and silent, gave distressing
<lb n="11069"/> prophecy of failure. The lady who sat next him looked round
<lb n="11070"/> at the deserted house once or twice and then said:
<lb n="11071"/> <said who="">―</said>What a pity there is such a poor house tonight! It's so hard
<lb n="11072"/> on people to have to sing to empty benches.</p>
<lb n="11073"/> <p>He took the remark as an invitation to talk. He was sur=
<lb n="11074"/> prised that she seemed so little awkward. While they talked he
<lb n="11075"/> tried to fix her permanently in his memory. When he learned
<lb n="11076"/> that the young girl beside her was her daughter he judged her
<lb n="11077"/> to be a year or so younger than himself. Her face, which must
<lb n="11078"/> have been handsome, had remained intelligent. It was an oval
<lb n="11079"/> face with strongly marked features. The eyes were very dark
<lb n="11080"/> blue and steady. Their gaze began with a defiant note but was
<lb n="11081"/> confused by what seemed a deliberate swoon of the pupil into
<lb n="11082"/> the iris, revealing for an instant a temperament of great sensi=
<lb n="11083"/> bility. The pupil reasserted itself quickly, this half disclosed
<lb n="11084"/> nature fell again under the reign of prudence, and her astra=
<lb n="11085"/> khan jacket, moulding a bosom of a certain fulness, struck the
<lb n="11086"/> note of defiance more definitely.</p>
<lb n="11087"/> <p>He met her again a few weeks afterwards at a concert in
<lb n="11088"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.334503 -6.257424 </geo> </location> <placeName> Earlsfort Terrace </placeName> </place> and seized the moments when her daughter's
<lb n="11089"/> attention was diverted to become intimate. She alluded once or
<lb n="11090"/> twice to her husband but her tone was not such as to make the
  <lb n="11091"/> allusion a warning. Her name was <persName xml:id="msi">Mrs Sinico</persName>. Her husband's
<lb n="11092"/> great-great-grandfather had come from <place> <location> <geo> 43.551876 10.308011 </geo> </location> <placeName> Leghorn </placeName> </place>. Her husband
<lb n="11093"/> was captain of a mercantile boat plying between Dublin and
<lb n="11094"/> <place> <location> <geo> 52.281601 4.570313 </geo> </location> <placeName> Holland </placeName> </place>: and they had one child.</p>
<lb n="11095"/> <p>Meeting her a third time by accident he found courage to
<lb n="11096"/> make an appointment. She came. This was the first of many
<lb n="11097"/> meetings; they met always in the evening and chose the most
  <lb n="11098"/> quiet quarters for their walks together. <persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName>, however,
<lb n="11099"/> had a distaste for underhand ways and, finding that they were
<lb n="11100"/> compelled to meet stealthily, he forced her to ask him to her
<lb n="11101"/> house. <persName xml:id="si">Captain Sinico</persName> encouraged his visits, thinking that his
<lb n="11102"/> daughter's hand was in question. He had dismissed his wife so
<lb n="11103"/> sincerely from his gallery of pleasures that he did not suspect
<lb n="11104"/> anyone else would take an interest in her. As the husband was
<lb n="11105"/> often away and the daughter out giving music lessons <persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName>
<lb n="11106"/> had many opportunities of enjoying the lady's society. Neither
<lb n="11107"/> he nor she had had any such adventure before and neither was
<lb n="11108"/> conscious of any incongruity. Little by little he entangled his
<lb n="11109"/> thoughts with hers. He lent her books, provided her with ideas,
<lb n="11110"/> shared his intellectual life with her. She listened to all.</p>
<lb n="11111"/> <p>Sometimes in return for his theories she gave out some fact
<lb n="11112"/> of her own life. With almost maternal solicitude she urged him
<lb n="11113"/> to let his nature open to the full; she became his confessor. He
<lb n="11114"/> told her that for some time he had assisted at the meetings of
<lb n="11115"/> an Irish Socialist Party where he had felt himself a unique
<lb n="11116"/> figure amid a score of sober workmen in a garret lit by an
<lb n="11117"/> inefficient oillamp. When the party had divided into three
<lb n="11118"/> sections, each under its own leader and in its own garret, he
<lb n="11119"/> had discontinued his attendances. The workmen's discussions,
<lb n="11120"/> he said, were too timorous; the interest they took in the
<lb n="11121"/> question of wages was inordinate. He felt that they were
<lb n="11122"/> hardfeatured realists and that they resented an exactitude
<lb n="11123"/> which was the product of a leisure not within their reach. No
<lb n="11124"/> social revolution, he told her, would be likely to strike Dublin
<lb n="11125"/> for some centuries.</p>
<lb n="11126"/> <p>She asked him why did he not write out his thoughts. For
<lb n="11127"/> what? he asked her with careful scorn. To compete with
<lb n="11128"/> phrase mongers, incapable of thinking consecutively for sixty
<lb n="11129"/> seconds? To submit himself to the criticisms of an obtuse
<lb n="11130"/> middle class which entrusted its morality to policemen and its
<lb n="11131"/> fine arts to impresarios?</p>
<lb n="11132"/> <p>He went often to her little cottage outside Dublin: often they
<lb n="11133"/> spent their evenings alone. Little by little as their thoughts
<lb n="11134"/> entangled they spoke of subjects less remote. Her companion=
<lb n="11135"/> ship was like a warm soil about an exotic. Many times she
<lb n="11136"/> allowed the dark to fall upon them, refraining from lighting the
<lb n="11137"/> lamp. The dark discreet room, their isolation, the music that
<lb n="11138"/> still vibrated in their ears united them. This union exalted him,
<lb n="11139"/> wore away the rough edges of his character, emotionalised his
<lb n="11140"/> mental life. Sometimes he caught himself listening to the sound
<lb n="11141"/> of his own voice. He thought that in her eyes he would ascend
<lb n="11142"/> to an angelical stature; and as he attached the fervent nature of
<lb n="11143"/> his companion more and more closely to him he heard the
<lb n="11144"/> strange impersonal voice, which he recognised as his own,
<lb n="11145"/> insisting on the soul's incurable loneliness. We cannot give
<lb n="11146"/> ourselves, it said: we are our own. The end of these discourses
<lb n="11147"/> was that one night, during which she had shown every sign of
  <lb n="11148"/> unusual excitement, <persName xml:id="msi">Mrs Sinico</persName> caught up his hand passion=
<lb n="11149"/> ately and pressed it to her cheek.</p>
  <lb n="11150"/> <p><persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName> was very much surprised. Her interpretation of his
<lb n="11151"/> words disillusioned him. He did not visit her for a week; then
<lb n="11152"/> he wrote to her asking her to meet him. As he did not wish
<lb n="11153"/> their last interview to be troubled by the influence of their
<lb n="11154"/> ruined confessional they met in a little cakeshop near the
<lb n="11155"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.349476 -6.301603 </geo> </location> <placeName> Parkgate </placeName> </place>. It was cold autumn weather but in spite of the cold
<lb n="11156"/> they wandered up and down the roads of the Park for nearly
<lb n="11157"/> three hours. They agreed to break off their intercourse: every
<lb n="11158"/> bond, he said, is a bond to sorrow. When they came out of the
<lb n="11159"/> Park they walked in silence towards the tram but here she
<lb n="11160"/> began to tremble so violently that, fearing another collapse on
<lb n="11161"/> her part, he bade her goodbye quickly and left her. A few days
<lb n="11162"/> later he received a parcel containing his books and music.</p>
  <lb n="11163"/> <p>Four years passed. <persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName> returned to his even way of life.
<lb n="11164"/> His room still bore witness of the orderliness of his mind. Some
<lb n="11165"/> new pieces of music encumbered the musicstand in the lower
<lb n="11166"/> room and on his shelves stood two volumes by Nietzsche, <emph>Thus
<lb n="11167"/> Spake Zarathustra</emph> and <emph>The Gay Science.</emph> He wrote seldom in
<lb n="11168"/> the sheaf of papers which lay in his desk. One of his sentences,
<lb n="11169"/> written two months after his last interview with <persName xml:id="msi">Mrs Sinico</persName>,
<lb n="11170"/> read: Love between man and man is impossible because there
<lb n="11171"/> must not be sexual intercourse and friendship between man
<lb n="11172"/> and woman is impossible because there must be sexual inter=
<lb n="11173"/> course. He kept away from concerts lest he should meet her.
<lb n="11174"/> His father died; the junior partner of the bank retired. And still
<lb n="11175"/> every morning he went into the city by tram and every evening
<lb n="11176"/> walked home from the city after having dined moderately in
<lb n="11177"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.34306 -6.264439 </geo> </location> <placeName> George's Street </placeName> </place> and read the evening paper for dessert.</p>
<lb n="11178"/> <p>One evening as he was about to put a morsel of corned beef
<lb n="11179"/> and cabbage into his mouth his hand stopped. His eyes fixed
<lb n="11180"/> themselves on a paragraph in the evening paper which he had
<lb n="11181"/> propped against the watercroft. He replaced the morsel of food
<lb n="11182"/> on his plate and read the paragraph attentively. Then he drank
<lb n="11183"/> a glass of water, pushed his plate to one side, doubled the paper
<lb n="11184"/> down before him between his elbows and read the paragraph
<lb n="11185"/> over and over again. The cabbage began to deposit a cold white
<lb n="11186"/> grease on his plate. The girl came over to him to ask was his
<lb n="11187"/> dinner not properly cooked. He said it was very good and ate a
<lb n="11188"/> few mouthfuls of it with difficulty. Then he paid his bill and
<lb n="11189"/> went out.</p>
<lb n="11190"/> <p>He walked along quickly through the November twilight,
<lb n="11191"/> his stout hazel stick striking the ground regularly, the fringe of
<lb n="11192"/> the buff <emph>Mail</emph> peeping out of a sidepocket of his tight reefer
<lb n="11193"/> overcoat. On the lonely road which leads from the <place> <location> <geo> 53.349476 -6.301603 </geo> </location> <placeName> Parkgate </placeName> </place> to
<lb n="11194"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.347271 -6.342888 </geo> </location> <placeName> Chapelizod </placeName> </place> he slackened his pace. His stick struck the ground
<lb n="11195"/> less emphatically and his breath, issuing irregularly, almost
<lb n="11196"/> with a sighing sound, condensed in the wintry air. When he
<lb n="11197"/> reached his house he went up at once to his bedroom and,
<lb n="11198"/> taking the paper from his pocket, read the paragraph again by
<lb n="11199"/> the failing light of the window. He read it not aloud but
<lb n="11200"/> moving his lips as a priest does when he reads the prayer <emph>In
<lb n="11201"/> Secretis.</emph> This was the paragraph:</p>
<lb n="11202"/> <p>DEATH OF A LADY AT SYDNEY PARADE
<lb n="11203"/> A PAINFUL CASE</p>
<lb n="11204"/> <p>Today at the <place> <location> <geo> 53.333538 -6.244239 </geo> </location> <placeName> City of Dublin Hospital </placeName> </place> the Deputy Coroner (in
  <lb n="11205"/> the absence of <persName xml:id="le">Mr Leverett</persName>) held an inquest on the body of <persName xml:id="msi">Mrs
  <lb n="11206"/> Emily Sinico</persName>, aged forty-three years, who was killed at Sydney
<lb n="11207"/> Parade Station yesterday evening. The evidence showed that
<lb n="11208"/> the deceased lady while attempting to cross the line was
<lb n="11209"/> knocked down by the engine of the ten o'clock slow train from
<lb n="11210"/> Kingstown, thereby sustaining injuries of the head and right
<lb n="11211"/> side which led to her death.</p>
  <lb n="11212"/> <p><persName xml:id="jl">James Lennon</persName>, driver of the engine, stated that he had been
<lb n="11213"/> in the employment of the railway company for fifteen years.
<lb n="11214"/> On hearing the guard's whistle he set the train in motion and a
<lb n="11215"/> second or two afterwards brought it to rest in response to loud
<lb n="11216"/> cries. The train was going slowly.</p>
  <lb n="11217"/> <p><persName xml:id="pd">P. Dunne</persName>, railway porter, stated that as the train was about
<lb n="11218"/> to start he observed a woman attempting to cross the lines. He
<lb n="11219"/> ran towards her and shouted but before he could reach her she
<lb n="11220"/> was caught by the buffer of the engine and fell to the ground.</p>
<lb n="11221"/> <p>A Juror - You saw the lady fall?</p>
<lb n="11222"/> <p>Witness - Yes.</p>
  <lb n="11223"/> <p>Police Sergeant <persName xml:id="cy">Croly</persName> deposed that when he arrived he found
<lb n="11224"/> the deceased lying on the platform apparently dead. He had the
<lb n="11225"/> body taken to the waitingroom pending the arrival of the
<lb n="11226"/> ambulance.</p>
<lb n="11227"/> <p>Constable 57 E corroborated.</p>
  <lb n="11228"/> <p><persName xml:id="hn">Dr Halpin</persName>, assistant house surgeon of the City of Dublin
<lb n="11229"/> Hospital, stated that the deceased had two lower ribs fractured
<lb n="11230"/> and had sustained severe contusions of the right shoulder. The
<lb n="11231"/> right side of the head had been injured in the fall. The injuries
<lb n="11232"/> were not sufficient to have caused death in a normal person.
<lb n="11233"/> Death, in his opinion, had been probably due to shock and
<lb n="11234"/> sudden failure of the heart's action.</p>
  <lb n="11235"/> <p>Mr <persName xml:id="hb">H. B. Patterson Finlay</persName>, on behalf of the railway com=
<lb n="11236"/> pany, expressed his deep regret at the accident. The company
<lb n="11237"/> had always taken every precaution to prevent people crossing
<lb n="11238"/> the lines except by the bridges, both by placing notices in every
<lb n="11239"/> station and by the use of patent spring gates at level crossings.
<lb n="11240"/> The deceased had been in the habit of crossing the lines late at
<lb n="11241"/> night from platform to platform and, in view of certain other
<lb n="11242"/> circumstances of the case, he did not think the railway officials
<lb n="11243"/> were to blame.</p>
  <lb n="11244"/> <p><persName xml:id="si">Captain Sinico</persName>, of Leoville, Sydney Parade, husband of the
<lb n="11245"/> deceased, also gave evidence. He stated that the deceased was
<lb n="11246"/> his wife. He was not in Dublin at the time of the accident as he
<lb n="11247"/> had arrived only that morning from <place> <location> <geo> 51.924217 4.481776 </geo> </location> <placeName> Rotterdam </placeName> </place>. They had been
<lb n="11248"/> married for twenty-two years and had lived happily until about
<lb n="11249"/> two years ago when his wife began to be rather intemperate in
<lb n="11250"/> her habits.</p>
  <lb n="11251"/> <p><persName xml:id="ssi">Miss Mary Sinico</persName> said that of late her mother had been in
<lb n="11252"/> the habit of going out at night to buy spirits. She, witness, had
<lb n="11253"/> often tried to reason with her mother and had induced her to
<lb n="11254"/> join a league. She was not at home until an hour after the
<lb n="11255"/> accident.</p>
<lb n="11256"/> <p>The jury returned a verdict in accordance with the medical
  <lb n="11257"/> evidence and exonerated <persName xml:id="jl">Lennon</persName> from all blame.</p>
  <lb n="11258"/> <p>The Deputy <persName xml:id="co">Coroner</persName> said it was a most painful case and
  <lb n="11259"/> expressed great sympathy with <persName xml:id="si">Captain Sinico</persName> and his daugh=
<lb n="11260"/> ter. He urged on the railway company to take strong measures
<lb n="11261"/> to prevent the possibility of similar accidents in the future. No
<lb n="11262"/> blame attached to anyone.</p>
<lb /> 
  <lb n="11263"/> <p><persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName> raised his eyes from the paper and gazed out of his
<lb n="11264"/> window on the cheerless evening landscape. The river lay quiet
<lb n="11265"/> beside the empty distillery and from time to time a light
<lb n="11266"/> appeared in some house on the <place> <location> <geo> 53.351372 -6.352844 </geo> </location> <placeName> Lucan road </placeName> </place>. What an end! The
<lb n="11267"/> whole narrative of her death revolted him and it revolted him
<lb n="11268"/> to think that he had ever spoken to her of what he held sacred.
<lb n="11269"/> The threadbare phrases, the inane expressions of sympathy, the
<lb n="11270"/> cautious words of a reporter won over to conceal the details of
<lb n="11271"/> a commonplace vulgar death attacked his stomach. Not merely
<lb n="11272"/> had she degraded herself; she had degraded him. He saw the
<lb n="11273"/> squalid tract of her vice, miserable and malodorous. His soul's
<lb n="11274"/> companion! He thought of the hobbling wretches whom he had
<lb n="11275"/> seen carrying cans and bottles to be filled by the barman. Just
<lb n="11276"/> God, what an end! Evidently she had been unfit to live, without
<lb n="11277"/> any strength of purpose, an easy prey to habits, one of the
<lb n="11278"/> wrecks on which civilisation has been reared. But that she
<lb n="11279"/> could have sunk so low! Was it possible he had deceived him=
<lb n="11280"/> self so utterly about her? He remembered her outburst of that
<lb n="11281"/> night and interpreted it in a harsher sense than he had ever
<lb n="11282"/> done. He had no difficulty now in approving of the course he
<lb n="11283"/> had taken.</p>
<lb n="11284"/> <p>As the light failed and his memory began to wander he
<lb n="11285"/> thought her hand touched his. The shock which had first at=
<lb n="11286"/> tacked his stomach was now attacking his nerves. He put on
<lb n="11287"/> his overcoat and hat quickly and went out. The cold air met
<lb n="11288"/> him on the threshold; it crept into the sleeves of his coat. When
<lb n="11289"/> he came to the publichouse at <place> <location> <geo> 53.347271 -6.342888 </geo> </location> <placeName> Chapelizod </placeName> </place> Bridge he went in
<lb n="11290"/> and ordered a hot punch.</p>
<lb n="11291"/> <p>The proprietor served him obsequiously but did not venture
<lb n="11292"/> to talk. There were five or six workingmen in the shop
<lb n="11293"/> discussing the value of a gentleman's estate in <place> <location> <geo> 53.159828 -6.908998 </geo> </location> <placeName> county Kildare </placeName> </place>.
<lb n="11294"/> They drank at intervals from their huge pint tumblers and
<lb n="11295"/> smoked, spitting often on the floor and sometimes dragging the
<lb n="11296"/> sawdust over their spits with their heavy boots. <persName xml:id="jd">Mr Duffy</persName> sat
<lb n="11297"/> on his stool and gazed at them, without seeing or hearing them.
<lb n="11298"/> After a while they went out and he called for another punch.
<lb n="11299"/> He sat a long time over it. The shop was very quiet. The
<lb n="11300"/> proprietor sprawled on the counter reading the <emph>Herald</emph> and
<lb n="11301"/> yawning. Now and again a tram was heard swishing along the
<lb n="11302"/> lonely road outside.</p>
<lb n="11303"/> <p>As he sat there, living over his life with her and evoking
<lb n="11304"/> alternately the two images in which he now conceived her, he
<lb n="11305"/> realised that she was dead, that she had ceased to exist, that she
<lb n="11306"/> had become a memory. He began to feel ill at ease. He asked
<lb n="11307"/> himself what else could he have done. He could not have
<lb n="11308"/> carried on a comedy of deception with her; he could not have
<lb n="11309"/> lived with her openly. He had done what seemed to him best.
<lb n="11310"/> How was he to blame? Now that she was gone he understood
<lb n="11311"/> how lonely her life must have been, sitting night after night
<lb n="11312"/> alone in that room. His life would be lonely too until he, too,
<lb n="11313"/> died, ceased to exist, became a memory - if anyone remembered
<lb n="11314"/> him.</p>
<lb n="11315"/> <p>It was after nine o'clock when he left the shop. The night
<lb n="11316"/> was cold and gloomy. He entered the Park by the first gate and
<lb n="11317"/> walked along under the gaunt trees. He walked through the
<lb n="11318"/> bleak alleys where they had walked four years before. She
<lb n="11319"/> seemed to be near him in the darkness. At moments he seemed
<lb n="11320"/> to feel her voice touch his ear, her hand touch his. He stood
<lb n="11321"/> still to listen. Why had he withheld life from her? Why had he
<lb n="11322"/> sentenced her to death? He felt his moral nature falling to
<lb n="11323"/> pieces.</p>
<lb n="11324"/> <p>When he gained the crest of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.349422 -6.309242 </geo> </location> <placeName> Magazine Hill </placeName> </place> he halted and
<lb n="11325"/> looked along the river towards Dublin, the lights of which
<lb n="11326"/> burned redly and hospitably in the cold night. He looked down
<lb n="11327"/> the slope and at the base, in the shadow of the wall of the Park,
<lb n="11328"/> he saw some human figures lying. Those venal and furtive loves
<lb n="11329"/> filled him with despair. He gnawed the rectitude of his life; he
<lb n="11330"/> felt that he had been outcast from life's feast. One human being
<lb n="11331"/> had seemed to love him and he had denied her life and
<lb n="11332"/> happiness: he had sentenced her to ignominy, a death of shame.
<lb n="11333"/> He knew that the prostrate creatures down by the wall were
<lb n="11334"/> watching him and wished him gone. No-one wanted him; he
<lb n="11335"/> was outcast from life's feast. He turned his eyes to the grey
<lb n="11336"/> gleaming river, winding along towards Dublin. Beyond the
<lb n="11337"/> river he saw a goods train winding out of <place> <location> <geo> 53.346554 -6.294823 </geo> </location> <placeName> Kingsbridge Station </placeName> </place>,
<lb n="11338"/> like a worm with a fiery head winding through the darkness
<lb n="11339"/> obstinately and laboriously. It passed slowly out of sight but
<lb n="11340"/> still he heard in his ears the laborious drone of the engine
<lb n="11341"/> reiterating the syllables of her name.</p>
<lb n="11342"/> <p>He turned back the way he had come, the rhythm of the
<lb n="11343"/> engine pounding in his ears. He began to doubt the reality of
<lb n="11344"/> what memory told him. He halted under a tree and allowed the
<lb n="11345"/> rhythm to die away. He could not feel her near him in the
<lb n="11346"/> darkness nor her voice touch his ear. He waited for some
<lb n="11347"/> minutes, listening. He could hear nothing: the night was per=
<lb n="11348"/> fectly silent. He listened again: perfectly silent. He felt that he
<lb n="11349"/> was alone.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
