<div n="13" type="story"><lb n="13000"/> <head rend="italics">A Mother</head>
  <lb n="13001"/> <p><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>, assistant secretary of the <emph>Eire Abu</emph> Society, had
<lb n="13002"/> been walking up and down Dublin for nearly a month, with his
<lb n="13003"/> hands and pockets full of dirty pieces of paper, arranging about
<lb n="13004"/> the series of concerts. He had a game leg and for this his friends
<lb n="13005"/> called him Hoppy Holohan. He walked up and down con=
<lb n="13006"/> stantly, stood by the hour at street corners arguing the point,
  <lb n="13007"/> and made notes: but in the end it was <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> who ar=
<lb n="13008"/> ranged everything.</p>
  <lb n="13009"/> <p><persName xml:id="de">Miss Devlin</persName> had become <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> out of spite. She had
<lb n="13010"/> been educated in a high-class convent where she had learned
<lb n="13011"/> French and music. As she was naturally pale and unbending in
<lb n="13012"/> manner she made few friends at school. When she came to the
<lb n="13013"/> age of marriage she was sent out to many houses where her
<lb n="13014"/> playing and ivory manners were much admired. She sat amid
<lb n="13015"/> the chilly circle of her accomplishments, waiting for some
<lb n="13016"/> suitor to brave it and offer her a brilliant life. But the young
<lb n="13017"/> men whom she met were ordinary and she gave them no
<lb n="13018"/> encouragement, trying to console her romantic desires by eat=
<lb n="13019"/> ing a great deal of Turkish Delight in secret. However, when
<lb n="13020"/> she drew near the limit and her friends began to loosen their
<lb n="13021"/> tongues about her she silenced them by marrying <persName xml:id="mke">Mr Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13022"/> who was a bootmaker on Ormond Quay.</p>
<lb n="13023"/> <p>He was much older than she. His conversation, which was
<lb n="13024"/> serious, took place at intervals in his great brown beard. After
  <lb n="13025"/> the first years of married life <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> perceived that such a
<lb n="13026"/> man would wear better than a romantic person but she never
<lb n="13027"/> put her own romantic ideas away. He was sober, thrifty and
<lb n="13028"/> pious: he went to the altar every first Friday, sometimes with
<lb n="13029"/> her, oftener by himself. But she never weakened in her religion
<lb n="13030"/> and was a good wife to him. At some party in a strange house
<lb n="13031"/> when she lifted her eyebrow ever so slightly he stood up to take
<lb n="13032"/> his leave and when his cough troubled him she put the eider=
<lb n="13033"/> down quilt over his feet and made a strong rum punch. For his
<lb n="13034"/> part he was a model father. By paying a small sum every week
<lb n="13035"/> into a society he insured for both his daughters a dowry of one
<lb n="13036"/> hundred pounds each when they came to the age of twenty=
  <lb n="13037"/> four. He sent the elder daughter, <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName>, to a good convent
<lb n="13038"/> where she learned French and music and afterwards paid her
<lb n="13039"/> fees at the Academy. Every year in the month of July <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13040"/> Kearney</persName> found occasion to say to some friend:
<lb n="13041"/> <said who="">―</said>My good man is packing us off to Skerries for a few weeks.</p>
<lb n="13042"/> <p>If it was not Skerries it was Howth or Greystones.</p>
<lb n="13043"/> <p>When the Irish Revival began to be appreciable <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13044"/> determined to take advantage of her daughter's name and
  <lb n="13045"/> brought an Irish teacher to the house. <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> and her sister
<lb n="13046"/> sent Irish picture postcards to their friends and these friends
<lb n="13047"/> sent back other Irish picture postcards. On special Sundays
  <lb n="13048"/> when <persName xml:id="mke">Mr Kearney</persName> went with his family to the pro-cathedral a
<lb n="13049"/> little crowd of people would assemble after mass at the corner
<lb n="13050"/> of Cathedral Street. They were all friends of the Kearneys,
<lb n="13051"/> musical friends or nationalist friends: and when they had
<lb n="13052"/> played every little counter of gossip they shook hands with one
<lb n="13053"/> another all together, laughing at the crossing of so many hands,
<lb n="13054"/> and said goodbye to one another in Irish. Soon the name of
  <lb n="13055"/> Miss <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen Kearney</persName> began to be heard often on people's
<lb n="13056"/> lips. People said that she was very clever at music and a very
<lb n="13057"/> nice girl and, moreover, that she was a believer in the language
  <lb n="13058"/> movement. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> was well content at this. Therefore
  <lb n="13059"/> she was not surprised when one day <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> came to her
<lb n="13060"/> and proposed that her daughter should be the accompanist at a
<lb n="13061"/> series of four grand concerts which his Society was going to
<lb n="13062"/> give in the Antient Concert Rooms. She brought him into the
<lb n="13063"/> drawingroom, made him sit down and brought out the de=
<lb n="13064"/> canter and the silver biscuit-barrel. She entered heart and soul
<lb n="13065"/> into the details of the enterprise, advised and dissuaded; and
  <lb n="13066"/> finally a contract was drawn up by which <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> was to
<lb n="13067"/> receive eight guineas for her services as accompanist at the four
<lb n="13068"/> grand concerts.</p>
  <lb n="13069"/> <p>As <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> was a novice in such delicate matters as the
<lb n="13070"/> wording of bills and the disposing of items for a programme
  <lb n="13071"/> <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> helped him. She had tact. She knew what <emph>artistes</emph>
<lb n="13072"/> should go into capitals and what <emph>artistes</emph> should go into small
<lb n="13073"/> type. She knew that the first tenor would not like to come on
  <lb n="13074"/> after <persName xml:id="md">Mr Meade</persName>'s comic turn. To keep the audience continually
<lb n="13075"/> diverted she slipped the doubtful items in between the old
  <lb n="13076"/> favourites. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> called to see her every day to have her
<lb n="13077"/> advice on some point. She was invariably friendly and advising:
<lb n="13078"/> homely, in fact. She pushed the decanter towards him, saying:
  <lb n="13079"/> <said who="">―</said>Now, help yourself, Mr <persName xml:id="ho">Holohan</persName>!</p>
<lb n="13080"/> <p>And while he was helping himself she said:
<lb n="13081"/> <said who="">―</said>Don't be afraid! Don't be afraid of it!</p>
  <lb n="13082"/> <p>Everything went on smoothly. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> bought some
<lb n="13083"/> lovely blush-pink charmeuse in Brown Thomas's to let into the
<lb n="13084"/> front of <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName>'s dress. It cost a pretty penny; but there are
<lb n="13085"/> occasions when a little expense is justifiable. She took a dozen
<lb n="13086"/> of two shilling tickets for the final concert and sent them to
<lb n="13087"/> those friends who could not be trusted to come otherwise. She
<lb n="13088"/> forgot nothing and, thanks to her, everything that was to be
<lb n="13089"/> done was done.</p>
<lb n="13090"/> <p>The concerts were to be on Wednesday, Thursday, Friday
  <lb n="13091"/> and Saturday. When <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> arrived with her daughter at
<lb n="13092"/> the Antient Concert Rooms on Wednesday night she did not
<lb n="13093"/> like the look of things. A few young men, wearing bright blue
<lb n="13094"/> badges in their coats, stood idle in the vestibule: none of them
<lb n="13095"/> wore evening dress. She passed by with her daughter and a
<lb n="13096"/> quick glance through the open door of the hall showed her the
<lb n="13097"/> cause of the stewards' idleness. At first she wondered had she
<lb n="13098"/> mistaken the hour. No, it was twenty minutes to eight.</p>
<lb n="13099"/> <p>In the dressingroom behind the stage she was introduced to
  <lb n="13100"/> the secretary of the Society, <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>. She smiled and
<lb n="13101"/> shook his hand. He was a little man with a white vacant face.
<lb n="13102"/> She noticed that he wore his soft brown hat carelessly on the
<lb n="13103"/> side of his head and that his accent was flat. He held a
<lb n="13104"/> programme in his hand and while he was talking to her he
<lb n="13105"/> chewed one end of it into a moist pulp. He seemed to bear
  <lb n="13106"/> disappointments lightly. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> came into the dressing=
<lb n="13107"/> room every few minutes with reports from the boxoffice. The
<lb n="13108"/> <emph>artistes</emph> talked among themselves nervously, glanced from time
<lb n="13109"/> to time at the mirror and rolled and unrolled their music. When
<lb n="13110"/> it was nearly half past eight the few people in the hall began to
<lb n="13111"/> express their desire to be entertained. <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> came in,
<lb n="13112"/> smiled vacantly at the room and said:
<lb n="13113"/> <said who="">―</said>Well now, ladies and gentlemen, I suppose we'd better open
<lb n="13114"/> the ball.</p>
  <lb n="13115"/> <p><persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> rewarded his very flat final syllable with a
<lb n="13116"/> quick stare of contempt and then said to her daughter encour=
<lb n="13117"/> agingly:
<lb n="13118"/> <said who="">―</said>Are you ready, dear?</p>
<lb n="13119"/> <p>When she had an opportunity she called <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> aside
  <lb n="13120"/> and asked him to tell her what it meant. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> did not
<lb n="13121"/> know what it meant. He said that the committee had made a
<lb n="13122"/> mistake in arranging for four concerts: four was too many.
<lb n="13123"/> <said who="">―</said>And the <emph>artistes!</emph> said <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>. Of course they are doing
<lb n="13124"/> their best but really they are no good.</p>
  <lb n="13125"/> <p><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> admitted that the <emph>artistes</emph> were no good but the
<lb n="13126"/> committee, he said, had decided to let the first three concerts go
<lb n="13127"/> as they pleased and reserve all the talent for Saturday night.
  <lb n="13128"/> <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> said nothing but, as the mediocre items followed
<lb n="13129"/> one another on the platform and the few people in the hall
<lb n="13130"/> grew fewer and fewer, she began to regret that she had put
<lb n="13131"/> herself to any expense for such a concert. There was something
<lb n="13132"/> she didn't like in the look of things and <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>'s vacant
<lb n="13133"/> smile irritated her very much. However she said nothing and
<lb n="13134"/> waited to see how it would end. The concert expired shortly
<lb n="13135"/> before ten and everyone went home quickly.</p>
<lb n="13136"/> <p>The concert on Thursday night was better attended but <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13137"/> Kearney</persName> saw at once that the house was filled with paper. The
<lb n="13138"/> audience behaved indecorously as if the concert were an infor=
  <lb n="13139"/> mal dress rehearsal. <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> seemed to enjoy himself; he
  <lb n="13140"/> was quite unconscious that <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> was taking angry note
<lb n="13141"/> of his conduct. He stood at the edge of the screen, from time to
<lb n="13142"/> time jutting out his head and exchanging a laugh with two
<lb n="13143"/> friends in the corner of the balcony. In the course of the
<lb n="13144"/> evening <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> learned that the Friday concert was to be
<lb n="13145"/> abandoned and that the committee was going to move heaven
<lb n="13146"/> and earth to secure a bumper house on Saturday night. When
  <lb n="13147"/> she heard this she sought out <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>. She buttonholed
<lb n="13148"/> him as he was limping out quickly with a glass of lemonade for
<lb n="13149"/> a young lady and asked him was it true. Yes, it was true.
<lb n="13150"/> <said who="">―</said>But, of course, that doesn't alter the contract, she said. The
<lb n="13151"/> contract was for four concerts. ...</p>
  <lb n="13152"/> <p><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> seemed to be in a hurry: he advised her to
  <lb n="13153"/> speak to <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> was now beginning to be
  <lb n="13154"/> alarmed. She called <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> away from his screen and
<lb n="13155"/> told him that her daughter had signed for four concerts and
<lb n="13156"/> that, of course, according to the terms of the contract she
<lb n="13157"/> should receive the sum originally stipulated for whether the
<lb n="13158"/> Society gave the four concerts or not. <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>, who did
<lb n="13159"/> not catch the point at issue very quickly, seemed unable to
<lb n="13160"/> resolve the difficulty and said that he would bring the matter
  <lb n="13161"/> before the committee. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>'s anger began to flutter in
<lb n="13162"/> her cheek and she had all she could do to keep from asking:
<lb n="13163"/> <said who="">―</said>And who is the <emph>cometty</emph>, pray?</p>
<lb n="13164"/> <p>But she knew that it would not be ladylike to do that: so she
<lb n="13165"/> was silent.</p>
<lb n="13166"/> <p>Little boys were sent out into the principal streets of Dublin
<lb n="13167"/> early on Friday morning with bundles of handbills. Special
<lb n="13168"/> puffs appeared in all the evening papers reminding the music=
<lb n="13169"/> loving public of the treat which was in store for it on the
  <lb n="13170"/> following evening. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> was somewhat reassured but
<lb n="13171"/> she thought well to tell her husband part of her suspicions. He
<lb n="13172"/> listened carefully and said that perhaps it would be better if he
<lb n="13173"/> went with her on Saturday night. She agreed. She respected her
<lb n="13174"/> husband in the same way as she respected the General Post
<lb n="13175"/> Office, as something large, secure and fixed; and though she
<lb n="13176"/> knew the small number of his talents she appreciated his
<lb n="13177"/> abstract value as a male. She was glad that he had suggested
<lb n="13178"/> coming with her. She thought her plans over.</p>
  <lb n="13179"/> <p>The night of the grand concert came. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>, with her
<lb n="13180"/> husband and daughter, arrived at the Antient Concert Rooms
<lb n="13181"/> three quarters of an hour before the time at which the concert
<lb n="13182"/> was to begin. By ill luck it was a rainy evening. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13183"/> placed her daughter's clothes and music in charge of her
<lb n="13184"/> husband and went all over the building looking for <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holo=
  <lb n="13185"/> han</persName> or <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>. She could find neither. She asked the
<lb n="13186"/> stewards was any member of the committee in the hall and,
<lb n="13187"/> after a great deal of trouble, a steward brought out a little
  <lb n="13188"/> woman named <persName xml:id="be">Miss Beirne</persName> to whom <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> explained
<lb n="13189"/> that she wanted to see one of the secretaries. <persName xml:id="be">Miss Beirne</persName>
<lb n="13190"/> expected them any minute and asked could she do anything.
  <lb n="13191"/> <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> looked searchingly at the oldish face which was
<lb n="13192"/> screwed into an expression of trustfulness and enthusiasm and
<lb n="13193"/> answered:
<lb n="13194"/> <said who="">―</said>No, thank you!</p>
<lb n="13195"/> <p>The little woman hoped they would have a good house. She
<lb n="13196"/> looked out at the rain until the melancholy of the wet street
<lb n="13197"/> effaced all the trustfulness and enthusiasm from her twisted
<lb n="13198"/> features. Then she gave a little sigh and said:
<lb n="13199"/> <said who="">―</said>Ah, well! We did our best, the dear knows.</p>
  <lb n="13200"/> <p><persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> had to go back to the dressingroom.</p>
<lb n="13201"/> <p>The <emph>artistes</emph> were arriving. The bass and the second tenor
  <lb n="13202"/> had already come. The bass, <persName xml:id="dg">Mr Duggan</persName>, was a slender young
<lb n="13203"/> man with a scattered black moustache. He was the son of a hall
<lb n="13204"/> porter in an office in the city and, as a boy, he had sung
<lb n="13205"/> prolonged bass notes in the resounding hall. From this humble
<lb n="13206"/> state he had raised himself until he had become a first-rate
<lb n="13207"/> <emph>artiste.</emph> He had appeared in grand opera. One night, when an
<lb n="13208"/> operatic <emph>artiste</emph> had fallen ill, he had undertaken the part of the
<lb n="13209"/> king in the opera of <emph>Maritana</emph> at the Queen's Theatre. He sang
<lb n="13210"/> his music with great feeling and volume and was warmly
<lb n="13211"/> welcomed by the gallery; but, unfortunately, he marred the
<lb n="13212"/> good impression by wiping his nose in his gloved hand once or
<lb n="13213"/> twice out of thoughtlessness. He was unassuming and spoke
<lb n="13214"/> little. He said <emph>yous</emph> so softly that it passed unnoticed and he
<lb n="13215"/> never drank anything stronger than milk for his voice' sake. <persName xml:id="bl">Mr
  <lb n="13216"/> Bell</persName>, the second tenor, was a fairhaired little man who com=
<lb n="13217"/> peted every year for prizes at the Feis Ceoil. On his fourth trial
<lb n="13218"/> he had been awarded a bronze medal. He was extremely
<lb n="13219"/> nervous and extremely jealous of other tenors and he covered
<lb n="13220"/> his nervous jealousy with an ebullient friendliness. It was his
<lb n="13221"/> humour to have people know what an ordeal a concert was to
  <lb n="13222"/> him. Therefore when he saw <persName xml:id="dg">Mr Duggan</persName> he went over to him
<lb n="13223"/> and asked:
<lb n="13224"/> <said who="">―</said>Are you in it too?
  <lb n="13225"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, said <persName xml:id="dg">Mr Duggan</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="13226"/> <p><persName xml:id="bl">Mr Bell</persName> laughed at his fellow sufferer, held out his hand and
<lb n="13227"/> said:
<lb n="13228"/> <said who="">―</said>Shake!</p>
  <lb n="13229"/> <p><persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> passed by these two young men and went to
<lb n="13230"/> the edge of the screen to view the house. The seats were being
<lb n="13231"/> filled up rapidly and a pleasant noise circulated in the auditor=
<lb n="13232"/> ium. She came back and spoke to her husband privately. Their
  <lb n="13233"/> conversation was evidently about <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> for they both
<lb n="13234"/> glanced at her often as she stood chatting to one of her nation=
  <lb n="13235"/> alist friends, <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName>, the contralto. An unknown solitary
<lb n="13236"/> woman with a pale face walked through the room. The women
<lb n="13237"/> followed with keen eyes the faded blue dress which was
<lb n="13238"/> stretched upon a meagre body. Someone said that she was
  <lb n="13239"/> <persName xml:id="mg">Madam Glynn</persName>, the soprano.
<lb n="13240"/> <said who="">―</said>I wonder where did they dig her up, said <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> to <persName xml:id="hy">Miss
  <lb n="13241"/> Healy</persName>. I'm sure I never heard of her.</p>
  <lb n="13242"/> <p><persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> had to smile. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> limped into the dress=
<lb n="13243"/> ingroom at that moment and the two young ladies asked him
  <lb n="13244"/> who was the unknown woman. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> said that she was
  <lb n="13245"/> <persName xml:id="mg">Madam Glynn</persName> from London. <persName xml:id="mg">Madam Glynn</persName> took her stand in
<lb n="13246"/> a corner of the room, holding a roll of music stiffly before her
<lb n="13247"/> and from time to time changing the direction of her startled
<lb n="13248"/> gaze. The shadow took her faded dress into shelter but fell
<lb n="13249"/> revengefully into the little cup behind her collarbone. The noise
<lb n="13250"/> of the hall became more audible. The first tenor and the
<lb n="13251"/> baritone arrived together. They were both well dressed, stout
<lb n="13252"/> and complacent and they brought a breath of opulence among
<lb n="13253"/> the company.</p>
  <lb n="13254"/> <p><persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> brought her daughter over to them and talked
<lb n="13255"/> to them amiably. She wanted to be on good terms with them
<lb n="13256"/> but, while she strove to be polite, her eyes followed <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holo=
  <lb n="13257"/> han</persName> in his limping and devious courses. As soon as she could
<lb n="13258"/> she excused herself and went out after him.
  <lb n="13259"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>, I want to speak to you for a moment, she said.</p>
<lb n="13260"/> <p>They went down to a discreet part of the corridor. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13261"/> Kearney</persName> asked him when was her daughter going to be paid.
  <lb n="13262"/> <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> said that <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> had charge of that. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13263"/> Kearney</persName> said that she didn't know anything about <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpat=
  <lb n="13264"/> rick</persName>. Her daughter had signed a contract for eight guineas and
  <lb n="13265"/> she would have to be paid. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> said that it wasn't his
<lb n="13266"/> business.
<lb n="13267"/> <said who="">―</said>Why isn't it your business? asked <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>. Didn't you
<lb n="13268"/> yourself bring her the contract? Anyway, if it's not your
<lb n="13269"/> business it's my business and I mean to see to it.
<lb n="13270"/> <said who="">―</said>You'd better speak to <persName xml:id="ke">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>
<lb n="13271"/> distantly.
<lb n="13272"/> <said who="">―</said>I don't know anything about <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>, repeated <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13273"/> Kearney</persName>. I have my contract and I intend to see that it is carried
<lb n="13274"/> out.</p>
<lb n="13275"/> <p>When she came back to the dressingroom her cheeks were
<lb n="13276"/> slightly suffused. The room was lively. Two men in outdoor
<lb n="13277"/> dress had taken possession of the fireplace and were chatting
  <lb n="13278"/> familiarly with <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> and the baritone. They were the
  <lb n="13279"/> <emph>Freeman</emph> man and <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden Burke</persName>. The <emph>Freeman</emph> man
<lb n="13280"/> had come in to say that he could not wait for the concert as he
<lb n="13281"/> had to report the lecture which an American priest was giving
<lb n="13282"/> in the Mansion House. He said they were to leave the report
<lb n="13283"/> for him at the <emph>Freeman</emph> office and he would see that it went in.
<lb n="13284"/> He was a greyhaired man with a plausible voice and careful
<lb n="13285"/> manners. He held an extinguished cigar in his hand and the
<lb n="13286"/> aroma of cigar smoke floated near him. He had not intended to
<lb n="13287"/> stay a moment because concerts and <emph>artistes</emph> bored him con=
<lb n="13288"/> siderably but he remained leaning against the mantelpiece.
  <lb n="13289"/> <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> stood in front of him, talking and laughing. He was
<lb n="13290"/> old enough to suspect one reason for her politeness but young
<lb n="13291"/> enough in spirit to turn the moment to account. The warmth,
<lb n="13292"/> fragrance and colour of her body appealed to his senses. He
<lb n="13293"/> was pleasantly conscious that the bosom which he saw rise and
<lb n="13294"/> fall slowly beneath him rose and fell at that moment for him,
<lb n="13295"/> that the laughter and fragrance and wilful glances were his
<lb n="13296"/> tribute. When he could stay no longer he took leave of her
<lb n="13297"/> regretfully.
  <lb n="13298"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="mb">O'Madden Burke</persName> will write the notice, he explained to <persName xml:id="ho">Mr
  <lb n="13299"/> Holohan</persName>, and I'll see it in.
<lb n="13300"/> <said who="">―</said>Thank you very much, <persName xml:id="hd">Mr Hendrick</persName>, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>.
<lb n="13301"/> You'll see it in, I know. Now, won't you have a little something
<lb n="13302"/> before you go?
  <lb n="13303"/> <said who="">―</said>I don't mind, said <persName xml:id="hd">Mr Hendrick</persName>.</p>
<lb n="13304"/> <p>The two men went along some tortuous passages and up a
<lb n="13305"/> dark staircase and came to a secluded room where one of the
<lb n="13306"/> stewards was uncorking bottles for a few gentlemen. One of
  <lb n="13307"/> these gentlemen was <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden Burke</persName> who had found out
<lb n="13308"/> the room by instinct. He was a suave elderly man who bal=
<lb n="13309"/> anced his imposing body, when at rest, upon a large silk um=
<lb n="13310"/> brella. His magniloquent western name was the moral umbrella
<lb n="13311"/> upon which he balanced the fine problem of his finances. He
<lb n="13312"/> was widely respected.</p>
  <lb n="13313"/> <p>While <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> was entertaining the <emph>Freeman</emph> man <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13314"/> Kearney</persName> was speaking so animatedly to her husband that he
<lb n="13315"/> had to ask her to lower her voice. The conversation of the
<lb n="13316"/> others in the dressingroom had become strained. <persName xml:id="bl">Mr Bell</persName>, the
<lb n="13317"/> first item, stood ready with his music but the accompanist
<lb n="13318"/> made no sign. Evidently something was wrong. <persName xml:id="mke">Mr Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13319"/> looked straight before him, stroking his beard, while <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs
  <lb n="13320"/> Kearney</persName> spoke into <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName>'s ear with subdued emphasis.
<lb n="13321"/> From the hall came sounds of encouragement, clapping and
<lb n="13322"/> stamping of feet. The first tenor and the baritone and <persName xml:id="hy">Miss
  <lb n="13323"/> Healy</persName> stood together, waiting tranquilly, but <persName xml:id="bl">Mr Bell</persName>'s nerves
<lb n="13324"/> were greatly agitated because he was afraid the audience would
<lb n="13325"/> think that he had come late.</p>
  <lb n="13326"/> <p><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> and <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden Burke</persName> came into the room.
  <lb n="13327"/> In a moment <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> perceived the hush. He went over to
  <lb n="13328"/> <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> and spoke with her earnestly. While they were
<lb n="13329"/> speaking the noise in the hall grew louder. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> became
<lb n="13330"/> very red and excited. He spoke volubly but <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> said
<lb n="13331"/> curtly at intervals:
<lb n="13332"/> <said who="">―</said>She won't go on. She must get her eight guineas.</p>
  <lb n="13333"/> <p><persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> pointed desperately towards the hall where the
<lb n="13334"/> audience was clapping and stamping. He appealed to <persName xml:id="mke">Mr
  <lb n="13335"/> Kearney</persName> and to <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName>. But <persName xml:id="mke">Mr Kearney</persName> continued to stroke
  <lb n="13336"/> his beard and <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> looked down, moving the point of her
  <lb n="13337"/> new shoe: it was not her fault. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> repeated:
<lb n="13338"/> <said who="">―</said>She won't go on without her money.</p>
  <lb n="13339"/> <p>After a swift struggle of tongues <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> hobbled out in
<lb n="13340"/> haste. The room was silent. When the strain of the silence had
  <lb n="13341"/> become somewhat painful <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> said to the baritone:
  <lb n="13342"/> <said who="">―</said>Have you seen <persName xml:id="pc">Mrs Pat Campbell</persName> this week?</p>
<lb n="13343"/> <p>The baritone had not seen her but he had been told that she
<lb n="13344"/> was very fine. The conversation went no further. The first
<lb n="13345"/> tenor bent his head and began to count the links of the gold
<lb n="13346"/> chain which was extended across his waist, smiling and hum=
<lb n="13347"/> ming random notes to observe the effect on the frontal sinus.
  <lb n="13348"/> From time to time everyone glanced at <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>.</p>
<lb n="13349"/> <p>The noise in the auditorium had risen to a clamour when <persName xml:id="fz">Mr
  <lb n="13350"/> Fitzpatrick</persName> burst into the room, followed by <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> who
<lb n="13351"/> was panting. The clapping and stamping in the hall were
  <lb n="13352"/> punctuated by whistling. <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> held a few bank notes
  <lb n="13353"/> in his hand. He counted out four into <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>'s hand and
<lb n="13354"/> said she would get the other half at the interval. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13355"/> said:
<lb n="13356"/> <said who="">―</said>This is four shillings short.</p>
  <lb n="13357"/> <p>But <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> gathered in her skirt and said <emph>Now, <persName xml:id="bl">Mr Bell</persName></emph>, to
<lb n="13358"/> the first item who was shaking like an aspen. The singer and
<lb n="13359"/> the accompanist went out together. The noise in the hall died
<lb n="13360"/> away. There was a pause of a few seconds: and then the piano
<lb n="13361"/> was heard.</p>
<lb n="13362"/> <p>The first part of the concert was very successful except for
  <lb n="13363"/> <persName xml:id="mg">Madam Glynn</persName>'s item. The poor lady sang <emph>Killarney</emph> in a
<lb n="13364"/> bodiless gasping voice, with all the oldfashioned mannerisms of
<lb n="13365"/> intonation and pronunciation which she believed lent elegance
<lb n="13366"/> to her singing. She looked as if she had been resurrected from
<lb n="13367"/> an old stage wardrobe and the cheaper parts of the hall made
<lb n="13368"/> fun of her high wailing notes. The first tenor and the contralto,
  <lb n="13369"/> however, brought down the house. <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> played a selection
<lb n="13370"/> of Irish airs which was generously applauded. The first part
<lb n="13371"/> closed with a stirring patriotic recitation delivered by a young
<lb n="13372"/> lady who arranged amateur theatricals. It was deservedly ap=
<lb n="13373"/> plauded; and when it was ended the men went out for the
<lb n="13374"/> interval, content.</p>
<lb n="13375"/> <p>All this time the dressingroom was a hive of excitement. In
  <lb n="13376"/> one corner were <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>, <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName>, <persName xml:id="be">Miss Beirne</persName>, two
<lb n="13377"/> of the stewards, the baritone, the bass and <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden
  <lb n="13378"/> Burke</persName>. <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden Burke</persName> said it was the most scandalous
<lb n="13379"/> exhibition he had ever witnessed. <persName xml:id="ka">Miss Kathleen Kearney</persName>'s
<lb n="13380"/> musical career was ended in Dublin after that, he said. The
  <lb n="13381"/> baritone was asked what did he think of <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>'s
<lb n="13382"/> conduct. He did not like to say anything. He had been paid his
<lb n="13383"/> money and wished to be at peace with men. However, he said
  <lb n="13384"/> that <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> might have taken the <emph>artistes</emph> into consider=
<lb n="13385"/> ation. The stewards and the secretaries debated hotly as to
<lb n="13386"/> what should be done when the interval came.
  <lb n="13387"/> <said who="">―</said>I agree with <persName xml:id="be">Miss Beirne</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden Burke</persName>. Pay her
<lb n="13388"/> nothing.</p>
  <lb n="13389"/> <p>In another corner of the room were <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> and her
  <lb n="13390"/> husband, <persName xml:id="bl">Mr Bell</persName>, <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> and the young lady who had
  <lb n="13391"/> recited the patriotic piece. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> said that the committee
<lb n="13392"/> had treated her scandalously. She had spared neither trouble
<lb n="13393"/> nor expense and this was how she was repaid. They thought
<lb n="13394"/> they had only a girl to deal with and that, therefore, they could
<lb n="13395"/> ride roughshod over her. But she would show them their
<lb n="13396"/> mistake. They wouldn't have dared to have treated her like that
<lb n="13397"/> if she had been a man. But she would see that her daughter got
<lb n="13398"/> her rights: she wouldn't be fooled. If they didn't pay her to the
<lb n="13399"/> last farthing she would make Dublin ring. Of course she was
<lb n="13400"/> sorry for the sake of the <emph>artistes.</emph> But what else could she do?
<lb n="13401"/> She appealed to the second tenor who said he thought she had
<lb n="13402"/> not been well treated. Then she appealed to <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName>. <persName xml:id="hy">Miss
  <lb n="13403"/> Healy</persName> wanted to join the other group but she did not like to do
  <lb n="13404"/> so because she was a great friend of <persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName>'s and the
<lb n="13405"/> Kearneys had often invited her to their house.</p>
<lb n="13406"/> <p>As soon as the first part was ended <persName xml:id="fz">Mr Fitzpatrick</persName> and <persName xml:id="ho">Mr
  <lb n="13407"/> Holohan</persName> went over to <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> and told her that the other
<lb n="13408"/> four guineas would be paid after the committee meeting on the
<lb n="13409"/> following Tuesday and that, in case her daughter did not play
<lb n="13410"/> for the second part, the committee would consider the contract
<lb n="13411"/> broken and would pay nothing.
<lb n="13412"/> <said who="">―</said>I haven't seen any committee, said <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> angrily. My
<lb n="13413"/> daughter has her contract. She will get four pounds eight into
<lb n="13414"/> her hand or a foot she won't put on that platform.
<lb n="13415"/> <said who="">―</said>I'm surprised at you, <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>. I
<lb n="13416"/> never thought you would treat us this way.
<lb n="13417"/> <said who="">―</said>And what way did you treat me? asked <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>.</p>
<lb n="13418"/> <p>Her face was inundated with an angry colour and she looked
<lb n="13419"/> as if she would attack someone with her hands.
<lb n="13420"/> <said who="">―</said>I'm asking for my rights, she said.
<lb n="13421"/> <said who="">―</said>You might have some sense of decency, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>.
<lb n="13422"/> <said who="">―</said>Might I indeed? ... And when I ask when my daughter is
<lb n="13423"/> going to be paid I can't get a civil answer.</p>
<lb n="13424"/> <p>She tossed her head and assumed a haughty voice:
<lb n="13425"/> <said who="">―</said>You must speak to the secretary. It's not my business. I'm a
<lb n="13426"/> great fellow fol-the-diddle-I-do.
<lb n="13427"/> <said who="">―</said>I thought you were a lady, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>, walking away
<lb n="13428"/> from her abruptly.</p>
  <lb n="13429"/> <p>After that <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>'s conduct was condemned on all
<lb n="13430"/> hands: everyone approved of what the committee had done.
<lb n="13431"/> She stood at the door, haggard with rage, arguing with her
<lb n="13432"/> husband and daughter, gesticulating with them. She waited
<lb n="13433"/> until it was time for the second part to begin in the hope that
  <lb n="13434"/> the secretaries would approach her. But <persName xml:id="hy">Miss Healy</persName> had kindly
<lb n="13435"/> consented to play one or two accompaniments. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName>
<lb n="13436"/> had to stand aside to allow the baritone and his accompanist to
<lb n="13437"/> pass up to the platform. She stood still for an instant like an
<lb n="13438"/> angry stone image and, when the first notes of the song struck
<lb n="13439"/> her ear, she caught up her daughter's cloak and said to her
<lb n="13440"/> husband:
<lb n="13441"/> <said who="">―</said>Get a cab!</p>
  <lb n="13442"/> <p>He went out at once. <persName xml:id="ke">Mrs Kearney</persName> wrapped the cloak round
<lb n="13443"/> her daughter and followed him. As she passed through the
  <lb n="13444"/> doorway she stopped and glared into <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>'s face:
<lb n="13445"/> <said who="">―</said>I'm not done with you yet, she said.
<lb n="13446"/> <said who="">―</said>But I'm done with you, said <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="13447"/> <p><persName xml:id="ka">Kathleen</persName> followed her mother meekly. <persName xml:id="ho">Mr Holohan</persName> began
<lb n="13448"/> to pace up and down the room in order to cool himself for he
<lb n="13449"/> felt his skin on fire:
<lb n="13450"/> <said who="">―</said>That's a nice lady! he said. O, she's a nice lady!
<lb n="13451"/> <said who="">―</said>You did the proper thing, <persName xml:id="ho">Holohan</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mb">Mr O'Madden
  <lb n="13452"/> Burke</persName>, poised upon his umbrella in approval.</p></div> <!-- End of story -->
