<div n="14" type="story"><lb n="14000"/> <head rend="italics">Grace</head>
<lb n="14001"/> <p>Two gentlemen who were in the lavatory at the time tried to
<lb n="14002"/> lift him up: but he was quite helpless. He lay curled up at the
<lb n="14003"/> foot of the stairs down which he had fallen. They succeeded in
<lb n="14004"/> turning him over. His hat had rolled a few yards away and his
<lb n="14005"/> clothes were smeared with the filth and ooze of the floor on
<lb n="14006"/> which he had lain, face downwards. His eyes were closed and
<lb n="14007"/> he breathed with a grunting noise. A thin stream of blood
<lb n="14008"/> trickled from the corner of his mouth.</p>
<lb n="14009"/> <p>These two gentlemen and one of the curates carried him up
<lb n="14010"/> the stairs and laid him down again on the floor of the bar. In
<lb n="14011"/> two minutes he was surrounded by a ring of men. The manager
<lb n="14012"/> of the bar asked everyone who he was and who was with him.
<lb n="14013"/> No-one knew who he was but one of the curates said <said who="curate" direct="false">he had
  <lb n="14014"/> served the gentleman with a small rum.</said>
  <lb n="14015"/> <said who="manager">―Was he by himself? </said>asked the manager.
<lb n="14016"/> <said who="curate">―No, sir. There was two gentlemen with him.</said>
<lb n="14017"/> <said who="manager">―And where are they?</said></p>
<lb n="14018"/> <p>No-one knew; a voice said:
<lb n="14019"/> <said who="someone">―Give him air. He's fainted.</said></p>
<lb n="14020"/> <p>The ring of onlookers distended and closed again elastically.
<lb n="14021"/> A dark medal of blood had formed itself near the man's head
<lb n="14022"/> on the tessellated floor. The manager, alarmed by the grey
<lb n="14023"/> pallor of the man's face, sent for a policeman.</p>
<lb n="14024"/> <p>His collar was unfastened and his necktie undone. He
<lb n="14025"/> opened his eyes for an instant, sighed and closed them again.
<lb n="14026"/> One of the gentlemen who had carried him upstairs held a
<lb n="14027"/> dinged silk hat in his hand. The manager asked repeatedly did
<lb n="14028"/> no-one know who the injured man was or where had his
<lb n="14029"/> friends gone. The door of the bar opened and an immense
<lb n="14030"/> constable entered. A crowd which had followed him down the
<lb n="14031"/> laneway collected outside the door, struggling to look in
<lb n="14032"/> through the glass panels.</p>
<lb n="14033"/> <p>The manager at once began to narrate what he knew. The
<lb n="14034"/> constable, a young man with thick immobile features, listened.
<lb n="14035"/> He moved his head slowly to right and left and from the
<lb n="14036"/> manager to the person on the floor as if he feared to be the
<lb n="14037"/> victim of some delusion. Then he drew off his glove, produced
<lb n="14038"/> a small book from his waist, licked the lead of his pencil and
<lb n="14039"/> made ready to indite. He asked in a suspicious provincial
<lb n="14040"/> accent:
<lb n="14041"/> <said who="constable">―Who is the man? What's his name and address?</said></p>
<lb n="14042"/> <p>A young man in a cycling suit cleared his way through the
<lb n="14043"/> ring of bystanders. He knelt down promptly beside the injured
<lb n="14044"/> man and called for water. The constable knelt down also to
<lb n="14045"/> help. The young man washed the blood from the injured man's
<lb n="14046"/> mouth and then called for some brandy. The constable re=
<lb n="14047"/> peated the order in an authoritative voice until a curate came
<lb n="14048"/> running with the glass. The brandy was forced down the man's
<lb n="14049"/> throat. In a few seconds he opened his eyes and looked about
<lb n="14050"/> him. He looked at the circle of faces and then, understanding,
<lb n="14051"/> strove to rise to his feet.
<lb n="14052"/> <said who="young man">―You're all right now? </said>asked the young man in the cycling
<lb n="14053"/> suit.
  <lb n="14054"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―'Sha,'s nothing, </said>said the injured man, trying to stand up.</p>
<lb n="14055"/> <p>He was helped to his feet. The manager said something
<lb n="14056"/> about a hospital and some of the bystanders gave advice. The
<lb n="14057"/> battered silk hat was placed on the man's head. The constable
<lb n="14058"/> asked:
<lb n="14059"/> <said who="constable">―Where do you live?</said></p>
<lb n="14060"/> <p>The man, without answering, began to twirl the ends of his
<lb n="14061"/> moustache. He made light of his accident. <said who="Tom Kernan">It was nothing, </said>he
  <lb n="14062"/> said: <said who="Tom Kernan">only a little accident.</said> He spoke very thickly.
  <lb n="14063"/> <said who="constable">―Where do you live? </said>repeated the constable.</p>
<lb n="14064"/> <p>The man said they were to get a cab for him. While the point
<lb n="14065"/> was being debated a tall agile gentleman of fair complexion,
<lb n="14066"/> wearing a long yellow ulster, came from the far end of the bar.
<lb n="14067"/> Seeing the spectacle he called out:
  <lb n="14068"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Hallo, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, old man! What's the trouble?</said>
<lb n="14069"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―'Sha,'s nothing, </said>said the man.</p>
<lb n="14070"/> <p>The newcomer surveyed the deplorable figure before him
<lb n="14071"/> and then turned to the constable, saying:
<lb n="14072"/> <said who="Jack Power">―It's all right, constable. I'll see him home.</said></p>
<lb n="14073"/> <p>The constable touched his helmet and answered:
  <lb n="14074"/> <said who="constable">―All right, <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>!</said>
  <lb n="14075"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Come now, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>, taking his friend by the
<lb n="14076"/> arm. <said who="Jack Power">No bones broken. What? Can you walk?</said></p>
<lb n="14077"/> <p>The young man in the cycling suit took the man by the other
<lb n="14078"/> arm and the crowd divided.
<lb n="14079"/> <said who="Jack Power">―How did you get yourself into this mess? </said>asked <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
<lb n="14080"/> <said who="young man">―The gentleman fell down the stairs, </said>said the young man.
<lb n="14081"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I' 'ery 'uch o'liged to you, sir, </said>said the injured man.
<lb n="14082"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Not at all.</said>
<lb n="14083"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―'an't we have a little .... ?</said>
<lb n="14084"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Not now. Not now.</said></p>
<lb n="14085"/> <p>The three men left the bar and the crowd sifted through the
<lb n="14086"/> doors into the laneway. The manager brought the constable to
<lb n="14087"/> the stairs to inspect the scene of the accident. They agreed that
<lb n="14088"/> the gentleman must have missed his footing. The customers
<lb n="14089"/> returned to the counter and a curate set about removing the
<lb n="14090"/> traces of blood from the floor.</p>
  <lb n="14091"/> <p>When they came out into <place> <location> <geo> 53.341751 -6.260147 </geo> </location> <placeName> Grafton Street </placeName> </place> <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> whistled
<lb n="14092"/> for an outsider. The injured man said again as well as he could:
<lb n="14093"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I' 'ery 'uch o'liged to you, sir. I hope we'll 'eet again. 'y na'e
  <lb n="14094"/> is <persName xml:id="tk">Kernan</persName>.</said></p>
<lb n="14095"/> <p>The shock and the incipient pain had partly sobered him.
  <lb n="14096"/> <said who="young man">―Don't mention it, </said>said the young man.</p>
  <lb n="14097"/> <p>They shook hands. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> was hoisted on to the car
  <lb n="14098"/> and, while <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> was giving directions to the carman, he
<lb n="14099"/> expressed his gratitude to the young man and regretted that
<lb n="14100"/> they could not have a little drink together.
<lb n="14101"/> <said who="young man">―Another time,</said> said the young man.</p>
<lb n="14102"/> <p>The car drove off towards <place> <location> <geo> 53.346001 -6.259074 </geo> </location> <placeName> Westmoreland Street </placeName> </place>. As it passed
<lb n="14103"/> the Ballast office the clock showed half past nine. A keen east
<lb n="14104"/> wind hit them blowing from the mouth of the river. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>
<lb n="14105"/> was huddled together with cold. His friend asked him to tell
<lb n="14106"/> how the accident had happened.
  <lb n="14107"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I 'an't,'an, </said>he answered. <said who="Tom Kernan">'y 'ongue is hurt.</said>
<lb n="14108"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Show.</said></p>
<lb n="14109"/> <p>The other leaned over the well of the car and peered into <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14110"/> Kernan</persName>'s mouth but he could not see. He struck a match and,
<lb n="14111"/> sheltering it in the shell of his hands, peered again into the
  <lb n="14112"/> mouth which <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> opened obediently. The swaying
<lb n="14113"/> movement of the car brought the match to and from the open
<lb n="14114"/> mouth. The lower teeth and gums were covered with clotted
<lb n="14115"/> blood and a minute piece of the tongue seemed to have been
<lb n="14116"/> bitten off. The match was blown out.
  <lb n="14117"/> <said who="Jack Power">―That's ugly, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
<lb n="14118"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―'Sha,'s nothing, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, closing his mouth and
<lb n="14119"/> pulling the collar of his filthy frock coat across his neck.</p>
  <lb n="14120"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> was a commercial traveler of the old school
<lb n="14121"/> which believed in the dignity of its calling. He had never been
<lb n="14122"/> seen in the city without a silk hat of some decency and a pair of
  <lb n="14123"/> gaiters. <said who="Tom Kernan">By grace of these two articles of clothing, </said>he said, <said who="Tom Kernan">a
  <lb n="14124"/> man could always pass muster.</said> He carried on the tradition of
<lb n="14125"/> his Napoleon, the great Blackwhite, whose memory he evoked
<lb n="14126"/> at times by legend and mimicry. Modern business methods had
<lb n="14127"/> spared him only so far as to allow him a little office in Crowe
<lb n="14128"/> Street on the window blind of which was written the name of
<lb n="14129"/> his firm with the address - London, E. C. On the mantelpiece
<lb n="14130"/> of this little office a little leaden battalion of canisters was
<lb n="14131"/> drawn up and on the table before the window stood four or
<lb n="14132"/> five china bowls which were usually half full of a black liquid.
  <lb n="14133"/> From these bowls <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> tasted tea. He took a mouthful,
<lb n="14134"/> drew it up, saturated his palate with it and then spat it forth
<lb n="14135"/> into the grate. Then he paused to judge.</p>
  <lb n="14136"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>, a much younger man, was employed in the Royal
<lb n="14137"/> Irish Constabulary Office in <place> <location> <geo> 53.34309 -6.266194 </geo> </location> <placeName> Dublin Castle </placeName> </place>. The arc of his
<lb n="14138"/> social rise intersected the arc of his friend's decline but <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14139"/> Kernan</persName>'s decline was mitigated by the fact that certain of those
<lb n="14140"/> friends who had known him at his highest point of success still
<lb n="14141"/> esteemed him as a character. <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> was one of these
<lb n="14142"/> friends. His inexplicable debts were a byword in his circle; he
<lb n="14143"/> was a debonair young man.</p>
<lb n="14144"/> <p>The car halted before a small house on <place> <location> <geo> 53.363589 -6.272317 </geo> </location> <placeName> the Glasnevin road </placeName> </place>
  <lb n="14145"/> and <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> was helped into the house. His wife put him to
  <lb n="14146"/> bed while <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> sat downstairs in the kitchen asking the
<lb n="14147"/> children where they went to school and what book they were
<lb n="14148"/> in. The children, two girls and a boy, conscious of their father's
<lb n="14149"/> helplessness and of their mother's absence, began some horse=
<lb n="14150"/> play with him. He was surprised at their manners and at their
<lb n="14151"/> accents and his brow grew thoughtful. After a while <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs
  <lb n="14152"/> Kernan</persName> entered the kitchen, exclaiming:
<lb n="14153"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―Such a sight! O, he'll do for himself one day and that's the
<lb n="14154"/> holy alls of it. He's been drinking since Friday.</said></p>
  <lb n="14155"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> was careful to explain to her that he was not
<lb n="14156"/> responsible, that he had come on the scene by the merest
  <lb n="14157"/> accident. <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName>, remembering <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>'s good offices
<lb n="14158"/> during domestic quarrels as well as many small but opportune
<lb n="14159"/> loans, said:
<lb n="14160"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―O, you needn't tell me that, <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. I know you're a
<lb n="14161"/> friend of his, not like some of those others he does be with.
<lb n="14162"/> They're all right so long as he has money in his pocket to keep
<lb n="14163"/> him out from his wife and family. Nice friends! Who was he
<lb n="14164"/> with tonight, I'd like to know?</said></p>
  <lb n="14165"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> shook his head but said nothing.
  <lb n="14166"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―I'm so sorry, </said>she continued, <said who="Mrs Kernan">that I've nothing in the house to
      <lb n="14167"/> offer you. But if you wait a minute I'll send round to <place> <location> <geo> 53.361523 -6.265431 </geo> </location> <placeName> Fogarty's </placeName> </place>
<lb n="14168"/> at the corner.</said></p>
  <lb n="14169"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> stood up.
<lb n="14170"/> <said who="Jack Power">―We were waiting for him to come home with the money. He
<lb n="14171"/> never seems to think he has a home at all.</said>
  <lb n="14172"/> <said who="Jack Power">―O now, <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName>, </said>said Mr Power, <said who="Jack Power">we'll make him turn
  <lb n="14173"/> over a new leaf. I'll talk to <persName xml:id="mc">Martin</persName>. He's the man. We'll come
<lb n="14174"/> here one of these nights and talk it over.</said></p>
<lb n="14175"/> <p>She saw him to the door. The carman was stamping up and
<lb n="14176"/> down the footpath and swinging his arms to warm himself.
<lb n="14177"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―It's very kind of you to bring him home, </said>she said.
  <lb n="14178"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Not at all, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14179"/> <p>He got up on the car. As it drove off he raised his hat to her
<lb n="14180"/> gaily.
  <lb n="14181"/> <said who="Jack Power">―We'll make a new man of him, </said>he said. <said who="Jack Power">Goodnight, <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs
  <lb n="14182"/> Kernan</persName>.</said></p>
<lb />   *  *  *
  <lb n="14183"/> <p><persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName>'s puzzled eyes watched the car till it was out of
<lb n="14184"/> sight. Then she withdrew them, went into the house and
<lb n="14185"/> emptied her husband's pockets.</p>
<lb n="14186"/> <p>She was an active practical woman of middle age. Not long
<lb n="14187"/> before she had celebrated her silver wedding and renewed her
<lb n="14188"/> intimacy with her husband by valsing with him to <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>'s
  <lb n="14189"/> accompaniment. In her days of courtship <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> had
<lb n="14190"/> seemed to her a not ungallant figure: and she still hurried to the
<lb n="14191"/> chapel door whenever a wedding was reported and, seeing the
<lb n="14192"/> bridal pair, recalled with vivid pleasure how she had passed out
<lb n="14193"/> of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.335751 -6.219973 </geo> </location> <placeName> Star of the Sea Church </placeName> </place> in Sandymount, leaning on the
<lb n="14194"/> arm of a jovial wellfed man who was dressed smartly in a frock
<lb n="14195"/> coat and lavender trousers and carried a silk hat gracefully
<lb n="14196"/> balanced upon his other arm. After three weeks she had found
<lb n="14197"/> a wife's life irksome and later on, when she was beginning to
<lb n="14198"/> find it unbearable, she had become a mother. The part of
<lb n="14199"/> mother presented to her no insuperable difficulties and for
<lb n="14200"/> twenty-five years she had kept house shrewdly for her husband.
<lb n="14201"/> Her two eldest sons were launched. One was in a draper's shop
<lb n="14202"/> in <place> <location> <geo> 55.865536 -4.25909 </geo> </location> <placeName> Glasgow </placeName> </place> and the other was clerk to a tea merchant in
<lb n="14203"/> <place> <location> <geo> 54.597267 -5.930109 </geo> </location> <placeName> Belfast </placeName> </place>. They were good sons, wrote regularly and sometimes
<lb n="14204"/> sent home money. The other children were still at school.</p>
  <lb n="14205"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> sent a letter to his office next day and remained
<lb n="14206"/> in bed. She made beef tea for him and scolded him roundly. She
<lb n="14207"/> accepted his frequent intemperance as part of the climate,
<lb n="14208"/> healed him dutifully whenever he was sick and always tried to
<lb n="14209"/> make him eat a breakfast. There were worse husbands. He had
<lb n="14210"/> never been violent since the boys had grown up and she knew
<lb n="14211"/> that he would walk to the end of <place> <location> <geo> 53.343048 -6.280646 </geo> </location> <placeName> Thomas Street </placeName> </place> and back again
<lb n="14212"/> to book even a small order.</p>
<lb n="14213"/> <p>Two nights after his friends came to see him. She brought
<lb n="14214"/> them up to his bedroom, the air of which was impregnated
<lb n="14215"/> with a personal odour, and gave them chairs at the fire. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14216"/> Kernan</persName>'s tongue, the occasional stinging pain of which had
<lb n="14217"/> made him somewhat irritable during the day, became more
<lb n="14218"/> polite. He sat propped up in the bed by pillows and the little
<lb n="14219"/> colour in his puffy cheeks made them resemble warm cinders.
<lb n="14220"/> He apologised to his guests for the disorder of the room but at
<lb n="14221"/> the same time looked at them a little proudly, with a veteran's
<lb n="14222"/> pride.</p>
<lb n="14223"/> <p>He was quite unconscious that he was the victim of a plot
  <lb n="14224"/> which his friends <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> and <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>
  <lb n="14225"/> had disclosed to <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> in the parlour. The idea had been
  <lb n="14226"/> <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>'s but its development was entrusted to <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunning=
  <lb n="14227"/> ham</persName>. <persName xml:id="mk">Mr Kernan</persName> came of Protestant stock and, though he had
<lb n="14228"/> been converted to the Catholic faith at the time of his marriage,
<lb n="14229"/> he had not been in the pale of the Church for twenty years. He
<lb n="14230"/> was fond, moreover, of giving side thrusts at Catholicism.</p>
  <lb n="14231"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> was the very man for such a case. He was
  <lb n="14232"/> an elder colleague of <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>'s. His own domestic life was
<lb n="14233"/> not very happy. People had great sympathy with him for it
<lb n="14234"/> was known that he had married an unpresentable woman who
<lb n="14235"/> was an incurable drunkard. He had set up house for her six
<lb n="14236"/> times and each time she had pawned the furniture on him.</p>
  <lb n="14237"/> <p>Everyone had respect for poor <persName xml:id="mc">Martin Cunningham</persName>. He was
<lb n="14238"/> a thoroughly sensible man, influential and intelligent. His blade
<lb n="14239"/> of human knowledge, natural astuteness particularised by long
<lb n="14240"/> association with cases in the police courts, had been tempered
<lb n="14241"/> by brief immersions in the waters of general philosophy. He
<lb n="14242"/> was well informed. His friends bowed to his opinions and
<lb n="14243"/> considered that his face was like Shakespeare's.</p>
<lb n="14244"/> <p>When the plot had been disclosed to her <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> had
<lb n="14245"/> said:
  <lb n="14246"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">I leave it all in your hands, </said><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14247"/> <p>After a quarter of a century of married life she had very few
<lb n="14248"/> illusions left. Religion for her was a habit and she suspected
<lb n="14249"/> that a man of her husband's age would not change greatly
<lb n="14250"/> before death. She was tempted to see a curious appropriateness
<lb n="14251"/> in his accident and, but that she did not wish to seem bloody=
<lb n="14252"/> minded, she would have told the gentleman that <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>'s
<lb n="14253"/> tongue would not suffer by being shortened. However <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cun=
  <lb n="14254"/> ningham</persName> was a capable man and religion was religion. The
<lb n="14255"/> scheme might do good and, at least, it could do no harm. Her
<lb n="14256"/> beliefs were not extravagant. She believed steadily in the Sacred
<lb n="14257"/> Heart as the most generally useful of all Catholic devotions and
<lb n="14258"/> approved of the sacraments. Her faith was bounded by her
<lb n="14259"/> kitchen but, if she was put to it, she could believe also in the
<lb n="14260"/> banshee and in the Holy Ghost.</p>
<lb n="14261"/> <p>The gentlemen began to talk of the accident. <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunning=
  <lb n="14262"/> ham</persName> said that <said who="Martin Cunningham" direct="false">he had once known a similar case. A man of
<lb n="14263"/> seventy had bitten off a piece of his tongue during an epileptic
<lb n="14264"/> fit and the tongue had filled in again so that no-one could see a
  <lb n="14265"/> trace of the bite.</said>
<lb n="14266"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Well, I'm not seventy, </said>said the invalid.
  <lb n="14267"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―God forbid, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
<lb n="14268"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―It doesn't pain you now? </said>asked <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14269"/> <p><persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> had been at one time a tenor of some reputation.
<lb n="14270"/> His wife, who had been a soprano, still taught young children
<lb n="14271"/> to play the piano at low terms. His line of life had not been the
<lb n="14272"/> shortest distance between two points and for short periods he
<lb n="14273"/> had been driven to live by his wits. He had been a clerk in the
<lb n="14274"/> Midland Railway, a canvasser for advertisements for the <emph>Irish
<lb n="14275"/> Times</emph> and for the <emph>Freeman's Journal</emph>, a town traveller for a
<lb n="14276"/> coal firm on commission, a private enquiry agent, a clerk in the
<lb n="14277"/> office of the Sub-Sheriff and he had recently become secretary
<lb n="14278"/> to the City Coroner. His new office made him professionally
  <lb n="14279"/> interested in <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>'s case.
  <lb n="14280"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Pain? Not much, </said>answered <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. <said who="Tom Kernan">But it's so sickening:
<lb n="14281"/> I feel as if I wanted to retch off.</said>
  <lb n="14282"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―That's the boose, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> firmly.
  <lb n="14283"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―No, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. <said who="Tom Kernan">I think I caught a cold on the car.
<lb n="14284"/> There's something keeps coming into my throat, phlegm
<lb n="14285"/> or ......</said>
  <lb n="14286"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Mucus, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14287"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―It keeps coming like from down in my throat; sickening
<lb n="14288"/> thing.</said>
  <lb n="14289"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Yes, yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy">that's the thorax.</said></p>
  <lb n="14290"/> <p>He looked at <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> and <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> at the same
  <lb n="14291"/> time with an air of challenge. <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> nodded his head
  <lb n="14292"/> rapidly and <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> said:
<lb n="14293"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Ah, well, all's well that ends well.</said>
<lb n="14294"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I'm very much obliged to you, old man, </said>said the invalid.</p>
  <lb n="14295"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> waved his hand.
<lb n="14296"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Those other two fellows I was with .....</said>
  <lb n="14297"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Who were you with? </said>asked <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
<lb n="14298"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―A chap - I don't know his name. Damn it now, what's his
<lb n="14299"/> name? Little chap with sandy hair ...</said>
<lb n="14300"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―And who else?</said>
  <lb n="14301"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―<persName xml:id="hf">Harford</persName>.</said>
  <lb n="14302"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Hm, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14303"/> <p>When <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> made that remark people were
<lb n="14304"/> silent. It was known that the speaker had secret sources of
<lb n="14305"/> information. In this case the monosyllable had a moral inten=
  <lb n="14306"/> tion. <persName xml:id="hf">Mr Harford</persName> sometimes formed one of a little detachment
<lb n="14307"/> which left the city shortly after noon on Sunday with the
<lb n="14308"/> purpose of arriving as soon as possible at some publichouse on
<lb n="14309"/> the outskirts of the city where its members duly qualified them=
<lb n="14310"/> selves as <emph>bonafide</emph> travellers. But his fellow travellers had never
<lb n="14311"/> consented to overlook his origin. He had begun life as an
<lb n="14312"/> obscure financier by lending small sums of money to workmen
<lb n="14313"/> at usurious interest. Later on he had become the partner of a
  <lb n="14314"/> very fat short gentleman, <persName xml:id="gb">Mr Goldberg</persName>, in the Liffey Loan
<lb n="14315"/> Bank. Though he had never embraced more than the jewish
<lb n="14316"/> ethical code his fellow Catholics, whenever they had smarted in
<lb n="14317"/> person or by proxy under his exactions, spoke of him bitterly
<lb n="14318"/> as an Irish Jew and an illiterate and saw divine disapproval of
<lb n="14319"/> usury made manifest through the person of his idiot son. At
<lb n="14320"/> other times they remembered his good points.
<lb n="14321"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I wonder where did he go to, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14322"/> <p>He wished the details of the incident to remain vague. He
<lb n="14323"/> wished his friends to think there had been some mistake, that
  <lb n="14324"/> <persName xml:id="hf">Mr Harford</persName> and he had missed each other. His friends, who
  <lb n="14325"/> knew quite well <persName xml:id="hf">Mr Harford</persName>'s manners in drinking, were silent.
  <lb n="14326"/> <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> said again:
<lb n="14327"/> <said who="Jack Power">―All's well that ends well.</said></p>
  <lb n="14328"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> changed the subject at once.
<lb n="14329"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―That was a decent young chap, that medical fellow, </said>he said.
  <lb n="14330"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">Only for him ......</said>
  <lb n="14331"/> <said who="Jack Power">―O, only for him, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>, <said who="Jack Power">it might have been a case of
<lb n="14332"/> seven days without the option of a fine.</said>
  <lb n="14333"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Yes, yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, trying to remember. <said who="Tom Kernan">I remember
<lb n="14334"/> now there was a policeman. Decent young fellow, he seemed.
  <lb n="14335"/> How did it happen at all?</said>
<lb n="14336"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―It happened that you were peloothered, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cun=
  <lb n="14337"/> ningham</persName> gravely.
  <lb n="14338"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―True bill, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> equally gravely.
<lb n="14339"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―I suppose you squared the constable, <persName xml:id="jp">Jack</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14340"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> did not relish the use of his Christian name. He
<lb n="14341"/> was not straitlaced but he could not forget that <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> had
<lb n="14342"/> recently made a crusade in search of valises and portmanteaus
  <lb n="14343"/> to enable <persName xml:id="mmco">Mrs M'Coy</persName> to fulfil imaginary engagements in the
<lb n="14344"/> country. More than he resented the fact that he had been
<lb n="14345"/> victimised he resented such low playing of the game. He
  <lb n="14346"/> answered the question, therefore, as if <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> had asked it.</p>
  <lb n="14347"/> <p>The narrative made <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> indignant. He was keenly
<lb n="14348"/> conscious of his citizenship, wished to live with his city on
<lb n="14349"/> terms mutually honourable and resented any affront put upon
<lb n="14350"/> him by those whom he called country bumpkins.
  <lb n="14351"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Is this what we pay rates for? </said>he asked. <said who="Tom Kernan">To feed and clothe
<lb n="14352"/> these ignorant bostoons ... and they're nothing else.</said></p>
  <lb n="14353"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> laughed. He was a Castle official only
<lb n="14354"/> during office hours.
<lb n="14355"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―How could they be anything else, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>? </said>he said.</p>
<lb n="14356"/> <p>He assumed a thick provincial accent and said in a tone of
<lb n="14357"/> command:
<lb n="14358"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―65, catch your cabbage!</said></p>
  <lb n="14359"/> <p>Everyone laughed. <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> who wanted to enter the
<lb n="14360"/> conversation by any door pretended that he had never heard
  <lb n="14361"/> the story. <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> said:
<lb n="14362"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―It is supposed - they say, you know - to take place in the
<lb n="14363"/> depot where they get these thundering big country fellows,
<lb n="14364"/> omadhauns, you know, to drill. The sergeant makes them
<lb n="14365"/> stand in a row against the wall and hold up their plates.</said></p>
<lb n="14366"/> <p>He illustrated the story by grotesque gestures.
<lb n="14367"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―At dinner, you know. Then he has a bloody big bowl of
<lb n="14368"/> cabbage before him on the table and a bloody big spoon like a
<lb n="14369"/> shovel. He takes up a wad of cabbage on the spoon and pegs it
<lb n="14370"/> across the room and the poor devils have to try and catch it on
<lb n="14371"/> their plates: <emph>65, catch your cabbage.</emph></said></p>
  <lb n="14372"/> <p>Everyone laughed again: but <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> was somewhat
<lb n="14373"/> indignant still. He talked of writing a letter to the papers.
  <lb n="14374"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―These yahoos coming up here, </said>he said, <said who="Tom Kernan">think they can boss
  <lb n="14375"/> the people. I needn't tell you, <persName xml:id="mc">Martin</persName>, what kind of men they
<lb n="14376"/> are.</said></p>
  <lb n="14377"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> gave a qualified assent.
  <lb n="14378"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―It's like everything else in this world, </said>he said. <said who="Mr Cunningham">You get some
<lb n="14379"/> bad ones and you get some good ones.</said>
  <lb n="14380"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―O yes, you get some good ones, I admit, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>,
<lb n="14381"/> satisfied.
  <lb n="14382"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―It's better to have nothing to say to them, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14383"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">That's my opinion.</said></p>
  <lb n="14384"/> <p><persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> entered the room and, placing a tray on the
<lb n="14385"/> table, said:
<lb n="14386"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―Help yourselves, gentlemen.</said></p>
  <lb n="14387"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> stood up to officiate, offering her his chair. She
<lb n="14388"/> declined it, saying that she was ironing downstairs and, after
  <lb n="14389"/> having exchanged a nod with <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> behind <persName xml:id="jp">Mr
  <lb n="14390"/> Power</persName>'s back, prepared to leave the room. Her husband called
<lb n="14391"/> out to her:
<lb n="14392"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―And have you nothing for me, duckie?</said>
  <lb n="14393"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―O, you! The back of my hand to you! </said>said <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName>
<lb n="14394"/> tartly.</p>
<lb n="14395"/> <p>Her husband called after her:
<lb n="14396"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Nothing for poor little hubby!</said></p>
<lb n="14397"/> <p>He assumed such a comical face and voice that the distribu=
<lb n="14398"/> tion of the bottles of stout took place amid general merriment.</p>
<lb n="14399"/> <p>The gentlemen drank from their glasses, set the glasses again
  <lb n="14400"/> on the table and paused. Then <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> turned to=
  <lb n="14401"/> wards <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> and said casually:
<lb n="14402"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―On Thursday night, you said, <persName xml:id="jp">Jack</persName>?</said>
  <lb n="14403"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Thursday, yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
  <lb n="14404"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Righto! </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> promptly.
  <lb n="14405"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―We can meet in <place> <location> <geo> 53.359982 -6.2608 </geo> </location> <placeName> M'Auley's </placeName> </place>, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>. <said who="Mr M'Coy">That'll be the
<lb n="14406"/> most convenient place.</said>
  <lb n="14407"/> <said who="Jack Power">―But we mustn't be late, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> earnestly, <said who="Jack Power">because it
<lb n="14408"/> is sure to be crammed to the doors.</said>
  <lb n="14409"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―We can meet at half seven, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
  <lb n="14410"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Righto! </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">Half seven at M'Auley's be it!</said></p>
  <lb n="14411"/> <p>There was a short silence. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> waited to see whether
<lb n="14412"/> he would be taken into his friends' confidence. Then he asked:
<lb n="14413"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―What's in the wind?</said>
  <lb n="14414"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, it's nothing, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">It's only a little matter
<lb n="14415"/> that we're arranging about for Thursday.</said>
  <lb n="14416"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―The opera, is it? </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.
  <lb n="14417"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―No, no, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> in an evasive tone, <said who="Mr Cunningham">it's just a
<lb n="14418"/> little .... spiritual matter.</said>
  <lb n="14419"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―O, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14420"/> <p>There was silence again. Then <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> said point blank:
  <lb n="14421"/> <said who="Jack Power">―To tell you the truth, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, we're going to make a retreat.</said>
  <lb n="14422"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Yes, that's it, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham"><persName xml:id="jp">Jack</persName> and I and <persName xml:id="mco">M'Coy</persName>
<lb n="14423"/> here we're all going to wash the pot.</said></p>
<lb n="14424"/> <p>He uttered the metaphor with a certain homely energy and,
<lb n="14425"/> encouraged by his own voice, proceeded:
<lb n="14426"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―You see, we may as well all admit we're a nice collection of
<lb n="14427"/> scoundrels, one and all. I say, one and all, he added with gruff
  <lb n="14428"/> charity and turning to <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. Own up now!</said>
  <lb n="14429"/> <said who="Jack Power">―I own up, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
  <lb n="14430"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―And I own up, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
  <lb n="14431"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―So we're going to wash the pot together, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunning=
  <lb n="14432"/> ham</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14433"/> <p>A thought seemed to strike him. He turned suddenly to the
<lb n="14434"/> invalid and said:
  <lb n="14435"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Do you know what, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, has just occurred to me? You
<lb n="14436"/> might join in and we'd have a fourhanded reel.</said>
  <lb n="14437"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Good idea, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. <said who="Jack Power">The four of us together.</said></p>
  <lb n="14438"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> was silent. The proposal conveyed very little
<lb n="14439"/> meaning to his mind but, understanding that some spiri=
<lb n="14440"/> tual agencies were about to concern themselves on his behalf,
<lb n="14441"/> he thought he owed it to his dignity to show a stiff neck. He
<lb n="14442"/> took no part in the conversation for a long while but listened,
<lb n="14443"/> with an air of calm enmity, while his friends discussed the
<lb n="14444"/> Jesuits.
  <lb n="14445"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I haven't such a bad opinion of the Jesuits, </said>he said, inter=
<lb n="14446"/> vening at length. <said who="Tom Kernan">They're an educated order. I believe they
<lb n="14447"/> mean well too.</said>
<lb n="14448"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―They're the grandest order in the Church, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr
  <lb n="14449"/> Cunningham</persName> with enthusiasm. <said who="Mr Cunningham">The General of the Jesuits
<lb n="14450"/> stands next to the Pope.</said>
  <lb n="14451"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―There's no mistake about it, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy">if you want a
<lb n="14452"/> thing well done and no flies about it you go to a Jesuit. They're
<lb n="14453"/> the boyos have influence. I'll tell you a case in point .......</said>
  <lb n="14454"/> <said who="Jack Power">―The Jesuits are a fine body of men, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
  <lb n="14455"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―It's a curious thing, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">about the Jesuit
<lb n="14456"/> Order. Every other order of the Church had to be reformed at
<lb n="14457"/> some time or other but the Jesuit Order was never once
<lb n="14458"/> reformed. It never fell away.</said>
  <lb n="14459"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Is that so? </said>asked <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
  <lb n="14460"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―That's a fact, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">That's history.</said>
  <lb n="14461"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Look at their church too, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. <said who="Jack Power">Look at the
<lb n="14462"/> congregation they have.</said>
  <lb n="14463"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―The Jesuits cater for the upper classes, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
  <lb n="14464"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Of course, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
  <lb n="14465"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. <said who="Tom Kernan">That's why I have a feeling for them.
<lb n="14466"/> It's some of those secular priests, ignorant, bumptious ......</said>
  <lb n="14467"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―They're all good men, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">each in his own
<lb n="14468"/> way. The Irish priesthood is honoured all the world over.</said></said>
  <lb n="14469"/> <said who="Jack Power">―O yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
<lb n="14470"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Not like some of the other priesthoods on the continent, </said>said
  <lb n="14471"/> <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy">unworthy of the name.</said>
  <lb n="14472"/> <said who="Mr Kernan">―Perhaps you're right, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> relenting.
  <lb n="14473"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Of course I'm right, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">I haven't been in
<lb n="14474"/> the world all this time and seen most sides of it without being a
<lb n="14475"/> judge of character.</said></p>
<lb n="14476"/> <p>The gentlemen drank again, one following another's ex=
  <lb n="14477"/> ample. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> seemed to be weighing something in his
<lb n="14478"/> mind. He was impressed. He had a high opinion of <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cun=
  <lb n="14479"/> ningham</persName> as a judge of character and as a reader of faces. He
<lb n="14480"/> asked for particulars.
  <lb n="14481"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, it's just a retreat, you know, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham"><persName xml:id="fp">Fa=
  <lb n="14482"/> ther Purdon</persName> is giving it. It's for business men, you know.</said>
<lb n="14483"/> <said who="Jack Power">―He won't be too hard on us, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> persua=
<lb n="14484"/> sively.
  <lb n="14485"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―<persName xml:id="fp">Father Purdon</persName>? <persName xml:id="fp">Father Purdon</persName>? </said>said the invalid.
  <lb n="14486"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, you must know him, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> stoutly.
<lb n="14487"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">Fine jolly fellow! He's a man of the world like ourselves.</said>
<lb n="14488"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Ah ... yes. I think I know him. Rather red face; tall.</said>
<lb n="14489"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―That's the man.</said>
  <lb n="14490"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―And tell me, <persName xml:id="mc">Martin</persName> .... Is he a good preacher?</said>
<lb n="14491"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Mmmno ..... It's not exactly a sermon, you know. It's just a
<lb n="14492"/> kind of a friendly talk, you know, in a commonsense way.</said></p>
  <lb n="14493"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> deliberated. <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> said:
  <lb n="14494"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―<persName xml:id="ftb">Father Tom Burke</persName>, that was the boy!</said>
  <lb n="14495"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, <persName xml:id="ftb">Father Tom Burke</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">that was a
  <lb n="14496"/> born orator. Did you ever hear him, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>?</said>
    <lb n="14497"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Did I ever hear him! </said>said the invalid, nettled. <said who="Tom Kernan">Rather! I heard
<lb n="14498"/> him ......</said>
    <lb n="14499"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―And yet they say he wasn't much of a theologian, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr
  <lb n="14500"/> Cunningham</persName>.
    <lb n="14501"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Is that so? </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14502"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, of course, nothing wrong, you know. Only sometimes,
    <lb n="14503"/> they say, he didn't preach what was quite orthodox.</said>
<lb n="14504"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Ah! .. he was a splendid man,</said> said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
    <lb n="14505"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I heard him once, </said><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> continued. <said who="Tom Kernan">I forget the subject
  <lb n="14506"/> of his discourse now. <persName xml:id="cf">Crofton</persName> and I were in the back of the ....
<lb n="14507"/> pit, you know ... the ...</said>
    <lb n="14508"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―The body, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
<lb n="14509"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Yes, in the back near the door. I forget now what ...... O yes,
<lb n="14510"/> it was on the Pope, the late Pope. I remember it well. Upon my
<lb n="14511"/> word it was magnificent, the style of the oratory. And his voice!
<lb n="14512"/> God! hadn't he a voice! <emph>The Prisoner of the Vatican</emph>, he called
  <lb n="14513"/> him. I remember <persName xml:id="cf">Crofton</persName> saying to me when we came out .....</said>
  <lb n="14514"/> <said who="Jack Power">―But he's an Orangeman, <persName xml:id="cf">Crofton</persName>, isn't he? </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
    <lb n="14515"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―'Course he is, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, <said who="Tom Kernan">and a damned decent Or=
<lb n="14516"/> angeman too. We went into Butler's in Moore Street - faith, I
<lb n="14517"/> was genuinely moved, tell you the God's truth - and I remem=
<lb n="14518"/> ber well his very words. <said who="Crofton" direct="false"><emph>Kernan</emph>, </said>he said, <said who="Crofton" direct="false"><emph>we worship at
    <lb n="14519"/> different altars</emph>, </said>he said, <said who="Crofton" direct="false"><emph>but our belief is the same.</emph></said> Struck me as
<lb n="14520"/> very well put.</said>
    <lb n="14521"/> <said who="Jack Power">―There's a good deal in that, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. <said who="Jack Power">There used
<lb n="14522"/> always be crowds of Protestants in the chapel when <persName xml:id="ftb">Father
  <lb n="14523"/> Tom</persName> was preaching.</said>
    <lb n="14524"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―There's not much difference between us, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14525"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">We both believe in ........ </said></p>
<lb n="14526"/> <p>He hesitated for a moment.
<lb n="14527"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">― ... in the Redeemer. Only they don't believe in the Pope and
<lb n="14528"/> in the mother of God.</said>
  <lb n="14529"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―>But, of course, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> quietly and effectively,
  <lb n="14530"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">our religion is <emph>the</emph> religion, the old, original faith.</said>
  <lb n="14531"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Not a doubt of it, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> warmly.</p>
  <lb n="14532"/> <p><persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> came to the door of the bedroom and an=
<lb n="14533"/> nounced:
<lb n="14534"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―Here's a visitor for you!</said>
<lb n="14535"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Who is it?</said>
  <lb n="14536"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―<persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>.</said>
<lb n="14537"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―O, come in! come in!</said></p>
<lb n="14538"/> <p>A pale oval face came forward into the light. The arch of its
<lb n="14539"/> fair trailing moustache was repeated in the fair eyebrows
<lb n="14540"/> looped above pleasantly astonished eyes. <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName> was a
<lb n="14541"/> modest grocer. He had failed in business in a licensed house in
<lb n="14542"/> the city because his financial condition had constrained him to
<lb n="14543"/> tie himself to second class distillers and brewers. He had
<lb n="14544"/> opened a small shop on <place> <location> <geo> 53.363589 -6.272317 </geo> </location> <placeName> the Glasnevin road </placeName> </place> where, he flattered
<lb n="14545"/> himself, his manners would ingratiate him with the housewives
<lb n="14546"/> of the district. He bore himself with a certain grace, compli=
<lb n="14547"/> mented little children and spoke with a neat enunciation. He
<lb n="14548"/> was not without culture.</p>
  <lb n="14549"/> <p><persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName> brought a gift with him, a half pint of special
  <lb n="14550"/> whisky. He enquired politely for <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, placed his gift on
<lb n="14551"/> the table and sat down with the company on equal terms. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14552"/> Kernan</persName> appreciated the gift all the more since he was aware
<lb n="14553"/> that there was a small account for groceries unsettled between
  <lb n="14554"/> him and <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>. He said:
<lb n="14555"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I wouldn't doubt you, old man. Open that, <persName xml:id="jp">Jack</persName>, will you?</said></p>
  <lb n="14556"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> again officiated. Glasses were rinsed and five
<lb n="14557"/> small measures of whisky were poured out. This new influence
  <lb n="14558"/> enlivened the conversation. <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>, sitting on a small area
<lb n="14559"/> of the chair, was specially interested.
    <lb n="14560"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Pope Leo XIII, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">was one of the lights
<lb n="14561"/> of the age. His great idea, you know, was the union of the
<lb n="14562"/> Latin and Greek Churches. That was the aim of his life.</said>
<lb n="14563"/> <said who="Jack Power">―I often heard he was one of the most intellectual men in
    <lb n="14564"/> Europe, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>. <said who="Jack Power">I mean apart from his being Pope.</said>
    <lb n="14565"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―So he was, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">if not <emph>the</emph> most so. His
<lb n="14566"/> motto, you know, as Pope was <emph>Lux upon Lux - Light upon
<lb n="14567"/> Light.</emph></said>
    <lb n="14568"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―No, no, </said>said <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName> eagerly, <said who="Mr Fogarty">I think you're wrong there.
<lb n="14569"/> It was <emph>Lux in Tenebris</emph>, I think - <emph>Light in Darkness.</emph></said>
    <lb n="14570"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―O yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy"><emph>Tenebrae.</emph></said>
    <lb n="14571"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Allow me, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> positively, <said who="Mr Cunningham">it was <emph>Lux upon
<lb n="14572"/> Lux.</emph> And Pius IX, his predecessor's motto was <emph>Crux upon
<lb n="14573"/> Crux</emph>, that is, <emph>Cross upon Cross</emph>, to show the difference be=
<lb n="14574"/> tween their two pontificates.</said></p>
  <lb n="14575"/> <p>The inference was allowed. <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> continued:
<lb n="14576"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Pope Leo, you know, was a great scholar and a poet.</said>
    <lb n="14577"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―He had a strong face, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.
    <lb n="14578"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">He wrote Latin poetry.</said>
    <lb n="14579"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―Is that so? </said>said <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14580"/> <p><persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> tasted his whisky contentedly and shook his head
<lb n="14581"/> with a double intention, saying:
<lb n="14582"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―That's no joke, I can tell you.</said>
  <lb n="14583"/> <said who="Jack Power">―We didn't learn that, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>, following <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr
  <lb n="14584"/> M'Coy</persName>'s example, <said who="Jack Power">when we went to the penny-a-week school.</said>
<lb n="14585"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―There was many a good man went to the penny-a-week
    <lb n="14586"/> school with a sod of turf under his oxter, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>
<lb n="14587"/> sententiously. <said who="Tom Kernan">The old system was the best: plain honest edu=
<lb n="14588"/> cation. None of your modern trumpery ......</said>
    <lb n="14589"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Quite right, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.
    <lb n="14590"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―No superfluities, </said>said <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14591"/> <p>He enunciated the word and then drank gravely.
  <lb n="14592"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―I remember reading, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">that one of Pope
<lb n="14593"/> Leo's poems was on the invention of the photograph - in Latin,
<lb n="14594"/> of course.</said>
  <lb n="14595"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―On the photograph! </said>exclaimed <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.
  <lb n="14596"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.</p>
<lb n="14597"/> <p>He also drank from his glass.
  <lb n="14598"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Well, you know, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy">isn't the photograph
<lb n="14599"/> wonderful when you come to think of it?</said>
  <lb n="14600"/> <said who="Jack Power">―O, of course, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>, <said who="Jack Power">great minds can see things ....</said>
<lb n="14601"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―As the poet says: <emph>Great minds are very near to madness</emph>, </said>said
  <lb n="14602"/> <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14603"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> seemed to be troubled in mind. He made an
<lb n="14604"/> effort to recall the Protestant theology on some thorny points
  <lb n="14605"/> and in the end addressed <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
    <lb n="14606"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Tell me, <persName xml:id="mc">Martin</persName>, </said>he said. <said who="Tom Kernan">Weren't some of the popes - of
<lb n="14607"/> course, not our present man or his predecessor, but some of the
<lb n="14608"/> old popes - not exactly .... you know .... up to the knocker?</said></p>
  <lb n="14609"/> <p>There was a silence. <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> said:
<lb n="14610"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O, of course, there were some bad lots ....... But the aston=
<lb n="14611"/> ishing thing is this. Not one of them, not the biggest drunkard,
<lb n="14612"/> not the most ... out-and-out ruffian, not one of them ever
<lb n="14613"/> preached <emph>ex cathedra</emph> a word of false doctrine. Now isn't that
<lb n="14614"/> an astonishing thing?</said>
  <lb n="14615"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">-That is, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>.
<lb n="14616"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―Yes, because when the Pope speaks <emph>ex cathedra</emph>, </said><persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>
<lb n="14617"/> explained, <said who="Mr Fogarty">he is infallible.</said>
  <lb n="14618"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
<lb n="14619"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―O, I know about the infallibility of the Pope. I remember I
<lb n="14620"/> was younger then ... Or was it that?</said></p>
  <lb n="14621"/> <p><persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName> interrupted. He took up the bottle and helped
  <lb n="14622"/> the others to a little more. <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, seeing that there was not
<lb n="14623"/> enough to go round, pleaded that he had not finished his first
<lb n="14624"/> measure. The others accepted under protest. The light music of
<lb n="14625"/> whisky falling into glasses made an agreeable interlude.
<lb n="14626"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―What's that you were saying, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>? </said>asked <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
    <lb n="14627"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―Papal infallibility, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">that was the great=
<lb n="14628"/> est scene in the whole history of the Church.</said>
  <lb n="14629"/> <said who="Jack Power">―How was that, <persName xml:id="mc">Martin</persName>? </said>asked <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14630"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> held up two thick fingers.
<lb n="14631"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―In the sacred college, you know, of cardinals and arch=
<lb n="14632"/> bishops and bishops there were two men who held out against
<lb n="14633"/> it while the others were all for it. The whole conclave except
<lb n="14634"/> these two was unanimous. No! They wouldn't have it!</said>
  <lb n="14635"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―Ha! </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14636"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham?">―And they were a German cardinal by the name of Dolling ...
  <lb n="14637"/> or <persName xml:id="dl">Dowling</persName> ...  or ... -</said>
  <lb n="14638"/> <said who="Jack Power">―<persName xml:id="dl">Dowling</persName> was no German and that's a sure five, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr
  <lb n="14639"/> Power</persName> laughing.
<lb n="14640"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham?">―Well, this great German cardinal, whatever his name was,
  <lb n="14641"/> was one and the other was <persName xml:id="jm">John MacHale</persName>.</said>
  <lb n="14642"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―What? cried <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. Is it John of Tuam?</said>
    <lb n="14643"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―Are you sure of that now? </said>asked <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName> dubiously. <said who="Mr Fogarty">I
<lb n="14644"/> thought it was some Italian or American ...</said>
    <lb n="14645"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―John of Tuam, </said>repeated <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">was the man.</said></p>
<lb n="14646"/> <p>He drank and the other gentlemen followed his lead. Then
<lb n="14647"/> he resumed:
<lb n="14648"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―There they were at it, all the cardinals and bishops and
<lb n="14649"/> archbishops from all the ends of the earth and these two
<lb n="14650"/> fighting dog and devil until at last the Pope himself stood up
<lb n="14651"/> and declared infallibility a dogma of the Church <emph>ex cathedra.</emph>
  <lb n="14652"/> On the very moment <persName xml:id="jm">John MacHale</persName>, who had been arguing
<lb n="14653"/> and arguing against it, stood up and shouted out with the voice
<lb n="14654"/> of a lion: <emph>Credo!</emph></said>
  <lb n="14655"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―<emph>I believe!</emph> </said>said <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>.
  <lb n="14656"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―<emph>Credo!</emph> </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>. <said who="Mr Cunningham">That showed the faith he had.
<lb n="14657"/> He submitted the moment the Pope spoke.</said>
  <lb n="14658"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―And what about <persName xml:id="dl">Dowling</persName>?</said> asked <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>.
<lb n="14659"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―The German cardinal wouldn't submit. He left the Church.</said></p>
  <lb n="14660"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>'s words had built up the vast image of the
<lb n="14661"/> Church in the minds of his hearers. His deep raucous voice had
<lb n="14662"/> thrilled them as it uttered the word of belief and submission.
  <lb n="14663"/> When <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> came into the room drying her hands she
<lb n="14664"/> came into a solemn company. She did not disturb the silence
<lb n="14665"/> but leaned over the rail at the foot of the bed.
  <lb n="14666"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I once saw <persName xml:id="jm">John MacHale</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, <said who="Tom Kernan">and I'll never
    <lb n="14667"/> forget it as long as I live.</said></p>
<lb n="14668"/> <p>He turned towards his wife to be confirmed.
<lb n="14669"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I often told you that?</said></p>
  <lb n="14670"/> <p><persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> nodded.
<lb n="14671"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―It was at the unveiling of Sir <persName xml:id="jg">John Gray</persName>'s statue. <persName xml:id="dg">Edmund
  <lb n="14672"/> Dwyer Gray</persName> was speaking, blathering away, and here was this
<lb n="14673"/> old fellow, crabbed-looking old chap, looking at him from un=
<lb n="14674"/> der his bushy eyebrows.</said></p>
  <lb n="14675"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> knitted his brows and, lowering his head like an
<lb n="14676"/> angry bull, glared at his wife.
    <lb n="14677"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―God! </said>he exclaimed, reassuming his natural face, <said who="Tom Kernan">I never saw
<lb n="14678"/> such an eye in a man's head. It was as much as to say: <emph>I have
<lb n="14679"/> you properly taped, my lad.</emph> He had an eye like a hawk.</said>
    <lb n="14680"/> <said who="Jack Power">―None of the Grays was any good, </said>said <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="14681"/> <p>There was a pause again. <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> turned to <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName><persName xml:id="tk">
<lb n="14682"/> and said with abrupt joviality:
  <lb n="14683"/> <said who="Jack Power">―Well, <persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName>, we're going to make your man here a
<lb n="14684"/> good holy pious and God-fearing Roman Catholic.</said></p>
<lb n="14685"/> <p>He swept his arm round the company inclusively.
<lb n="14686"/> <said who="Jack Power">―We're all going to make a retreat together and confess our
<lb n="14687"/> sins and God knows we want it badly.</said>
    <lb n="14688"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I don't mind, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, smiling a little nervously.</p>
  <lb n="14689"/> <p><persName xml:id="mk">Mrs Kernan</persName> thought it would be wiser to conceal her satis=
<lb n="14690"/> faction. So she said:
<lb n="14691"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―I pity the poor priest that has to listen to your tale.</said></p>
  <lb n="14692"/> <p><persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>'s expression changed.
    <lb n="14693"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―If he doesn't like it, </said>he said bluntly, <said who="Tom Kernan">he can .... do the other
<lb n="14694"/> thing. I'll just tell him my little tale of woe. I'm not such a bad
<lb n="14695"/> fellow ..... </said></p>
  <lb n="14696"/> <p><persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName> intervened promptly.
    <lb n="14697"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―We'll all renounce the devil, </said>he said, <said who="Mr Cunningham">together, not forgetting
<lb n="14698"/> his works and pomps.</said>
    <lb n="14699"/> <said who="Mr Fogarty">―Get behind me, Satan! </said>said <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>, laughing and look=
<lb n="14700"/> ing at the others.</p>
  <lb n="14701"/> <p><persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> said nothing. He felt completely outgeneralled.
<lb n="14702"/> But a pleased expression flickered across his face.
    <lb n="14703"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―All we have to do, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>, <said who="Mr Cunningham">is to stand up with
<lb n="14704"/> lighted candles in our hands and renew our baptismal vows.</said>
<lb n="14705"/> <said who="Mr M'Coy">―O, don't forget the candle, <persName xml:id="tk">Tom</persName>, </said>said <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName>, <said who="Mr M'Coy">whatever
<lb n="14706"/> you do.</said>
    <lb n="14707"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―What? </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. <said who="Tom Kernan">Must I have a candle?</said>
    <lb n="14708"/> <said who="Mr Cunningham">―O yes, </said>said <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>.
    <lb n="14709"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―No, damn it all, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> sensibly, <said who="Tom Kernan">I draw the line
<lb n="14710"/> there. I'll do the job right enough. I'll do the retreat business
<lb n="14711"/> and confession and ... all that business. But ... no candles! No,
<lb n="14712"/> damn it all, I bar the candles!</said></p>
<lb n="14713"/> <p>He shook his head with farcical gravity.
    <lb n="14714"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―Listen to that! </said>said his wife.
    <lb n="14715"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―I bar the candles, </said>said <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>, conscious of having
<lb n="14716"/> created an effect on his audience and continuing to shake his
<lb n="14717"/> head to and fro. <said who="Tom Kernan">I bar the magic lantern business.</said></p>
<lb n="14718"/> <p>Everyone laughed heartily.
    <lb n="14719"/> <said who="Mrs Kernan">―There's a nice Catholic for you! </said>said his wife.
    <lb n="14720"/> <said who="Tom Kernan">―No candles! </said>repeated <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> obdurately. <said who="Tom Kernan">That's off!</said></p>
<lb /> *  *  *
<lb n="14721"/> <p>The transept of the Jesuit Church in <place> <location> <geo> 53.357903 -6.259664 </geo> </location> <placeName> Gardiner Street </placeName> </place> was
<lb n="14722"/> almost full; and still at every moment gentlemen entered from
<lb n="14723"/> the sidedoor and, directed by the lay brother, walked on tiptoe
<lb n="14724"/> along the aisles until they found seating accommodation. The
<lb n="14725"/> gentlemen were all well dressed and orderly. The light of the
<lb n="14726"/> lamps of the church fell upon an assembly of black clothes and
<lb n="14727"/> white collars, relieved here and there by tweeds, on dark
<lb n="14728"/> mottled pillars of green marble and on lugubrious canvasses.
<lb n="14729"/> The gentlemen sat in the benches, having hitched their trousers
<lb n="14730"/> slightly above their knees and laid their hats in security. They
<lb n="14731"/> sat well back and gazed formally at the distant speck of red
<lb n="14732"/> light which was suspended before the high altar.</p>
<lb n="14733"/> <p>In one of the benches near the pulpit sat <persName xml:id="mc">Mr Cunningham</persName>
  <lb n="14734"/> and <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>. In the bench behind sat <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr M'Coy</persName> alone: and
  <lb n="14735"/> in the bench behind him sat <persName xml:id="jp">Mr Power</persName> and <persName xml:id="fg">Mr Fogarty</persName>. <persName xml:id="cpm">Mr
  <lb n="14736"/> M'Coy</persName> had tried unsuccessfully to find a place in the bench
<lb n="14737"/> with the others and, when the party had settled down in the
<lb n="14738"/> form of a quincunx, he had tried unsuccessfully to make comic
<lb n="14739"/> remarks. As these had not been well received he had desisted.
<lb n="14740"/> Even he was sensible of the decorous atmosphere and even he
<lb n="14741"/> began to respond to the religious stimulus. In a whisper <persName xml:id="mc">Mr
  <lb n="14742"/> Cunningham</persName> drew <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>'s attention to <persName xml:id="hf">Mr Harford</persName>, the
<lb n="14743"/> moneylender, who sat some distance off, and to <persName xml:id="jf">Mr Fanning</persName>,
<lb n="14744"/> the registration agent and mayormaker of the city, who was
<lb n="14745"/> sitting immediately under the pulpit beside one of the newly
<lb n="14746"/> elected councillors of the ward. To the right sat old <persName xml:id="mg">Michael
  <lb n="14747"/> Grimes</persName>, the owner of three pawnbroker's shops, and <persName xml:id="dh">Dan
  <lb n="14748"/> Hogan</persName>'s nephew who was up for the job in the Town Clerk's
  <lb n="14749"/> office. Farther in front sat <persName xml:id="hn">Mr Hendrick</persName>, the chief reporter of
<lb n="14750"/> the <emph>Freeman's Journal</emph>, and poor <persName xml:id="oc">O'Carroll</persName>, an old friend of <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14751"/> Kernan</persName>'s, who had been at one time a considerable commercial
<lb n="14752"/> figure. Gradually, as he recognised familiar faces, <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName>
<lb n="14753"/> began to feel more at home. His hat, which had been rehabili=
<lb n="14754"/> tated by his wife, rested upon his knees. Once or twice he
<lb n="14755"/> pulled down his cuffs with one hand while he held the brim of
<lb n="14756"/> his hat lightly but firmly with the other hand.</p>
<lb n="14757"/> <p>A powerful-looking figure, the upper part of which was
<lb n="14758"/> draped with a white surplice, was observed to be struggling up
<lb n="14759"/> into the pulpit. Simultaneously the congregation unsettled,
<lb n="14760"/> produced handkerchiefs and knelt upon them with care. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr
  <lb n="14761"/> Kernan</persName> followed the general example. The priest's figure now
<lb n="14762"/> stood upright in the pulpit, two-thirds of its bulk crowned by a
<lb n="14763"/> massive red face appearing above the balustrade.</p>
  <lb n="14764"/> <p><persName xml:id="fp">Father Purdon</persName> knelt down, turned towards the red speck of
<lb n="14765"/> light and, covering his face with his hands, prayed. After an
<lb n="14766"/> interval he uncovered his face and rose. The congregation rose
  <lb n="14767"/> also and settled again on its benches. <persName xml:id="tk">Mr Kernan</persName> restored his
<lb n="14768"/> hat to its original position on his knee and presented an
<lb n="14769"/> attentive face to the preacher. The preacher turned back each
<lb n="14770"/> wide sleeve of his surplice with an elaborate large gesture and
<lb n="14771"/> slowly surveyed the array of faces. Then he said:
<lb n="14772"/> <said who="preacher">―<emph>For the children of this world are wiser in their generation
<lb n="14773"/> than the children of light. Wherefore make unto yourselves
<lb n="14774"/> friends out of the Mammon of iniquity so that when you die
<lb n="14775"/> they may receive you into everlasting dwellings.</emph></said></p>
  <lb n="14776"/> <p><persName xml:id="fp">Father Purdon</persName> developed the text with resonant assurance. <said who="Father Purdon">It
    <lb n="14777"/> was one of the most difficult texts in all the scriptures,</said> he said,<said who="Father Purdon">
    <lb n="14778"/> to interpret properly.</siad> It was a text which might seem to the
<lb n="14779"/> casual observer at variance with the lofty morality elsewhere
    <lb n="14780"/> preached by Jesus Christ. <said who="Father Purdon">But, </said>he told his hearers, <said who="Father Purdon">the text had
<lb n="14781"/> seemed to him specially adapted for the guidance of those
<lb n="14782"/> whose lot it was to lead the life of the world and who yet
<lb n="14783"/> wished to lead that life not in the manner of worldlings. It was
<lb n="14784"/> a text for business men and professional men. Jesus Christ,
<lb n="14785"/> with His divine understanding of every cranny of our human
<lb n="14786"/> nature, understood that all men were not called to the religious
<lb n="14787"/> life, that by far the vast majority were forced to live in the
<lb n="14788"/> world and, to a certain extent, for the world: and in this
<lb n="14789"/> sentence He designed to give them a word of counsel, setting
<lb n="14790"/> before them as exemplars in the religious life those very
<lb n="14791"/> worshippers of Mammon who were of all men the least
    <lb n="14792"/> solicitous in matters religious.</said></p>
<lb n="14793"/> <p>He told his hearers that <said who="Father Purdon" direct="false">he was there that evening for no
<lb n="14794"/> terrifying, no extravagant purpose, but as a man of the world
<lb n="14795"/> speaking to his fellow men. He came to speak to business men
    <lb n="14796"/> and he would speak to them in a businesslike way.</said> <said who="Father Purdon">If he might
    <lb n="14797"/> use the metaphor, </said>he said, <said who="Father Purdon">he was their spiritual accountant
<lb n="14798"/> and he wished each and every one of his hearers to open his
<lb n="14799"/> books, the books of his spiritual life, and see if they tallied
    <lb n="14800"/> accurately with conscience.</said></p>
<lb n="14801"/> <p><said who="Father Purdon">Jesus Christ was not a hard taskmaster. He understood our
<lb n="14802"/> little failings, understood the weakness of our poor fallen
<lb n="14803"/> nature, understood the temptations of this life. We might have
<lb n="14804"/> had, we all had from time to time, our temptations: we might
    <lb n="14805"/> have, we all had, our failings. But one thing only, </said>he
<lb n="14806"/> said, <said who="Father Purdon">he would ask of his hearers. And that was: to be straight and
<lb n="14807"/> manly with God. If their accounts tallied in every point to say:
<lb n="14808"/> <said who="believers">―Well, I have verified my accounts. I find all well.</said></p>
<lb n="14809"/> <p>But if, as might happen, there were some discrepancies, to
<lb n="14810"/> admit the truth, to be frank and say like a man:
<lb n="14811"/> <said who="believers">―Well, I have looked into my accounts. I find this wrong and
<lb n="14812"/> this wrong. But, with God's grace, I will rectify this and this. I
    <lb n="14813"/> will set right my accounts.</said></said></p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
