<div n="15" type="story"><lb n="150000"/> <head rend="italics">The Dead</head>
  <lb n="150001"/> <p><persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>, the caretaker's daughter, was literally run off her feet.
<lb n="150002"/> Hardly had she brought one gentleman into the little pantry
<lb n="150003"/> behind the office on the groundfloor and helped him off with
<lb n="150004"/> his overcoat when the wheezy halldoor bell clanged again and
<lb n="150005"/> she had to scamper along the bare hallway to let in another
<lb n="150006"/> guest. It was well for her she had not to attend to the ladies
  <lb n="150007"/> also. But <persName xml:id="kt">Miss Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="jl">Miss Julia</persName> had thought of that and had
<lb n="150008"/> converted the bathroom upstairs into a ladies' dressingroom.
  <lb n="150009"/> <persName xml:id="kt">Miss Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="jl">Miss Julia</persName> were there, gossiping and laughing
<lb n="150010"/> and fussing, walking after each other to the head of the stairs,
<lb n="150011"/> peering down over the banisters and calling down to <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> to ask
<lb n="150012"/> her who had come.</p>
<lb n="150013"/> <p>It was always a great affair, the Misses Morkan's annual
<lb n="150014"/> dance. Everybody who knew them came to it, members of the
<lb n="150015"/> family, old friends of the family, the members of <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s choir,
  <lb n="150016"/> any of <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>'s pupils that were grown up enough and even some
  <lb n="150017"/> of <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>'s pupils too. Never once had it fallen flat. For
<lb n="150018"/> years and years it had gone off in splendid style as long as
  <lb n="150019"/> anyone could remember, ever since <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, after the
  <lb n="150020"/> death of their brother <persName xml:id="pt">Pat</persName>, had left the house in <place> <location> <geo> 53.350693 -6.282098 </geo> </location> <placeName> Stony Batter </placeName> </place>
  <lb n="150021"/> and taken <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, their only niece, to live with them in the
<lb n="150022"/> dark gaunt house on <place> <location> <geo> 53.346397 -6.282658 </geo> </location> <placeName> Usher's Island </placeName> </place>, the upper part of which
  <lb n="150023"/> they had rented from <persName xml:id="fl">Mr Fullam</persName>, the corn factor on the
<lb n="150024"/> groundfloor. That was a good thirty years ago if it was a day.
  <lb n="150025"/><persName xml:id="mj"> Mary Jane</persName>, who was then a little girl in short clothes, was now
<lb n="150026"/> the main prop of the household for she had the organ in
<lb n="150027"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.335758 -6.239469 </geo> </location> <placeName> Haddington Road </placeName> </place>. She had been through the academy and gave
<lb n="150028"/> a pupils' concert every year in the upper room of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.344395 -6.250074 </geo> </location> <placeName> Antient
<lb n="150029"/> Concert Rooms </placeName> </place>. Many of her pupils belonged to better class
<lb n="150030"/> families on the <place> <location> <geo> 53.290518 -6.14838 </geo> </location> <placeName> Kingstown </placeName> </place> and <place> <location> <geo> 53.279133 -6.105698 </geo> </location> <placeName> Dalkey </placeName> </place> line. Old as they were,
  <lb n="150031"/> her aunts also did their share. <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, though she was quite grey,
<lb n="150032"/> was still the leading soprano in <place> <location> <geo> 53.345119 -6.274325 </geo> </location> <placeName> Adam and Eve's </placeName> </place> and <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>,
<lb n="150033"/> being too feeble to go about much, gave music lessons to
<lb n="150034"/> beginners on the old square piano in the back room. <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>, the
<lb n="150035"/> caretaker's daughter, did housemaid work for them. Though
<lb n="150036"/> their life was modest they believed in eating well, the best of
<lb n="150037"/> everything: diamond bone sirloins, three shilling tea and the
  <lb n="150038"/> best bottled stout. But <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> seldom made a mistake in the
<lb n="150039"/> orders so that she got on well with her three mistresses. They
<lb n="150040"/> were fussy, that was all. But the only thing they would not
<lb n="150041"/> stand was back answers.</p>
<lb n="150042"/> <p>Of course they had good reason to be fussy on such a night.
<lb n="150043"/> And then it was long after ten o'clock and yet there was no sign
  <lb n="150044"/> of <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> and his wife. Besides they were dreadfully afraid that
  <lb n="150045"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> might turn up screwed. They would not wish
  <lb n="150046"/> for worlds that any of <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>'s pupils should see him under
<lb n="150047"/> the influence: and when he was like that it was sometimes very
  <lb n="150048"/> hard to manage him. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> always came late but they
  <lb n="150049"/> wondered what could be keeping <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>: and that was what
<lb n="150050"/> brought them every two minutes to the banisters to ask <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>
  <lb n="150051"/> had <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> or <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName> come.
  <lb n="150052"/> <said who="">―</said>O, <persName xml:id="gc">Mr Conroy</persName>, said <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> to <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> when she opened the
  <lb n="150053"/> door for him, <persName xml:id="kt">Miss Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="jl">Miss Julia</persName> thought you were never
  <lb n="150054"/> coming. Good night, <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>.
<lb n="150055"/> <said who="">―</said>I'll engage they did, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, but they forget that my
<lb n="150056"/> wife here takes three mortal hours to dress herself.</p>
<lb n="150057"/> <p>He stood on the mat, scraping the snow from his goloshes,
  <lb n="150058"/> while <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> led his wife to the foot of the stairs and called out:
  <lb n="150059"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="kt">Miss Kate</persName>, here's <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150060"/> <p><persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> came toddling down the dark stairs at once.
  <lb n="150061"/> Both of them kissed <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s wife, said she must be perished
<lb n="150062"/> alive and asked was <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> with her.
<lb n="150063"/> <said who="">―</said>Here I am as right as the mail, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>! Go on up. I'll
  <lb n="150064"/> follow, called out <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> from the dark.</p>
<lb n="150065"/> <p>He continued scraping his feet vigorously while the three
<lb n="150066"/> women went upstairs, laughing, to the ladies' dressingroom. A
<lb n="150067"/> light fringe of snow lay like a cape on the shoulders of his
<lb n="150068"/> overcoat and like toecaps on the toes of his goloshes; and, as
<lb n="150069"/> the buttons of his overcoat slipped with a squeaking noise
<lb n="150070"/> through the snowstiffened frieze, a cold fragrant air from out
<lb n="150071"/> of doors escaped from crevices and folds.
<lb n="150072"/> <said who="">―</said>Is it snowing again, <persName xml:id="gc">Mr Conroy</persName>? asked <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150073"/> <p>She had preceded him into the pantry to help him off with
  <lb n="150074"/> his overcoat. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> smiled at the three syllables she had given
<lb n="150075"/> his surname and glanced at her. She was a slim growing girl,
<lb n="150076"/> pale in complexion and with haycoloured hair. The gas in the
  <lb n="150077"/> pantry made her look still paler. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> had known her when
<lb n="150078"/> she was a child and used to sit on the lowest step nursing a rag
<lb n="150079"/> doll.
  <lb n="150080"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>, he answered, and I think we're in for a night of it.</p>
<lb n="150081"/> <p>He looked up at the pantry ceiling which was shaking with
<lb n="150082"/> the stamping and shuffling of feet on the floor above, listened
<lb n="150083"/> for a moment to the piano and then glanced at the girl who was
<lb n="150084"/> folding his overcoat carefully at the end of a shelf.
  <lb n="150085"/> <said who="">―</said>Tell me, <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>, he said in a friendly tone, do you still go to
<lb n="150086"/> school?
<lb n="150087"/> <said who="">―</said>O no, sir, she answered, I'm done schooling this year and
<lb n="150088"/> more.
  <lb n="150089"/> <said who="">―</said>O then, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> gaily, I suppose we'll be going to your
<lb n="150090"/> wedding one of these fine days with your young man - eh?</p>
<lb n="150091"/> <p>The girl glanced back at him over her shoulder and said with
<lb n="150092"/> great bitterness:
<lb n="150093"/> <said who="">―</said>The men that is now is only all palaver and what they can
<lb n="150094"/> get out of you.</p>
  <lb n="150095"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> coloured as if he felt he had made a mistake and,
<lb n="150096"/> without looking at her, kicked off his goloshes and flicked
<lb n="150097"/> actively with his muffler at his patent leather shoes.</p>
<lb n="150098"/> <p>He was a stout tallish young man. The high colour of his
<lb n="150099"/> cheeks pushed upwards even to his forehead where it scattered
<lb n="150100"/> itself in a few formless patches of pale red; and on his hairless
<lb n="150101"/> face there scintillated restlessly the polished lenses and bright
<lb n="150102"/> gilt rims of the glasses which screened his delicate and restless
<lb n="150103"/> eyes. His glossy black hair was parted in the middle and
<lb n="150104"/> brushed in a long curve behind his ears where it curled slightly
<lb n="150105"/> beneath the groove left by his hat.</p>
<lb n="150106"/> <p>When he had flicked lustre into his shoes he stood up and
<lb n="150107"/> pulled his waistcoat down more tightly on his plump body.
<lb n="150108"/> Then he took a coin rapidly from his pocket.
  <lb n="150109"/> <said who="">―</said>O <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>, he said, thrusting it into her hand, it's Christmas
<lb n="150110"/> time, isn't it? Just .... here's a little .... </p>
<lb n="150111"/> <p>He walked rapidly towards the door.
<lb n="150112"/> <said who="">―</said>O no, sir! cried the girl, following him. Really, sir, I
<lb n="150113"/> wouldn't take it.
<lb n="150114"/> <said who="">―</said>Christmas time! Christmas time! said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, a<persName xml:id="ll">lmost trot=
<lb n="150115"/> ting to the stairs and waving his hand to her in deprecation.</p>
<lb n="150116"/> <p>The girl, seeing that he had gained the stairs, called out after
<lb n="150117"/> him:
<lb n="150118"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, thank you, sir.</p>
<lb n="150119"/> <p>He waited outside the drawingroom door until the waltz
<lb n="150120"/> should finish, listening to the skirts that swept against it and to
<lb n="150121"/> the shuffling of feet. He was still discomposed by the girl's
<lb n="150122"/> bitter and sudden retort. It had cast a gloom over him which he
<lb n="150123"/> tried to dispel by arranging his cuffs and the bows of his tie.
<lb n="150124"/> Then he took from his waistcoat pocket a little paper and
<lb n="150125"/> glanced at the headings he had made for his speech. He was
  <lb n="150126"/> undecided about the lines from <persName xml:id="rb">Robert Browning</persName> for he feared
<lb n="150127"/> they would be above the heads of his hearers. Some quotation
<lb n="150128"/> that they could recognise from Shakespeare or from the mel=
<lb n="150129"/> odies would be better. The indelicate clacking of the men's
<lb n="150130"/> heels and the shuffling of their soles reminded him that their
<lb n="150131"/> grade of culture differed from his. He would only make himself
<lb n="150132"/> ridiculous by quoting poetry to them which they could not
<lb n="150133"/> understand. They would think that he was airing his superior
<lb n="150134"/> education. He would fail with them just as he had failed with
<lb n="150135"/> the girl in the pantry. He had taken up a wrong tone. His
<lb n="150136"/> whole speech was a mistake from first to last, an utter failure.</p>
<lb n="150137"/> <p>Just then his aunts and his wife came out of the ladies'
<lb n="150138"/> dressingroom. His aunts were two small plainly dressed old
  <lb n="150139"/> women. Aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> was an inch or so the taller. Her hair,
<lb n="150140"/> drawn low over the tops of her ears, was grey; and grey also,
<lb n="150141"/> with darker shadows, was her large flaccid face. Though she
<lb n="150142"/> was stout in build and stood erect her slow eyes and parted lips
<lb n="150143"/> gave her the appearance of a woman who did not know where
  <lb n="150144"/> she was or where she was going. Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> was more viva=
<lb n="150145"/> cious. Her face, healthier than her sister's, was all puckers and
<lb n="150146"/> creases like a shrivelled red apple and her hair, braided in the
<lb n="150147"/> same oldfashioned way, had not lost its ripe nut colour.</p>
  <lb n="150148"/> <p>They both kissed <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> frankly. He was their favourite
  <lb n="150149"/> nephew, the son of their dead elder sister <persName xml:id="el">Ellen</persName> who had
  <lb n="150150"/> married <persName xml:id="tjc">T J Conroy</persName> of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.350868 -6.218374 </geo> </location> <placeName> Port and Docks </placeName> </place>.
  <lb n="150151"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> tells me you're not going to take a cab back to
  <lb n="150152"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.293205 -6.153396 </geo> </location> <placeName> Monkstown </placeName> </place> tonight, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, said Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>.
  <lb n="150153"/> <said who="">―</said>No, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, turning to his wife, we had quite enough
<lb n="150154"/> of that last year, hadn't we? Don't you remember, Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>,
  <lb n="150155"/> what a cold <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> got out of it? Cab windows rattling all the
<lb n="150156"/> way and the east wind blowing in after we passed <place> <location> <geo> 53.30257 -6.192169 </geo> </location> <placeName> Merrion </placeName> </place>.
  <lb n="150157"/> Very jolly it was. <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> caught a dreadful cold.</p>
  <lb n="150158"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> frowned severely and nodded her head at every
<lb n="150159"/> word.
  <lb n="150160"/> <said who="">―</said>Quite right, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, quite right, she said. You can't be too
<lb n="150161"/> careful.
  <lb n="150162"/> <said who="">―</said>But as for <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> there, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, she'd walk home in the
<lb n="150163"/> snow if she were let.</p>
  <lb n="150164"/> <p><persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName> laughed.
  <lb n="150165"/> <said who="">―</said>Don't mind him, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, she said. He's really an awful
<lb n="150166"/> bother, what with green shades for Tom's eyes at night and
<lb n="150167"/> making him do the dumbbells and forcing Lottie to eat the
<lb n="150168"/> stirabout. The poor child! And she simply hates the sight of
<lb n="150169"/> it! .... O, but you'll never guess what he makes me wear now!</p>
<lb n="150170"/> <p>She broke out into a peal of laughter and glanced at her
<lb n="150171"/> husband whose admiring and happy eyes had been wandering
<lb n="150172"/> from her dress to her face and hair. The two aunts laughed
  <lb n="150173"/> heartily too for <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s solicitude was a standing joke with
<lb n="150174"/> them.
  <lb n="150175"/> <said who="">―</said>Goloshes! said <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>. That's the latest. Whenever it's
<lb n="150176"/> wet underfoot I must put on my goloshes. Tonight even he
<lb n="150177"/> wanted me to put them on but I wouldn't. The next thing he'll
<lb n="150178"/> buy me will be a diving suit.</p>
  <lb n="150179"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> laughed nervously and patted his tie reassuringly
  <lb n="150180"/> while aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> nearly doubled herself so heartily did she enjoy
  <lb n="150181"/> the joke. The smile soon faded from aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s face and her
<lb n="150182"/> mirthless eyes were directed towards her nephew's face. After a
<lb n="150183"/> pause she asked:
<lb n="150184"/> <said who="">―</said>And what are goloshes, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>?
  <lb n="150185"/> <said who="">―</said>Goloshes, <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>! exclaimed her sister. Goodness me, don't
<lb n="150186"/> you know what goloshes are? You wear them over your ....
  <lb n="150187"/> over your boots, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>, isn't it?
  <lb n="150188"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, said <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>. Guttapercha things. We both have a
  <lb n="150189"/> pair now. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> says everyone wears them on the continent.
<lb n="150190"/> <said who="">―</said>O, on the continent, murmured aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, nodding her head
<lb n="150191"/> slowly.</p>
  <lb n="150192"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> knitted his brows and said, as if he were slightly
<lb n="150193"/> angered:
<lb n="150194"/> <said who="">―</said>It's nothing very wonderful but <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> thinks it very funny
<lb n="150195"/> because she says the word reminds her of christy minstrels.
  <lb n="150196"/> <said who="">―</said>But tell me, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> with brisk tact. Of
  <lb n="150197"/> course you've seen about the room. <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> was saying ....
<lb n="150198"/> <said who="">―</said>O, the room is all right, replied <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persNAme>. I've taken one in the
<lb n="150199"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.35165 -6.260879 </geo> </location> <placeName> Gresham </placeName> </place>.
  <lb n="150200"/> <said who="">―</said>To be sure, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, by far the best thing to do. And
  <lb n="150201"/> the children, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>, you're not anxious about them?
<lb n="150202"/> <said who="">―</said>O, for one night, said <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>. Besides <persName xml:id="bs">Bessie will look
<lb n="150203"/> after them.
  <lb n="150204"/> <said who="">―</said>To be sure, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> again. What a comfort it is to
<lb n="150205"/> have a girl like that, one you can depend on! There's that <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>,
<lb n="150206"/> I'm sure I don't know what has come over her lately. She's not
<lb n="150207"/> the girl she was at all.</p>
  <lb n="150208"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> was about to ask his aunt some questions on this
<lb n="150209"/> point but she broke off suddenly to gaze after her sister who
<lb n="150210"/> had wandered down the stairs and was craning her neck over
<lb n="150211"/> the banisters.
<lb n="150212"/> <said who="">―</said>Now, I ask you, she said almost testily, where is <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> going.
  <lb n="150213"/> <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>! <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>! Where are you going?</p>
  <lb n="150214"/> <p><persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> who had gone half way down one flight came back and
<lb n="150215"/> announced blandly:
  <lb n="150216"/> <said who="">―</said>Here's <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName>!</p>
<lb n="150217"/> <p>At the same moment a clapping of hands and a final flourish
<lb n="150218"/> of the pianist told that the waltz had ended. The drawingroom
<lb n="150219"/> door was opened from within and some couples came out.
  <lb n="150220"/> Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> drew <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> aside hurriedly and whispered into his
<lb n="150221"/> ear:
  <lb n="150222"/> <said who="">―</said>Slip down, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, like a good fellow and see if he's all right
<lb n="150223"/> and don't let him up if he's screwed. I'm sure he's screwed. I'm
<lb n="150224"/> sure he is.</p>
  <lb n="150225"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> went to the stairs and listened over the banisters. He
<lb n="150226"/> could hear two persons talking in the pantry. Then he recog=
  <lb n="150227"/> nised <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins'</persName> laugh. He went down the stairs noisily.
<lb n="150228"/> <said who="">―</said>It's such a relief, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> to <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>, that <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>
<lb n="150229"/> is here. I always feel easier in my mind when he's here .....
  <lb n="150230"/> <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, there's <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName> and <persName xml:id="pw">Miss Power</persName> will take some refresh=
  <lb n="150231"/> ment. Thanks for your beautiful waltz, <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName>. It made
<lb n="150232"/> lovely time.</p>
<lb n="150233"/> <p>A tall wizenfaced man with a stiff grizzled moustache and
<lb n="150234"/> swarthy skin who was passing out with his partner said:
<lb n="150235"/> <said who="">―</said>And may we have some refreshment too, Miss Morkan?
  <lb n="150236"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> summarily, and here's <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> and
  <lb n="150237"/> <persName xml:id="fr">Miss Furlong</persName>. Take them in, <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, with <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName> and <persName xml:id="pw">Miss
  <lb n="150238"/> Power</persName>.
<lb n="150239"/> <said who="">―</said>I'm the man for the ladies, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, pursing his lips
<lb n="150240"/> until his moustache bristled and smiling in all his wrinkles. You
<lb n="150241"/> know, Miss Morkan, the reason they are so fond of me is .....</p>
<lb n="150242"/> <p>He did not finish his sentence but, seeing that aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> was
<lb n="150243"/> out of earshot, at once led the three young ladies into the back
<lb n="150244"/> room. The middle of the room was occupied by two square
  <lb n="150245"/> tables placed end to end and on these aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> and the
<lb n="150246"/> caretaker were straightening and smoothing a large cloth. On
<lb n="150247"/> the sideboard were arrayed dishes and plates and glasses and
<lb n="150248"/> bundles of knives and forks and spoons. The top of the closed
<lb n="150249"/> square piano served also as a sideboard for viands and sweets.
<lb n="150250"/> At a smaller sideboard in one corner two young men were
<lb n="150251"/> standing, drinking hop bitters.</p>
  <lb n="150252"/> <p><persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> led his charges thither and invited them all, in
<lb n="150253"/> jest, to some ladies' punch, hot, strong and sweet. As they said
<lb n="150254"/> they never took anything strong he opened three bottles of
<lb n="150255"/> lemonade for them. Then he asked one of the young men to
<lb n="150256"/> move aside and, taking hold of the decanter, filled out for him=
<lb n="150257"/> self a goodly measure of whisky. The young men eyed him
<lb n="150258"/> respectfully while he took a trial sip.
<lb n="150259"/> <said who="">―</said>God help me, he said smiling, it's the doctor's orders.</p>
<lb n="150260"/> <p>His wizened face broke into a broader smile and the three
<lb n="150261"/> young ladies laughed in musical echo to his pleasantry, swaying
<lb n="150262"/> their bodies to and fro, with nervous jerks of their shoulders.
<lb n="150263"/> The boldest said:
  <lb n="150264"/> <said who="">―</said>O, now, <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, I'm sure the doctor never ordered any=
<lb n="150265"/> thing of the kind.</p>
  <lb n="150266"/> <p><persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> took another sip of his whisky and said, with
<lb n="150267"/> sidling mimicry:
<lb n="150268"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, you see, I'm like the famous <persName xml:id="ca">Mrs Cassidy</persName> who is
  <lb n="150269"/> reported to have said: <emph>Now, <persName xml:id="mg">Mary Grimes</persName>, if I don't take it
<lb n="150270"/> make me take it for I feel I want it.</emph></p>
<lb n="150271"/> <p>His hot face had leaned forward a little too confidentially
<lb n="150272"/> and he had assumed a very low Dublin accent so that the young
<lb n="150273"/> ladies, with one instinct, received his speech in silence. <persName xml:id="fr">Miss
  <lb n="150274"/> Furlong</persName>, who was one of <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>'s pupils, asked <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName>
<lb n="150275"/> what was the name of the pretty waltz she had played; and <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150276"/> Browne</persName>, seeing that he was ignored, turned promptly to the
<lb n="150277"/> two young men who were more appreciative.</p>
<lb n="150278"/> <p>A redfaced young woman, dressed in pansy, came into the
<lb n="150279"/> room, excitedly clapping her hands and crying:
<lb n="150280"/> <said who="">―</said>Quadrilles! Quadrilles!</p>
  <lb n="150281"/> <p>Close on her heels came aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, crying:
<lb n="150282"/> <said who="">―</said>Two gentlemen and three ladies, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>!
  <lb n="150283"/> <said who="">―</said>O, here's <persName xml:id="bg">Mr Bergin</persName> and <persName xml:id="kg">Mr Kerrigan</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>. <persName xml:id="kg">Mr
  <lb n="150284"/> Kerrigan</persName>, will you take <persName xml:id="pw">Miss Power</persName>. <persName xml:id="fr">Miss Furlong</persName>, may I get
  <lb n="150285"/> you a partner, <persName xml:id="bg">Mr Bergin</persName>. O, that'll just do now.
  <lb n="150286"/> <said who="">―</said>Three ladies, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150287"/> <p>The two young gentlemen asked the ladies if they might
  <lb n="150288"/> have the pleasure and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> turned to <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName>.
  <lb n="150289"/> <said who="">―</said>O, <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName>, you're really awfully good after playing for
<lb n="150290"/> the last two dances but really we're so short of ladies tonight.
<lb n="150291"/> <said who="">―</said>I don't mind in the least, Miss Morkan.
<lb n="150292"/> <said who="">―</said>But I've a nice partner for you, <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>, the tenor.
<lb n="150293"/> I'll get him to sing later on. All Dublin is raving about him.
<lb n="150294"/> <said who="">―</said>Lovely voice, lovely voice! said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150295"/> <p>As the piano had twice begun the prelude to the first figure
  <lb n="150296"/> <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> led her recruits quickly from the room. They had
  <lb n="150297"/> hardly gone when aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> wandered slowly into the room,
<lb n="150298"/> looking behind her at something.
  <lb n="150299"/> <said who="">―</said>What is the matter, <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>? asked aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> anxiously. Who
<lb n="150300"/> is it?</p>
  <lb n="150301"/> <p><persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, who was carrying in a column of table-napkins,
<lb n="150302"/> turned to her sister and said simply, as if the question had
<lb n="150303"/> surprised her:
  <lb n="150304"/> <said who="">―</said>It's only <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName>, <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> with him.</p>
  <lb n="150305"/> <p>In fact right behind her <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> could be seen piloting
  <lb n="150306"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> across the landing. The latter, a young man of
  <lb n="150307"/> about forty, was of <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s size and build with very round
<lb n="150308"/> shoulders. His face was fleshy and pallid, touched with colour
<lb n="150309"/> only at the thick hanging lobes of his ears and at the wide
<lb n="150310"/> wings of his nose. He had coarse features, a blunt nose, a
<lb n="150311"/> convex and receding brow, tumid and protruded lips. His
<lb n="150312"/> heavylidded eyes and the disorder of his scanty hair made him
<lb n="150313"/> look sleepy. He was laughing heartily in a high key at a story
  <lb n="150314"/> which he had been telling <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> on the stairs and at the same
<lb n="150315"/> time rubbing the knuckles of his left fist backwards and
<lb n="150316"/> forwards into his left eye.
  <lb n="150317"/> <said who="">―</said>Good evening, <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150318"/> <p><persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> bade the Misses Morkan good evening in
<lb n="150319"/> what seemed an offhand fashion by reason of the habitual
  <lb n="150320"/> catch in his voice and then, seeing that <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> was
<lb n="150321"/> grinning at him from the sideboard, crossed the room on rather
<lb n="150322"/> shaky legs and began to repeat in an undertone the story he had
  <lb n="150323"/> just told to <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="150324"/> <said who="">―</said>He's not so bad, is he? said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> to <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150325"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s brows were dark but he raised them quickly and
<lb n="150326"/> answered:
<lb n="150327"/> <said who="">―</said>O no, hardly noticeable.
<lb n="150328"/> <said who="">―</said>Now, isn't he a terrible fellow! she said. And his poor
<lb n="150329"/> mother made him take the pledge on New Year's Eve. But come
  <lb n="150330"/> on, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, into the drawingroom.</p>
  <lb n="150331"/> <p>Before leaving the room with <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> she signalled to <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150332"/> Browne</persName> by frowning and shaking her forefinger in warning to
  <lb n="150333"/> and fro. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> nodded in answer and, when she had
  <lb n="150334"/> gone, said to <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>:
<lb n="150335"/> <said who="">―</said>Now then, Teddy, I'm going to fill you out a good glass of
<lb n="150336"/> lemonade just to buck you up.</p>
  <lb n="150337"/> <p><persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>, who was nearing the climax of his story,
  <lb n="150338"/> waved the offer aside impatiently but <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, having first
  <lb n="150339"/> called <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>' attention to a disarray in his dress, filled
<lb n="150340"/> out and handed him a full glass of lemonade. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins'</persName>
<lb n="150341"/> left hand accepted the glass mechanically, his right hand being
<lb n="150342"/> engaged in the mechanical readjustment of his dress. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150343"/> Browne</persName>, whose face was once more wrinkling with mirth,
<lb n="150344"/> poured out for himself a glass of whisky while <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>
<lb n="150345"/> exploded, before he had well reached the climax of his story, in
<lb n="150346"/> a kink of highpitched bronchitic laughter and, setting down his
<lb n="150347"/> untasted and overflowing glass, began to rub the knuckles of
<lb n="150348"/> his left fist backwards and forwards into his left eye, repeating
<lb n="150349"/> words of his last phrase as well as his fit of laughter would
<lb n="150350"/> allow him.</p>
<lb /> *  *  *
  <lb n="150351"/> <p>Gabriel could not listen while <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> was playing her
<lb n="150352"/> academy piece, full of runs and difficult passages, to the hushed
<lb n="150353"/> drawingroom. He liked music but the piece she was playing
<lb n="150354"/> had no melody for him and he doubted whether it had any
<lb n="150355"/> melody for the other listeners though they had begged <persName xml:id="mj">Mary
  <lb n="150356"/> Jane</persName> to play something. Four young men, who had come from
<lb n="150357"/> the refreshment room to stand in the doorway at the sound of
<lb n="150358"/> the piano, had gone away quietly in couples after a few
<lb n="150359"/> minutes. The only persons who seemed to follow the music
  <lb n="150360"/> were <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> herself, her hands racing along the keyboard
<lb n="150361"/> or lifted from it at the pauses like those of a priestess in
  <lb n="150362"/> momentary imprecation, and aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> standing at her elbow
<lb n="150363"/> to turn the page.</p>
  <lb n="150364"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s eyes, irritated by the floor which glittered with
<lb n="150365"/> beeswax under the heavy chandelier, wandered to the wall
<lb n="150366"/> above the piano. A picture of the balcony scene in <emph>Romeo and
<lb n="150367"/> Juliet</emph> hung there and beside it was a picture of the two
  <lb n="150368"/> murdered princes in the tower which aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> had worked in
<lb n="150369"/> red, blue and brown wools when she was a girl. Probably in the
<lb n="150370"/> school they had gone to as girls that kind of work had been
<lb n="150371"/> taught, for one year his mother had worked for him as a
<lb n="150372"/> birthday present a waistcoat of purple tabinet with little foxes'
<lb n="150373"/> heads upon it, lined with brown satin and having round
<lb n="150374"/> mulberry buttons. It was strange that his mother had had no
  <lb n="150375"/> musical talent though aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> used to call her the brains=
  <lb n="150376"/> carrier of the Morkan family. Both she and <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> had always
<lb n="150377"/> seemed a little proud of their serious and matronly sister. Her
<lb n="150378"/> photograph stood before the pierglass. She held an open book
<lb n="150379"/> on her knees and was pointing out something in it to <persName xml:id="ct">Constan=
  <lb n="150380"/> tine</persName> who, dressed in a man-o'-war suit, lay at her feet. It was
<lb n="150381"/> she who had chosen the names for her sons for she was very
<lb n="150382"/> sensible of the dignity of family life. Thanks to her, <persName xml:id="ct">Constantine</persName>
<lb n="150383"/> was now senior curate in <place> <location> <geo> 53.607685 -6.184122 </geo> </location> <placeName> Balbriggan </placeName> </place> and, thanks to her,
  <lb n="150384"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> himself had taken his degree in the royal university. A
<lb n="150385"/> shadow passed over his face as he remembered her sullen
<lb n="150386"/> opposition to his marriage. Some slighting phrases she had used
<lb n="150387"/> still rankled in his memory. She had once spoken of <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> as
  <lb n="150388"/> being country cute and that was not true of <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> at all. It was
  <lb n="150389"/> <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> who had nursed her all during her last long illness in
<lb n="150390"/> their house at <place> <location> <geo> 53.293205 -6.153396 </geo> </location> <placeName> Monkstown </placeName> </place>.</p>
  <lb n="150391"/> <p>He knew that <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> must be near the end of her piece
<lb n="150392"/> for she was playing again the opening melody with runs of
<lb n="150393"/> scales after every bar and while he waited for the end the
<lb n="150394"/> resentment died down in his heart. The piece ended with a trill
<lb n="150395"/> of octaves in the treble and a final deep octave in the bass.
  <lb n="150396"/> Great applause greeted <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> as, blushing and rolling up
<lb n="150397"/> her music nervously, she escaped from the room. The most
<lb n="150398"/> vigorous clapping came from the four young men in the
<lb n="150399"/> doorway who had gone away to the refreshment room at the
<lb n="150400"/> beginning of the piece but had come back when the piano had
<lb n="150401"/> stopped.</p>
  <lb n="150402"/> <p>Lancers were arranged. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> found himself partnered
  <lb n="150403"/> with <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>. She was a frankmannered talkative young lady
<lb n="150404"/> with a freckled face and prominent brown eyes. She did not
<lb n="150405"/> wear a lowcut bodice and the large brooch which was fixed in
<lb n="150406"/> the front of her collar bore on it an Irish device.</p>
<lb n="150407"/> <p>When they had taken their places she said abruptly:
<lb n="150408"/> <said who="">―</said>I have a crow to pluck with you.
  <lb n="150409"/> <said who="">―</said>With me? said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150410"/> <p>She nodded her head gravely.
  <lb n="150411"/> <said who="">―</said>What is it? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, smiling at her solemn manner.
<lb n="150412"/> <said who="">―</said>Who is G. C.? answered <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> turning her eyes upon
<lb n="150413"/> him.</p>
  <lb n="150414"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> coloured and was about to knit his brows as if he
<lb n="150415"/> did not understand when she said bluntly:
<lb n="150416"/> <said who="">―</said>O, innocent Amy! I have found out that you write for the
<lb n="150417"/> <emph>Daily Express.</emph> Now aren't you ashamed of yourself?
<lb n="150418"/> <said who="">―</said>Why should I be ashamed of myself? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> blinking
<lb n="150419"/> his eyes and trying to smile.
<lb n="150420"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, I'm ashamed of you, said <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> frankly. To say
<lb n="150421"/> you'd write for a rag like that. I didn't think you were a west
<lb n="150422"/> Briton.</p>
  <lb n="150423"/> <p>A look of perplexity appeared on <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s face. It was true
<lb n="150424"/> that he wrote a literary column every Wednesday in the <emph>Daily
<lb n="150425"/> Express</emph> for which he was paid fifteen shillings. But that did not
<lb n="150426"/> make him a west Briton surely. The books he received for
<lb n="150427"/> review were almost more welcome than the paltry cheque. He
<lb n="150428"/> loved to feel the covers and turn over the pages of newly
<lb n="150429"/> printed books. Nearly every day when his teaching in the
<lb n="150430"/> college was ended he used to wander down the quays to the
<lb n="150431"/> secondhand booksellers, to Hickey's on <place> <location> <geo> 53.347355 -6.260034 </geo> </location> <placeName> Bachelor's Walk </placeName> </place>, to
<lb n="150432"/> Webb's or Massey's on <place> <location> <geo> 53.34676 -6.260017 </geo> </location> <placeName> Aston's Quay </placeName> </place> or to Clohissey's in the
<lb n="150433"/> bystreet. He did not know how to meet her charge. He wanted
<lb n="150434"/> to say that literature was above politics. But they were friends
<lb n="150435"/> of many years' standing and their careers had been parallel,
<lb n="150436"/> first at the university and then as teachers: he could not risk a
<lb n="150437"/> grandiose phrase with her. He continued blinking his eyes and
<lb n="150438"/> trying to smile and murmured lamely that he saw nothing
<lb n="150439"/> political in writing reviews of books.</p>
<lb n="150440"/> <p>When their turn to cross had come he was still perplexed
  <lb n="150441"/> and inattentive. <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> promptly took his hand in a warm
<lb n="150442"/> grasp and said in a soft friendly tone:
<lb n="150443"/> <said who="">―</said>Of course, I was only joking. Come, we cross now.</p>
<lb n="150444"/> <p>When they were together again she spoke of the university
  <lb n="150445"/> question and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> felt more at ease. A friend of hers had
  <lb n="150446"/> shown her his review of <persName xml:id="rb">Browning</persName>'s poems. That was how she
<lb n="150447"/> had found out the secret: but she liked the review immensely.
<lb n="150448"/> Then she said suddenly:
  <lb n="150449"/> <said who="">―</said>O, <persName xml:id="gc">Mr Conroy</persName>, will you come for an excursion to the <place> <location> <geo> 53.057331 -9.531842 </geo> </location> <placeName> Aran
<lb n="150450"/> Isles </placeName> </place> this summer? We're going to stay there a whole month. It
<lb n="150451"/> will be splendid out in the Atlantic. You ought to come. <persName xml:id="cl">Mr
  <lb n="150452"/> Clancy</persName> is coming and <persName xml:id="ki">Mr Kilkelly</persName> and <persName xml:id="kk">Kathleen Kearney</persName>. It
  <lb n="150453"/> would be splendid for <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> too if she'd come. She's from
<lb n="150454"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.572918 -8.990035 </geo> </location> <placeName> Connacht </placeName> </place>, isn't she?
  <lb n="150455"/> <said who="">―</said>Her people are, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> shortly.
<lb n="150456"/> <said who="">―</said>But you will come, won't you? said <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>, laying her
<lb n="150457"/> warm hand eagerly on his arm.
  <lb n="150458"/> <said who="">―</said>The fact is, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, I have already arranged to go ...
  <lb n="150459"/> <said who="">―</said>Go where? asked <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>.
<lb n="150460"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, you know, every year I go for a cycling tour with some
<lb n="150461"/> fellows and so ...
  <lb n="150462"/> <said who="">―</said>But where? asked <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persNAme>.
<lb n="150463"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, we usually go to <place> <location> <geo> 46.377254 4.130859 </geo> </location> <placeName> France </placeName> </place> or <place> <location> <geo> 50.457504 5.009766 </geo> </location> <placeName> Belgium </placeName> </place> or perhaps Ger=
  <lb n="150464"/> many, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> awkwardly.
<lb n="150465"/> <said who="">―</said>And why do you go to <place> <location> <geo> 46.377254 4.130859 </geo> </location> <placeName> France </placeName> </place> and <place> <location> <geo> 50.457504 5.009766 </geo> </location> <placeName> Belgium </placeName> </place>, said <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>,
<lb n="150466"/> instead of visiting your own land?
  <lb n="150467"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, it's partly to keep in touch with the
<lb n="150468"/> languages and partly for a change.
<lb n="150469"/> <said who="">―</said>And haven't you your own language to keep in touch with,
  <lb n="150470"/> Irish? asked <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>.
<lb n="150471"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, said Gabriel, if it comes to that, you know, Irish is not
<lb n="150472"/> my language.</p>
<lb n="150473"/> <p>Their neighbours had turned to listen to the crossexamin=
  <lb n="150474"/> ation. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> glanced right and left nervously and tried to keep
<lb n="150475"/> his good humour under the ordeal which was making a blush
<lb n="150476"/> invade his forehead.
<lb n="150477"/> <said who="">―</said>And haven't you your own land to visit, continued <persName xml:id="iv">Miss
  <lb n="150478"/> Ivors</persName>, that you know nothing of, your own people and your
<lb n="150479"/> own country?
<lb n="150480"/> <said who="">―</said>O, to tell you the truth, retorted <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> suddenly, I'm sick
<lb n="150481"/> of my own country, sick of it!
  <lb n="150482"/> <said who="">―</said>Why? asked <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150483"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> did not answer for his retort had heated him.
  <lb n="150484"/> <said who="">―</said>Why? repeated <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150485"/> <p>They had to go visiting together and, as he had not
  <lb n="150486"/> answered her, <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> said warmly:
<lb n="150487"/> <said who="">―</said>Of course, you've no answer.</p>
  <lb n="150488"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName><persName xml:id="mj"> tried to cover his agitation by taking part in the
<lb n="150489"/> dance with great energy. He avoided her eyes for he had seen a
<lb n="150490"/> sour expression on her face. But when they met in the long
<lb n="150491"/> chain he was surprised to feel his hand firmly pressed. She
<lb n="150492"/> looked at him from under her brows for a moment quizzically
<lb n="150493"/> until he smiled. Then, just as the chain was about to start
<lb n="150494"/> again, she stood on tiptoe and whispered into his ear:
<lb n="150495"/> <said who="">―</said>West Briton!</p>
  <lb n="150496"/> <p>When the lancers were over <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> went away to a remote
  <lb n="150497"/> corner of the room where <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins'</persName> mother was sitting.
<lb n="150498"/> She was a stout feeble old woman with white hair. Her voice
<lb n="150499"/> had a catch in it like her son's and she stuttered slightly. She
  <lb n="150500"/> had been told that <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName> had come and that he was nearly all
  <lb n="150501"/> right. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> asked her whether she had had a good crossing.
<lb n="150502"/> She lived with her married daughter in <place> <location> <geo> 55.865627 -4.257223 </geo> </location> <placeName> Glasgow </placeName> </place> and came to
<lb n="150503"/> Dublin on a visit once a year. She answered placidly that she
<lb n="150504"/> had had a beautiful crossing and that the captain had been
<lb n="150505"/> most attentive to her. She spoke also of the beautiful house her
<lb n="150506"/> daughter kept in <place> <location> <geo> 55.865627 -4.257223 </geo> </location> <placeName> Glasgow </placeName> </place> and of the nice friends they had
  <lb n="150507"/> there. While her tongue rambled on <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> tried to banish
<lb n="150508"/> from his mind all memory of the unpleasant incident with <persName xml:id="iv">Miss
  <lb n="150509"/> Ivors</persName>. Of course the girl or woman or whatever she was was an
<lb n="150510"/> enthusiast but there was a time for all things. Perhaps he ought
<lb n="150511"/> not to have answered her like that. But she had no right to call
<lb n="150512"/> him a west Briton before people, even in joke. She had tried to
<lb n="150513"/> make him ridiculous before people, heckling him and staring at
<lb n="150514"/> him with her rabbit's eyes.</p>
<lb n="150515"/> <p>He saw his wife making her way towards him through the
<lb n="150516"/> waltzing couples. When she reached him she said into his ear:
  <lb n="150517"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> wants to know won't you carve the goose
  <lb n="150518"/> as usual. <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName> will carve the ham and I'll do the pudding.
  <lb n="150519"/> <said who="">―</said>All right, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="150520"/> <said who="">―</said>She's sending in the younger ones first as soon as this waltz
<lb n="150521"/> is over so that we'll have the table to ourselves.
<lb n="150522"/> <said who="">―</said>Were you dancing? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="150523"/> <said who="">―</said>Of course I was. Didn't you see me? What words had you
  <lb n="150524"/> with <persName xml:id="iv">Molly Ivors</persName>?
<lb n="150525"/> <said who="">―</said>No words. Why! Did she say so?
<lb n="150526"/> <said who="">―</said>Something like that. I'm trying to get that <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName> to
<lb n="150527"/> sing. He's full of conceit, I think.
<lb n="150528"/> <said who="">―</said>There were no words, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> moodily, only she
<lb n="150529"/> wanted me to go for a trip to the west of Ireland and I said I
<lb n="150530"/> wouldn't.</p>
<lb n="150531"/> <p>His wife clasped her hands excitedly and gave a little jump.
  <lb n="150532"/> <said who="">―</said>O, do go, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, she cried. I'd love to see <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place> again.
<lb n="150533"/> <said who="">―</said>You can go if you like, said Gabriel coldly.</p>
<lb n="150534"/> <p>She looked at him for a moment, then turned to <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName>
<lb n="150535"/> and said:
<lb n="150536"/> <said who="">―</said>There's a nice husband for you, <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName>.</p>
<lb n="150537"/> <p>While she was threading her way back across the room <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs
  <lb n="150538"/> Malins</persName>, without adverting to the interruption, went on to tell
  <lb n="150539"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> what beautiful places there were in Scotland and beau=
<lb n="150540"/> tiful scenery. Her son-in-law brought them every year to the
<lb n="150541"/> lakes and they used to go fishing. Her son-in-law was a
<lb n="150542"/> splendid fisher. One day he caught a fish, a beautiful big big
<lb n="150543"/> fish: and the man in the hotel boiled it for their dinner.</p>
  <lb n="150544"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> hardly heard what she said. Now that supper was
<lb n="150545"/> coming near he began to think again about his speech and
  <lb n="150546"/> about the quotation. When he saw <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> coming
  <lb n="150547"/> across the room to visit his mother <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> left the chair free
<lb n="150548"/> for him and retired into the embrasure of the window. The
<lb n="150549"/> room had already cleared and from the back room came the
<lb n="150550"/> clatter of plates and knives. Those who still remained in the
<lb n="150551"/> drawingroom seemed tired of dancing and were conversing
  <lb n="150552"/> quietly in little groups. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s warm trembling fingers
<lb n="150553"/> tapped the cold pane of the window. How cool it must be
<lb n="150554"/> outside! How pleasant it would be to walk out alone, first
<lb n="150555"/> along by the river and then through the park! The snow would
<lb n="150556"/> be lying on the branches of the trees and forming a bright cap
<lb n="150557"/> on the top of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.349117 -6.302977 </geo> </location> <placeName> Wellington monument </placeName> </place>. How much more
<lb n="150558"/> pleasant it would be there than at the supper table!</p>
<lb n="150559"/> <p>He ran over the headings of his speech: Irish hospitality, sad
<lb n="150560"/> memories, the Three Graces, <place> <location> <geo> 48.856667 2.350987 </geo> </location> <placeName> Paris </placeName> </place>, the quotation from <persName xml:id="rb">Brown=
  <lb n="150561"/> ing</persName>. He repeated to himself a phrase he had written in his
<lb n="150562"/> review: <emph>One feels that one is listening to a thoughttormented
  <lb n="150563"/> music.</emph> <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> had praised the review. Was she sincere? Had
<lb n="150564"/> she really any life of her own behind all her propagandism?
<lb n="150565"/> There had never been any ill feeling between them until that
<lb n="150566"/> night. It unnerved him to think that she would be at the supper
<lb n="150567"/> table, looking up at him while he spoke with her critical
<lb n="150568"/> quizzing eyes. Perhaps she would not be sorry to see him fail in
<lb n="150569"/> his speech. An idea came into his mind and gave him courage.
  <lb n="150570"/> He would say, alluding to aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>: <emph>Ladies and
<lb n="150571"/> gentlemen, the generation which is now on the wane among us
<lb n="150572"/> may have had its faults but for my part I think it had certain
<lb n="150573"/> qualities of hospitality, of humour, of humanity, which the new
<lb n="150574"/> and very serious and hypereducated generation that is growing
<lb n="150575"/> up around us seems to me to lack.</emph> Very good: that was one for
  <lb n="150576"/> <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>. What did he care that his aunts were only two
<lb n="150577"/> ignorant old women?</p>
<lb n="150578"/> <p>A murmur in the room attracted his attention. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>
<lb n="150579"/> was advancing from the door, gallantly escorting aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>
<lb n="150580"/> who leaned upon his arm, smiling and hanging her head. An
<lb n="150581"/> irregular musketry of applause escorted her also as far as the
  <lb n="150582"/> piano and then, as <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> seated herself on the stool and
  <lb n="150583"/> aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, no longer smiling, half turned so as to pitch her
<lb n="150584"/> voice fairly into the room, gradually ceased. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> recognised
<lb n="150585"/> the prelude. It was that of an old song of aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s, <emph>Arrayed
<lb n="150586"/> for the Bridal.</emph> Her voice strong and clear in tone attacked with
<lb n="150587"/> great spirit the runs which embellish the air and, though she
<lb n="150588"/> sang very rapidly, she did not miss even the smallest of the
<lb n="150589"/> grace notes. To follow the voice, without looking at the singer's
<lb n="150590"/> face, was to feel and share the excitement of swift and secure
  <lb n="150591"/> flight. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> applauded loudly with all the others at the close
<lb n="150592"/> of the song and loud applause was borne in from the invisible
<lb n="150593"/> supper table. It sounded so genuine that a little colour struggled
  <lb n="150594"/> into aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s face as she bent to replace in the music stand
<lb n="150595"/> the old leatherbound songbook that had her initials on the
  <lb n="150596"/> cover. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>, who had listened with his head perched
<lb n="150597"/> sideways to hear the better, was still applauding when everyone
<lb n="150598"/> else had ceased and talking animatedly to his mother who
<lb n="150599"/> nodded her head gravely and slowly in acquiescence. At last,
<lb n="150600"/> when he could clap no more, he stood up suddenly and hurried
  <lb n="150601"/> across the room to aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, whose hand he seized and held in
<lb n="150602"/> both his hands, shaking it when words failed him or the catch
<lb n="150603"/> in his voice proved too much for him.
<lb n="150604"/> <said who="">―</said>I was just telling my mother, he said, I never heard you sing
<lb n="150605"/> so well, never. No, I never heard your voice so good as it is
<lb n="150606"/> tonight. Now! Would you believe that now? That's the truth.
<lb n="150607"/> Upon my word and honour that's the truth. I never heard your
<lb n="150608"/> voice sound so fresh and so ... so clear and fresh, never.</p>
  <lb n="150609"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> smiled broadly and murmured something about
<lb n="150610"/> compliments as she released her hand from his grasp. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150611"/> Browne</persName> extended his open hand towards her and said to those
<lb n="150612"/> who were near him in the manner of a showman introducing a
<lb n="150613"/> prodigy to an audience:
  <lb n="150614"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="jl">Miss Julia Morkan</persName>, my latest discovery!</p>
<lb n="150615"/> <p>He was laughing very heartily at this himself when <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy
  <lb n="150616"/> Malins</persName> turned to him and said:
  <lb n="150617"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, <persName xml:id="bw">Browne</persName>, if you're serious you might make a worse
<lb n="150618"/> discovery. All I can say is I never heard her sing half so well as
<lb n="150619"/> long as I am coming here. And that's the honest truth.
  <lb n="150620"/> <said who="">―</said>Neither did I, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>. I think her voice has greatly
<lb n="150621"/> improved.</p>
  <lb n="150622"/> <p><persName xml:id="jl">Aunt Julia</persName> shrugged her shoulders and said with meek pride:
<lb n="150623"/> <said who="">―</said>Thirty years ago I hadn't a bad voice as voices go.
  <lb n="150624"/> <said who="">―</said>I often told <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> emphatically, that she was
<lb n="150625"/> simply thrown away in that choir. But she never would be said
<lb n="150626"/> by me.</p>
<lb n="150627"/> <p>She turned as if to appeal to the good sense of the others
  <lb n="150628"/> against a refractory child while aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> gazed in front of her,
<lb n="150629"/> a vague smile of reminiscence playing on her face.
  <lb n="150630"/> <said who="">―</said>No, continued aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, she wouldn't be said or led by
<lb n="150631"/> anyone, slaving there in that choir night and day, night and
<lb n="150632"/> day. Six o'clock on Christmas morning! And all for what?
<lb n="150633"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, isn't it for the honour of God, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>? asked <persName xml:id="mj">Mary
  <lb n="150634"/> Jane</persName> twisting round on the piano stool and smiling.</p>
  <lb n="150635"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> turned fiercely on her niece and said:
<lb n="150636"/> <said who="">―</said>I know all about the honour of God, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, but I think
<lb n="150637"/> it's not at all honourable for the pope to turn out the women
<lb n="150638"/> out of the choirs that have slaved there all their lives and put
<lb n="150639"/> little whippersnappers of boys over their heads. I suppose it is
<lb n="150640"/> for the good of the church if the pope does it. But it's not just,
  <lb n="150641"/> <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, and it's not right.</p>
<lb n="150642"/> <p>She had worked herself into a passion and would have con=
<lb n="150643"/> tinued in defence of her sister for it was a sore subject with her
  <lb n="150644"/> but <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, seeing that all the dancers had come back,
<lb n="150645"/> intervened pacifically:
  <lb n="150646"/> <said who="">―</said>Now, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, you're giving scandal to <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> who is
<lb n="150647"/> of the other persuasion.</p>
  <lb n="150648"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> turned to <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, who was grinning at this
<lb n="150649"/> allusion to his religion, and said hastily:
<lb n="150650"/> <said who="">―</said>O, I don't question the pope's being right. I'm only a stupid
<lb n="150651"/> old woman and I wouldn't presume to do such a thing. But
<lb n="150652"/> there's such a thing as common everyday politeness and grati=
  <lb n="150653"/> tude. And if I were in <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s place I'd tell that <persName xml:id="fh">Father Healy</persName>
<lb n="150654"/> straight up to his face ...
  <lb n="150655"/> <said who="">―</said>And besides, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, we really are all
<lb n="150656"/> hungry and when we are hungry we are all very quarrelsome.
<lb n="150657"/> <said who="">―</said>And when we are thirsty we are also quarrelsome, added <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150658"/> Browne</persName>.
<lb n="150659"/> <said who="">―</said>So that we had better go to supper, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, and
<lb n="150660"/> finish the discussion afterwards.</p>
  <lb n="150661"/> <p>On the landing outside the drawingroom <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> found his
  <lb n="150662"/> wife and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> trying to persuade <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> to stay for
  <lb n="150663"/> supper. But <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>, who had put on her hat and was
<lb n="150664"/> buttoning her cloak, would not stay. She did not feel in the
<lb n="150665"/> least hungry and she had already overstayed her time.
<lb n="150666"/> <said who="">―</said>But only for ten minutes, <persName xml:id="iv">Molly</persName>, said <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>. That
<lb n="150667"/> won't delay you.
<lb n="150668"/> <said who="">―</said>To take a pick itself, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, after all your dancing.
<lb n="150669"/> <said who="">―</said>I really couldn't, said <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>.
<lb n="150670"/> <said who="">―</said>I am afraid you didn't enjoy yourself at all, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>
<lb n="150671"/> hopelessly.
<lb n="150672"/> <said who="">―</said>Ever so much, I assure you, said <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>, but you really
<lb n="150673"/> must let me run off now.
<lb n="150674"/> <said who="">―</said>But how can you get home? asked <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>.
<lb n="150675"/> <said who="">―</said>O, it's only two steps up the quay.</p>
  <lb n="150676"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> hesitated a moment and said:
<lb n="150677"/> <said who="">―</said>If you will allow me, <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName>, I'll see you home if you
<lb n="150678"/> really are obliged to go.</p>
  <lb n="150679"/> <p>But <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> broke away from them.
<lb n="150680"/> <said who="">―</said>I won't hear of it, she cried. For goodness' sake go in to your
<lb n="150681"/> suppers and don't mind me. I'm quite well able to take care of
<lb n="150682"/> myself.
<lb n="150683"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, you're the comical girl, <persName xml:id="iv">Molly</persName>, said <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName>
<lb n="150684"/> frankly.
<lb n="150685"/> <said who="">―</said><emph>Beannacht libh</emph>, cried <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> with a laugh as she ran
<lb n="150686"/> down the staircase.</p>
  <lb n="150687"/> <p><persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> gazed after her, a moody puzzled expression on
  <lb n="150688"/> her face, while <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName> leaned over the banisters to listen
  <lb n="150689"/> for the halldoor. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> asked himself was he the cause of her
<lb n="150690"/> abrupt departure. But she did not seem to be in ill humour: she
<lb n="150691"/> had gone away laughing. He stared blankly down the staircase.</p>
  <lb n="150692"/> <p>At that moment aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> came toddling out of the supper
<lb n="150693"/> room, almost wringing her hands in despair.
  <lb n="150694"/> <said who="">―</said>Where is <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>? she cried. Where on earth is <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>?
<lb n="150695"/> There's everyone waiting in there, stage to let, and nobody to
<lb n="150696"/> carve the goose!
  <lb n="150697"/> <said who="">―</said>Here I am, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>! cried <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> with sudden animation,
<lb n="150698"/> ready to carve a flock of geese, if necessary.</p>
<lb n="150699"/> <p>A fat brown goose lay at one end of the table and at the
<lb n="150700"/> other end, on a bed of creased paper strewn with sprigs of
<lb n="150701"/> parsley, lay a great ham, stripped of its outer skin and peppered
<lb n="150702"/> over with crust crumbs, a neat paper frill round its shin, and
<lb n="150703"/> beside this was a round of spiced beef. Between these rival ends
<lb n="150704"/> ran parallel lines of side dishes: two little minsters of jelly, red
<lb n="150705"/> and yellow, a shallow dish full of blocks of blancmange and
<lb n="150706"/> red jam, a large green leafshaped dish with a stalkshaped
<lb n="150707"/> handle on which lay bunches of purple raisins and peeled
<lb n="150708"/> almonds, a companion dish on which lay a solid rectangle of
<lb n="150709"/> Smyrna figs, a dish of custard topped with grated nutmeg, a
<lb n="150710"/> small bowl full of chocolates and sweets wrapped in gold and
<lb n="150711"/> silver papers and a glass vase in which stood some tall celery
<lb n="150712"/> stalks. In the centre of the table there stood, as sentries to a
<lb n="150713"/> fruit stand which upheld a pyramid of oranges and American
<lb n="150714"/> apples, two squat oldfashioned decanters of cut glass, one
<lb n="150715"/> containing port and the other dark sherry. On the closed
<lb n="150716"/> square piano a pudding in a huge yellow dish lay in waiting
<lb n="150717"/> and behind it were three squads of bottles of stout and ale and
<lb n="150718"/> minerals drawn up according to the colours of their uniforms,
<lb n="150719"/> the first two black with brown and red labels, the third and
<lb n="150720"/> smallest squad white, with transverse green sashes.</p>
  <lb n="150721"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> took his seat boldly at the head of the table and,
<lb n="150722"/> having looked to the edge of the carver, plunged his fork firmly
<lb n="150723"/> into the goose. He felt quite at ease now for he was an expert
<lb n="150724"/> carver and liked nothing better than to find himself at the head
<lb n="150725"/> of a well laden table.
  <lb n="150726"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="fr">Miss Furlong</persName>, what shall I send you? he asked. A wing or a
<lb n="150727"/> slice of the breast?
<lb n="150728"/> <said who="">―</said>Just a small slice of the breast.
  <lb n="150729"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="hg">Miss Higgins</persName>, what for you?
  <lb n="150730"/> <said who="">―</said>O, anything at all, <persName xml:id="gc">Mr Conroy</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150731"/> <p>While <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> and <persName xml:id="dl">Miss Daly</persName> exchanged plates of goose and
  <lb n="150732"/> plates of ham and spiced beef <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> went from guest to guest
<lb n="150733"/> with a dish of hot floury potatoes wrapped in a white napkin.
  <lb n="150734"/> This was <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>'s idea and she had also suggested apple
  <lb n="150735"/> sauce for the goose but aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> had said that plain roast
<lb n="150736"/> goose without any apple sauce had always been good enough
<lb n="150737"/> for her and she hoped she might never eat worse. <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>
<lb n="150738"/> waited on her pupils and saw that they got the best slices and
  <lb n="150739"/> aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> opened and carried across from the
<lb n="150740"/> piano bottles of stout and ale for the gentlemen and bottles of
<lb n="150741"/> minerals for the ladies. There was a great deal of confusion and
<lb n="150742"/> laughter and noise, the noise of orders and counterorders, of
<lb n="150743"/> knives and forks, of corks and glass stoppers. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> began to
<lb n="150744"/> carve second helpings as soon as he had finished the first round
<lb n="150745"/> without serving himself. Everyone protested loudly so that he
<lb n="150746"/> compromised by taking a long draught of stout for he had
  <lb n="150747"/> found the carving hot work. <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> settled down quietly to
  <lb n="150748"/> her supper but aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> were still toddling
<lb n="150749"/> round the table, walking on each other's heels, getting in each
<lb n="150750"/> other's way and giving each other unheeded orders. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>
<lb n="150751"/> begged of them to sit down and eat their supper and so did
  <lb n="150752"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> but they said they were time enough so that, at last,
  <lb n="150753"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> stood up and, capturing aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, plumped her
<lb n="150754"/> down on her chair amid general laughter.</p>
  <lb n="150755"/> <p>When everyone had been well served <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> said smiling:
<lb n="150756"/> <said who="">―</said>Now if anyone wants a little more of what vulgar people call
<lb n="150757"/> stuffing let him or her speak.</p>
<lb n="150758"/> <p>A chorus of voices invited him to begin his own supper and
  <lb n="150759"/> <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName> came forward with three potatoes which she had reserved
<lb n="150760"/> for him.
  <lb n="150761"/> <said who="">―</said>Very well, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> amiably as he took another prepara=
<lb n="150762"/> tory draught, kindly forget my existence, ladies and gentlemen,
<lb n="150763"/> for a few minutes.</p>
<lb n="150764"/> <p>He set to his supper and took no part in the conversation
  <lb n="150765"/> with which the table covered <persName xml:id="ll">Lily</persName>'s removal of the plates. The
<lb n="150766"/> subject of talk was the opera company which was then at the
  <lb n="150767"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.340607 -6.254075 </geo> </location> <placeName> Theatre Royal </placeName> </place>. <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>, the tenor, a dark-com=
<lb n="150768"/> plexioned young man with a smart moustache, praised very
<lb n="150769"/> highly the leading contralto of the company but <persName xml:id="fr">Miss Furlong</persName>
<lb n="150770"/> thought she had a rather vulgar style of production. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy
  <lb n="150771"/> Malins</persName> said there was a negro chieftain singing in the second
<lb n="150772"/> part of the Gaiety pantomime who had one of the finest tenor
<lb n="150773"/> voices he had ever heard.
<lb n="150774"/> <said who="">―</said>Have you heard him? he asked <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName> across the
<lb n="150775"/> table.
<lb n="150776"/> <said who="">―</said>No, answered <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName> carelessly.
  <lb n="150777"/> <said who="">―</said>Because, <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> explained, now I'd be curious to
<lb n="150778"/> hear your opinion of him. I think he has a grand voice.
<lb n="150779"/> <said who="">―</said>It takes Teddy to find out the really good things, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150780"/> Browne</persName> familiarly to the table.
<lb n="150781"/> <said who="">―</said>And why couldn't he have a voice too? asked <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>
<lb n="150782"/> sharply. Is it because he's only a black?</p>
  <lb n="150783"/> <p>Nobody answered this question and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> led the table
<lb n="150784"/> back to the legitimate opera. One of her pupils had given her a
<lb n="150785"/> pass for <emph>Mignon.</emph> Of course, it was very fine, she said, but it
  <lb n="150786"/> made her think of poor Georgina Burns. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> could go
<lb n="150787"/> back farther still to the old Italian companies that used to come
<lb n="150788"/> to Dublin, Tietjens, Trebelli, Ilma de Murzka, Campanini, the
<lb n="150789"/> great Giuglini, Ravelli, Aramburo. Those were the days, he
<lb n="150790"/> said, when there was something like singing to be heard in
<lb n="150791"/> Dublin. He told too of how the top gallery of the old Royal
<lb n="150792"/> used to be packed night after night, of how one night an Italian
<lb n="150793"/> tenor had sung five encores to <emph>Let Me Like a Soldier Fall</emph>,
<lb n="150794"/> introducing a high C every time, and of how the gallery boys
<lb n="150795"/> would sometimes in their enthusiasm unyoke the horses from
<lb n="150796"/> the carriage of some great <emph>prima donna</emph> and pull her themselves
<lb n="150797"/> through the streets to her hotel. Why did they never play the
<lb n="150798"/> grand old operas now, he asked. <emph>Dinorah, Lucrezia Borgia?</emph>
<lb n="150799"/> Because they could not get the voices to sing them: that was
<lb n="150800"/> why.
<lb n="150801"/> <said who="">―</said>O, well, said <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>, I presume there are as good
<lb n="150802"/> singers today as there were then.
<lb n="150803"/> <said who="">―</said>Where are they? asked <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> defiantly.
<lb n="150804"/> <said who="">―</said>In <place> <location> <geo> 51.500153 -0.126236 </geo> </location> <placeName> London </placeName> </place>, <place> <location> <geo> 48.856667 2.350987 </geo> </location> <placeName> Paris </placeName> </place>, <place> <location> <geo> 45.463688 9.188141 </geo> </location> <placeName> Milan </placeName> </place>, said <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName> warmly. I
<lb n="150805"/> suppose Caruso, for example, is quite as good, if not better
<lb n="150806"/> than any of the men you have mentioned.
  <lb n="150807"/> <said who="">―</said>Maybe so, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>. But I may tell you I doubt it
<lb n="150808"/> strongly.
<lb n="150809"/> <said who="">―</said>O, I'd give anything to hear Caruso sing, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>.
  <lb n="150810"/> <said who="">―</said>For me, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, who had been picking a bone, there
<lb n="150811"/> was only one tenor. To please me, I mean. But I suppose none
<lb n="150812"/> of you ever heard of him.
<lb n="150813"/> <said who="">―</said>Who was he, Miss Morkan? asked <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName> pol=
<lb n="150814"/> itely.
  <lb n="150815"/> <said who="">―</said>His name, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, was <persName xml:id="pk">Parkinson</persName>. I heard him when
<lb n="150816"/> he was in his prime and I think he had then the purest tenor
<lb n="150817"/> voice that was ever put into a man's throat.
<lb n="150818"/> <said who="">―</said>Strange, said <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>. I never even heard of him.
<lb n="150819"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, yes, Miss Morkan is right, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>. I remember
  <lb n="150820"/> hearing of old <persName xml:id="pk">Parkinson</persName> but he's too far back for me.
<lb n="150821"/> <said who="">―</said>A beautiful pure sweet mellow English tenor, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>
<lb n="150822"/> with enthusiasm.</p>
  <lb n="150823"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> having finished, the huge pudding was transferred to
<lb n="150824"/> the table. The clatter of forks and spoons began again. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabri=
  <lb n="150825"/> el</persName>'s wife served out spoonfuls of the pudding and passed the
<lb n="150826"/> plates down the table. Midway down they were held up by
  <lb n="150827"/> <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> who replenished them with raspberry or orange jelly
<lb n="150828"/> or with blancmange and jam. The pudding was of aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s
<lb n="150829"/> making and she received praises for it from all quarters. She
<lb n="150830"/> herself said that it was not quite brown enough.
<lb n="150831"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, I hope, Miss Morkan, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, that I'm brown
<lb n="150832"/> enough for you because, you know, I'm all brown.</p>
  <lb n="150833"/> <p>All the gentlemen, except <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, ate some of the pudding
  <lb n="150834"/> out of compliment to aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>. As <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> never ate sweets
  <lb n="150835"/> the celery had been left for him. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> also took a
<lb n="150836"/> stalk of celery and ate it with his pudding. He had been told
<lb n="150837"/> that celery was a capital thing for the blood and he was just
  <lb n="150838"/> then under doctor's care. <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName>, who had been silent all
<lb n="150839"/> through the supper, said that her son was going down to
<lb n="150840"/> <place> <location> <geo> 52.188727 -7.858994 </geo> </location> <placeName> Mount Melleray </placeName> </place> in a week or so. The table then spoke of
<lb n="150841"/> <place> <location> <geo> 52.188727 -7.858994 </geo> </location> <placeName> Mount Melleray </placeName> </place>, how bracing the air was down there, how
<lb n="150842"/> hospitable the monks were and how they never asked for a
<lb n="150843"/> penny-piece from their guests.
<lb n="150844"/> <said who="">―</said>And do you mean to say, asked <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> incredulously,
<lb n="150845"/> that a chap can go down there and put up there as if it were a
<lb n="150846"/> hotel and live on the fat of the land and then come away with=
<lb n="150847"/> out paying a farthing?
<lb n="150848"/> <said who="">―</said>O, most people give some donation to the monastery when
  <lb n="150849"/> they leave, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>.
<lb n="150850"/> <said who="">―</said>I wish we had an institution like that in our church, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150851"/> Browne</persName> candidly.</p>
<lb n="150852"/> <p>He was astonished to hear that the monks never spoke, got
<lb n="150853"/> up at two in the morning and slept in their coffins. He asked
<lb n="150854"/> what they did it for.
<lb n="150855"/> <said who="">―</said>That's the rule of the order, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> firmly.
  <lb n="150856"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, but why? asked <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150857"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> repeated that it was the rule, that was all. <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="150858"/> Browne</persName> still seemed not to understand. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> ex=
<lb n="150859"/> plained to him, as best he could, that the monks were trying to
<lb n="150860"/> make up for the sins committed by all the sinners in the outside
<lb n="150861"/> world. The explanation was not very clear for <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>
<lb n="150862"/> grinned and said:
<lb n="150863"/> <said who="">―</said>I like that idea very much but wouldn't a comfortable spring
<lb n="150864"/> bed do them as well as a coffin?
  <lb n="150865"/> <said who="">―</said>The coffin, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, is to remind them of their last
<lb n="150866"/> end.</p>
<lb n="150867"/> <p>As the subject had grown lugubrious it was buried in a si=
  <lb n="150868"/> lence of the table during which <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName> could be heard
<lb n="150869"/> saying to her neighbour in an indistinct undertone:
<lb n="150870"/> <said who="">―</said>They are very good men, the monks, very pious men.</p>
<lb n="150871"/> <p>The raisins and almonds and figs and apples and oranges
<lb n="150872"/> and chocolates and sweets were now passed about the table
  <lb n="150873"/> and aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> invited all the guests to have either port or
  <lb n="150874"/> sherry. At first <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName> refused to take either but one
<lb n="150875"/> of his neighbours nudged him and whispered something to
<lb n="150876"/> him upon which he allowed his glass to be filled. Gradually as
<lb n="150877"/> the last glasses were being filled the conversation ceased. A
<lb n="150878"/> pause followed, broken only by the noise of the wine and by
<lb n="150879"/> unsettlings of chairs. The Misses Morkan, all three, looked
<lb n="150880"/> down at the tablecloth. Someone coughed once or twice and
<lb n="150881"/> then a few gentlemen patted the table gently as a signal for
  <lb n="150882"/> silence. The silence came and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> pushed back his chair
<lb n="150883"/> and stood up.</p>
<lb n="150884"/> <p>The patting at once grew louder in encouragement and then
  <lb n="150885"/> ceased altogether. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> leaned his ten trembling fingers on
<lb n="150886"/> the tablecloth and smiled nervously at the company. Meeting a
<lb n="150887"/> row of upturned faces he raised his eyes to the chandelier. The
<lb n="150888"/> piano was playing a waltz tune and he could hear the skirts
<lb n="150889"/> sweeping against the drawingroom door. People perhaps were
<lb n="150890"/> standing in the snow on the quay outside, gazing up at the
<lb n="150891"/> lighted windows and listening to the waltz music. The air was
<lb n="150892"/> pure there. In the distance lay the park where the trees were
<lb n="150893"/> weighted with snow. The <place> <location> <geo> 53.349117 -6.302977 </geo> </location> <placeName> Wellington monument </placeName> </place> wore a gleam=
<lb n="150894"/> ing cap of snow that flashed westward over the white field of
<lb n="150895"/> Fifteen Acres.</p>
<lb n="150896"/> <p>He began:
<lb n="150897"/> <said who="">―</said>Ladies and gentlemen.
<lb n="150898"/> It has fallen to my lot this evening as in years past to perform a
<lb n="150899"/> very pleasing task, but a task for which I am afraid my poor
<lb n="150900"/> powers as a speaker are all too inadequate.
  <lb n="150901"/> <said who="">―</said>No, no, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>.
<lb n="150902"/> <said who="">―</said>But, however that may be, I can only ask you tonight to take
<lb n="150903"/> the will for the deed and to lend me your attention for a few
<lb n="150904"/> moments while I endeavour to express to you in words what
<lb n="150905"/> my feelings are on this occasion.
<lb n="150906"/> <said who="">―</said>Ladies and gentlemen. It is not the first time that we have
<lb n="150907"/> gathered together under this hospitable roof, around this hos=
<lb n="150908"/> pitable board. It is not the first time that we have been the
<lb n="150909"/> recipients - or, perhaps I had better say, the victims - of the
<lb n="150910"/> hospitality of certain good ladies.</p>
<lb n="150911"/> <p>He made a circle in the air with his arm and paused. Every=
  <lb n="150912"/> one laughed or smiled at aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary
  <lb n="150913"/> Jane</persName> who all turned crimson with pleasure. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> went on
<lb n="150914"/> more boldly:
<lb n="150915"/> <said who="">―</said>I feel more strongly with every recurring year that our
<lb n="150916"/> country has no tradition which does it so much honour and
<lb n="150917"/> which it should guard so jealously as that of its hospitality. It is
<lb n="150918"/> a tradition that is unique so far as my experience goes (and I
<lb n="150919"/> have visited not a few places abroad) among the modern
<lb n="150920"/> nations. Some would say, perhaps, that with us it is rather a
<lb n="150921"/> failing than anything to be boasted of. But granted even that, it
<lb n="150922"/> is, to my mind, a princely failing and one that I trust will long
<lb n="150923"/> be cultivated among us. Of one thing, at least, I am sure. As
<lb n="150924"/> long as this one roof shelters the good ladies aforesaid - and I
<lb n="150925"/> wish from my heart it may do so for many and many a long
<lb n="150926"/> year to come - the tradition of genuine warmhearted courteous
<lb n="150927"/> Irish hospitality, which our forefathers have handed down to us
<lb n="150928"/> and which we in turn must hand down to our descendants, is
<lb n="150929"/> still alive among us.</p>
<lb n="150930"/> <p>A hearty murmur of assent ran round the table. It shot
  <lb n="150931"/> through <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s mind that <persName xml:id="iv">Miss Ivors</persName> was not there and that
<lb n="150932"/> she had gone away discourteously: and he said with confidence
<lb n="150933"/> in himself:
<lb n="150934"/> <said who="">―</said>Ladies and gentlemen.
<lb n="150935"/> A new generation is growing up in our midst, a generation
<lb n="150936"/> actuated by new ideas and new principles. It is serious and
<lb n="150937"/> enthusiastic for these new ideas and its enthusiasm, even when
<lb n="150938"/> it is misdirected, is, I believe, in the main sincere. But we are
<lb n="150939"/> living in a sceptical and, if I may use the phrase, a thoughttor=
<lb n="150940"/> mented age: and sometimes I fear that this new generation,
<lb n="150941"/> educated or hypereducated as it is, will lack those qualities of
<lb n="150942"/> humanity, of hospitality, of kindly humour which belonged to
<lb n="150943"/> an older day. Listening tonight to the names of all those great
<lb n="150944"/> singers of the past it seemed to me, I must confess, that we
<lb n="150945"/> were living in a less spacious age. Those days might without
<lb n="150946"/> exaggeration be called spacious days: and if they are gone be=
<lb n="150947"/> yond recall let us hope, at least, that in gatherings such as this
<lb n="150948"/> we shall still speak of them with pride and affection, still
<lb n="150949"/> cherish in our hearts the memory of those dead and gone great
<lb n="150950"/> ones whose fame the world will not willingly let die.
  <lb n="150951"/> <said who="">―</said>Hear! hear! said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> loudly.
  <lb n="150952"/> <said who="">―</said>But yet, continued <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, his voice falling into a softer
<lb n="150953"/> inflection, there are always in gatherings such as this sadder
<lb n="150954"/> thoughts that will recur to our minds: thoughts of the past, of
<lb n="150955"/> youth, of changes, of absent faces that we miss here tonight.
<lb n="150956"/> Our path through life is strewn with many such sad memories:
<lb n="150957"/> and were we to brood upon them always we could not find the
<lb n="150958"/> heart to go on bravely with our work among the living. We
<lb n="150959"/> have all of us living duties and living affections which claim,
<lb n="150960"/> and rightly claim, our strenuous endeavours.</p>
<lb n="150961"/> <p>Therefore I will not linger on the past. I will not let any
<lb n="150962"/> gloomy moralising intrude upon us here tonight. Here we are
<lb n="150963"/> gathered together for a brief moment from the bustle and rush
<lb n="150964"/> of our everyday routine. We are met here as friends, in the
<lb n="150965"/> spirit of good fellowship, as colleagues also, to a certain extent,
<lb n="150966"/> in the true spirit of <emph>camaraderie</emph>, and as the guests of - what
<lb n="150967"/> shall I call them? - the three Graces of the Dublin musical
<lb n="150968"/> world.</p>
<lb n="150969"/> <p>The table burst into applause and laughter at this sally. Aunt
  <lb n="150970"/> <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> vainly asked each of her neighbours in turn to tell her
  <lb n="150971"/> what <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> had said.
<lb n="150972"/> <said who="">―</said>He says we are the three Graces, aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="150973"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> did not understand but she looked up, smiling, at
  <lb n="150974"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> who continued in the same vein:
<lb n="150975"/> <said who="">―</said>Ladies and gentlemen.
<lb n="150976"/> I will not attempt to play tonight the part that <place> <location> <geo> 48.856667 2.350987 </geo> </location> <placeName> Paris </placeName> </place> played
<lb n="150977"/> on another occasion. I will not attempt to choose between
<lb n="150978"/> them. The task would be an invidious one and one beyond my
<lb n="150979"/> poor powers. For when I view them in turn, whether it be our
<lb n="150980"/> chief hostess herself, whose good heart, whose too good heart,
<lb n="150981"/> has become a byword with all who know her, or her sister,
<lb n="150982"/> who seems to be gifted with perennial youth and whose singing
<lb n="150983"/> must have been a surprise and a revelation to us all tonight, or,
<lb n="150984"/> last but not least, when I consider our youngest hostess,
<lb n="150985"/> talented, cheerful, hard-working and the best of nieces, I
<lb n="150986"/> confess, ladies and gentlemen, that I do not know to which of
<lb n="150987"/> them I should award the prize.</p>
  <lb n="150988"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> glanced down at his aunts and, seeing the large smile
  <lb n="150989"/> on aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>'s face and the tears which had risen to aunt
  <lb n="150990"/> <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>'s eyes, hastened to his close. He raised his glass of port
<lb n="150991"/> gallantly while every member of the company fingered a glass
<lb n="150992"/> expectantly and said loudly:
<lb n="150993"/> <said who="">―</said>Let us toast them all three together. Let us drink to their
<lb n="150994"/> health, wealth, long life, happiness and prosperity and may
<lb n="150995"/> they long continue to hold the proud and selfwon position
<lb n="150996"/> which they hold in their profession and the position of honour
<lb n="150997"/> and affection which they hold in our hearts.</p>
<lb n="150998"/> <p>All the guests stood up, glass in hand and, turning towards
<lb n="150999"/> the three seated ladies, sang in unison with <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> as
<lb n="151000"/> leader:
<lb n="151001"/> <said who="all">--</said>For they are jolly gay fellows,
<lb n="151002"/> For they are jolly gay fellows,
<lb n="151003"/> For they are jolly gay fellows
<lb n="151004"/> Which nobody can deny.</p>
  <lb n="151005"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> was making frank use of her handkerchief and
  <lb n="151006"/> even aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> seemed moved. <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> beat time with
<lb n="151007"/> his pudding fork and the singers turned towards one another as
<lb n="151008"/> if in melodious conference, while they sang with emphasis:</p>
<lb n="151009"/> <p><said who="">―</said>Unless he tells a lie,</p>
<lb n="151010"/> <p>.Unless he tells a lie.</p>
<lb n="151011"/> <p>Then turning once more towards their hostesses they sang:</p>
<lb n="151012"/> <p><said who="">―</said>For they are jolly gay fellows,</p>
<lb n="151013"/> <p>.For they are jolly gay fellows,</p>
<lb n="151014"/> <p>.For they are jolly gay fellows</p>
<lb n="151015"/> <p>.Which nobody can deny.</p>
<lb n="151016"/> <p>The acclamation which followed was taken up beyond the
<lb n="151017"/> door of the supper room by many of the other guests and
  <lb n="151018"/> renewed time after time, <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> acting as officer with
<lb n="151019"/> his fork on high.</p>
<lb /> *  *  *
<lb n="151020"/> <p>The piercing morning air came into the hall where they
  <lb n="151021"/> were standing so that aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> said:
<lb n="151022"/> <said who="">―</said>Close the door, somebody. <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName> will get her death of
<lb n="151023"/> cold.
  <lb n="151024"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="bw">Browne</persName> is out there, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>.
  <lb n="151025"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="bw">Browne</persName> is everywhere, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> lowering her voice.</p>
  <lb n="151026"/> <p><persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> laughed at her tone.
<lb n="151027"/> <said who="">―</said>Really, she said archly, he is very attentive.
<lb n="151028"/> <said who="">―</said>He has been laid on here like the gas, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> in the
<lb n="151029"/> same tone, all during the Christmas.</p>
<lb n="151030"/> <p>She laughed herself this time good-humouredly and then
<lb n="151031"/> added quickly:
<lb n="151032"/> <said who="">―</said>But tell him to come in, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, and close the door. I
<lb n="151033"/> hope to goodness he didn't hear me.</p>
<lb n="151034"/> <p>At that moment the halldoor was opened and <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>
<lb n="151035"/> came in from the doorstep, laughing as if his heart would
<lb n="151036"/> break. He was dressed in a long green overcoat with mock
<lb n="151037"/> astrakhan cuffs and collar and wore on his head an oval fur
<lb n="151038"/> cap. He pointed down the snowcovered quay whence the sound
<lb n="151039"/> of shrill prolonged whistling was borne in.
  <lb n="151040"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="ty">Teddy</persName> will have all the cabs in Dublin out, he said.</p>
  <lb n="151041"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> advanced from the little pantry behind the office,
<lb n="151042"/> struggling into his overcoat and, looking round the hall, said:
  <lb n="151043"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> not down yet?
<lb n="151044"/> <said who="">―</said>She's getting on her things, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>.
<lb n="151045"/> <said who="">―</said>Who's playing up there? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151046"/> <said who="">―</said>Nobody. They're all gone.
  <lb n="151047"/> <said who="">―</said>O no, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>. <persName xml:id="bda">Bartell D'Arcy</persName> and Miss
  <lb n="151048"/> <persName xml:id="ocl">O'Callaghan</persName> aren't gone yet.
<lb n="151049"/> <said who="">―</said>Someone is strumming at the piano, anyhow, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="151050"/> <p><persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> glanced at <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> and <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> and said with
<lb n="151051"/> a shiver:
<lb n="151052"/> <said who="">―</said>It makes me feel cold to look at you two gentlemen muffled
<lb n="151053"/> up like that. I wouldn't like to face your journey home at this
<lb n="151054"/> hour.
<lb n="151055"/> <said who="">―</said>I'd like nothing better this minute, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> stoutly,
<lb n="151056"/> than a rattling fine walk in the country or a fast drive with a
<lb n="151057"/> good spanking goer between the shafts.
<lb n="151058"/> <said who="">―</said>We used to have a very good horse and trap at home, said
  <lb n="151059"/> aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> sadly.
<lb n="151060"/> <said who="">―</said>The never-to-be-forgotten Johnny, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> laughing.</p>
  <lb n="151061"/> <p>Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> laughed too.
<lb n="151062"/> <said who="">―</said>Why, what was wonderful about Johnny? asked <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="151063"/> Browne</persName>.
<lb n="151064"/> <said who="">―</said>The late lamented <persName xml:id="pm">Patrick Morkan</persName>, our grandfather that is,
  <lb n="151065"/> explained <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, commonly known in his later years as the
<lb n="151066"/> old gentleman, was a glue boiler.
  <lb n="151067"/> <said who="">―</said>O now, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> laughing, he had a starch
<lb n="151068"/> mill.
<lb n="151069"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, glue or starch, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, the old gentleman had a
<lb n="151070"/> horse by the name of Johnny. And Johnny used to work in the
<lb n="151071"/> old gentleman's mill walking round and round in order to drive
<lb n="151072"/> the mill. That was all very well; but now comes the tragic part
<lb n="151073"/> about Johnny. One fine day the old gentleman thought he'd
<lb n="151074"/> like to drive out with the quality to a military review in the
<lb n="151075"/> park.
<lb n="151076"/> <said who="">―</said>The Lord have mercy on his soul, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> com=
<lb n="151077"/> passionately.
  <lb n="151078"/> <said who="">―</said>Amen, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>. So the old gentleman, as I said, har=
<lb n="151079"/> nessed Johnny and put on his very best tall hat and his very
<lb n="151080"/> best stock collar and drove out in grand style from his ancestral
<lb n="151081"/> mansion somewhere near <place> <location> <geo> 53.342514 -6.273225 </geo> </location> <placeName> Back Lane </placeName> </place>, I think.</p>
  <lb n="151082"/> <p>Everyone laughed, even <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName>, at <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s manner
  <lb n="151083"/> and aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> said:
  <lb n="151084"/> <said who="">―</said>O now, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, he didn't live in <place> <location> <geo> 53.342514 -6.273225 </geo> </location> <placeName> Back Lane </placeName> </place> really. Only the
<lb n="151085"/> mill was there.
<lb n="151086"/> <said who="">―</said>Out from the mansion of his forefathers, continued <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>,
<lb n="151087"/> he drove with Johnny. And everything went on beautifully until
<lb n="151088"/> Johnny came in sight of King Billy's statue: and whether he fell
<lb n="151089"/> in love with the horse King Billy sits on or whether he thought
<lb n="151090"/> he was back again in the mill, anyhow he began to walk round
<lb n="151091"/> the statue.</p>
  <lb n="151092"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> paced in a circle round the hall in his goloshes amid
<lb n="151093"/> the laughter of the others.
<lb n="151094"/> <said who="">―</said>Round and round he went, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, and the old gentle=
<lb n="151095"/> man, who was a very pompous old gentleman, was highly
<lb n="151096"/> indignant. <emph>Go on, sir! What do you mean, sir? Johnny! Johnny!
<lb n="151097"/> Most extraordinary conduct! Can't understand the horse!</emph></p>
  <lb n="151098"/> <p>The peals of laughter which followed <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s imitation of
<lb n="151099"/> the incident were interrupted by a resounding knock at the
  <lb n="151100"/> halldoor. <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> ran to open it and let in <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>.
  <lb n="151101"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName>, with his hat well back on his head and his
<lb n="151102"/> shoulders humped with cold, was puffing and steaming after
<lb n="151103"/> his exertions.
<lb n="151104"/> <said who="">―</said>I could only get one cab, he said.
<lb n="151105"/> <said who="">―</said>O, we'll find another along the quay, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
  <lb n="151106"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>. Better not keep <persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName> standing in
<lb n="151107"/> the draught.</p>
  <lb n="151108"/> <p><persName xml:id="mn">Mrs Malins</persName> was helped down the front steps by her son and
  <lb n="151109"/> <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> and, after many manoeuvres, hoisted into the cab.
  <lb n="151110"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> clambered in after her and spent a long time
  <lb n="151111"/> settling her on the seat, <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> helping him with advice. At
  <lb n="151112"/> last she was settled comfortably and <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> invited <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="151113"/> Browne</persName> into the cab. There was a good deal of confused talk,
  <lb n="151114"/> then <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> got into the cab. The cabman settled his rug
<lb n="151115"/> over his knees and bent down for the address. The confusion
<lb n="151116"/> grew greater and the cabman was directed differently by
  <lb n="151117"/> <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> and <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>, each of whom had his head out
<lb n="151118"/> through a window of the cab. The difficulty was to know
  <lb n="151119"/> where to drop <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName> along the route and aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, aunt
  <lb n="151120"/> <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> helped the discussion from the doorstep
<lb n="151121"/> with cross-directions and contradictions and abundance of
  <lb n="151122"/> laughter. As for <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy Malins</persName> he was speechless with laugh=
<lb n="151123"/> ter. He popped his head in and out of the window every mo=
<lb n="151124"/> ment, to the great danger of his hat, and told his mother
<lb n="151125"/> how the discussion was progressing till at last <persName xml:id="bw">Mr Browne</persName>
<lb n="151126"/> shouted to the bewildered cabman above the din of everybody's
<lb n="151127"/> laughter:
<lb n="151128"/> <said who="">―</said>Do you know <place> <location> <geo> 53.344471 -6.258795 </geo> </location> <placeName> Trinity College </placeName> </place>?
<lb n="151129"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, sir, said the cabman.
<lb n="151130"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, drive bang up against <place> <location> <geo> 53.344471 -6.258795 </geo> </location> <placeName> Trinity College </placeName> </place> gates, said <persName xml:id="bw">Mr
  <lb n="151131"/> Browne</persName>, and then we'll tell you where to go. You understand
<lb n="151132"/> now?
<lb n="151133"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, sir, said the cabman.
<lb n="151134"/> <said who="">―</said>Make like a bird for <place> <location> <geo> 53.344471 -6.258795 </geo> </location> <placeName> Trinity College </placeName> </place>.
<lb n="151135"/> <said who="">―</said>Right, sir, cried the cabman.</p>
<lb n="151136"/> <p>The horse was whipped up and the cab rattled off along the
<lb n="151137"/> quay amid a chorus of laughter and adieus.</p>
<lb n="151138"/> <p>Gabriel had not gone to the door with the others. He was in
<lb n="151139"/> a dark part of the hall gazing up the staircase. A woman was
<lb n="151140"/> standing near the top of the first flight in the shadow also. He
<lb n="151141"/> could not see her face but he could see the terracotta and
<lb n="151142"/> salmonpink panels of her skirt which the shadow made appear
<lb n="151143"/> black and white. It was his wife. She was leaning on the
  <lb n="151144"/> banisters listening to something. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> was surprised at her
<lb n="151145"/> stillness and strained his ear to listen also. But he could hear
<lb n="151146"/> little save the noise of laughter and dispute on the front steps, a
<lb n="151147"/> few chords struck on the piano and a few notes of a man's
<lb n="151148"/> voice singing.</p>
<lb n="151149"/> <p>He stood still in the gloom of the hall, trying to catch the air
<lb n="151150"/> that the voice was singing and gazing up at his wife. There was
<lb n="151151"/> grace and mystery in her attitude as if she were a symbol of
<lb n="151152"/> something. He asked himself what is a woman standing on the
<lb n="151153"/> stairs in the shadow, listening to distant music, a symbol of. If
<lb n="151154"/> he were a painter he would paint her in that attitude. Her blue
<lb n="151155"/> felt hat would show off the bronze of her hair against the
<lb n="151156"/> darkness and the dark panels of her skirt would show off the
<lb n="151157"/> light ones. <emph>Distant Music</emph> he would call the picture if he were a
<lb n="151158"/> painter.</p>
  <lb n="151159"/> <p>The halldoor was closed and aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> and <persName xml:id="mj">Mary
  <lb n="151160"/> Jane</persName> came down the hall, still laughing.
  <lb n="151161"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, isn't <persName xml:id="fm">Freddy</persName> terrible? said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>. He's really ter=
<lb n="151162"/> rible.</p>
  <lb n="151163"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> said nothing but pointed up the stairs towards
<lb n="151164"/> where his wife was standing. Now that the halldoor was closed
<lb n="151165"/> the voice and the piano could be heard more clearly. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>
<lb n="151166"/> held up his hand for them to be silent. The song seemed to be
<lb n="151167"/> in the old Irish tonality and the singer seemed uncertain both of
<lb n="151168"/> his words and of his voice. The voice made plaintive by the
<lb n="151169"/> distance and by the singer's hoarseness faintly illuminated the
<lb n="151170"/> cadence of the air with words expressing grief:</p>
<lb n="151171"/> <p><said who="">―</said><emph>O, the rain falls on my heavy locks</p>
<lb n="151172"/> <p>And the dew wets my skin,</p>
<lb n="151173"/> <p>My babe lies cold ...</emph>
  <lb n="151174"/> <said who="">―</said>O, exclaimed <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>. It's <persName xml:id="bda">Bartell D'Arcy</persName> singing and he
<lb n="151175"/> wouldn't sing all the night. O, I'll get him to sing a song before
<lb n="151176"/> he goes.
  <lb n="151177"/> <said who="">―</said>O do, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="151178"/> <p><persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName> brushed past the others and ran to the staircase
<lb n="151179"/> but before she reached it the singing stopped and the piano was
<lb n="151180"/> closed abruptly.
<lb n="151181"/> <said who="">―</said>O, what a pity! she cried. Is he coming down, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>?</p>
  <lb n="151182"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> heard his wife answer yes and saw her come down
<lb n="151183"/> towards them. A few steps behind her were <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>
  <lb n="151184"/> and <persName xml:id="ocl">Miss O'Callaghan</persName>.
  <lb n="151185"/> <said who="">―</said>O, <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>, cried <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, it's downright mean of you
<lb n="151186"/> to break off like that when we were all in raptures listening to
<lb n="151187"/> you.
<lb n="151188"/> <said who="">―</said>I have been at him all the evening, said <persName xml:id="ocl">Miss O'Callaghan</persName>,
  <lb n="151189"/> and <persName xml:id="gt">Mrs Conroy</persName> too, and he told us he had a dreadful cold and
<lb n="151190"/> couldn't sing.
  <lb n="151191"/> <said who="">―</said>O, <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, now that was a great fib to
<lb n="151192"/> tell.
<lb n="151193"/> <said who="">―</said>Can't you see that I'm as hoarse as a crow? said <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>
<lb n="151194"/> roughly.</p>
<lb n="151195"/> <p>He went into the pantry hastily and put on his overcoat. The
<lb n="151196"/> others, taken aback by his rude speech, could find nothing to
  <lb n="151197"/> say. Aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> wrinkled her brows and made signs to the
  <lb n="151198"/> others to drop the subject. <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName> stood swathing his neck
<lb n="151199"/> carefully and frowning.
<lb n="151200"/> <said who="">―</said>It's the weather, said aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> after a pause.
<lb n="151201"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, everybody has colds, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName> readily, everybody.
  <lb n="151202"/> <said who="">―</said>They say, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, we haven't had snow like it for
<lb n="151203"/> thirty years: and I read this morning in the newspaper that the
<lb n="151204"/> snow is general all over Ireland.
<lb n="151205"/> <said who="">―</said>I love the look of snow, said aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> sadly.
<lb n="151206"/> <said who="">―</said>So do I, said <persName xml:id="ocl">Miss O'Callaghan</persName>. I think Christmas is never
<lb n="151207"/> really Christmas unless we have the snow on the ground.
  <lb n="151208"/> <said who="">―</said>But poor <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName> doesn't like the snow, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>
<lb n="151209"/> smiling.</p>
  <lb n="151210"/> <p><persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName> came from the pantry, fully swathed and but=
<lb n="151211"/> toned, and in a repentant tone told them the history of his cold.
<lb n="151212"/> Everyone gave him advice and said it was a great pity and
<lb n="151213"/> urged him to be very careful of his throat in the night air.
  <lb n="151214"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> watched his wife who did not join in the conversation.
<lb n="151215"/> She was standing right under the dusty fanlight and the flame
<lb n="151216"/> of the gas lit up the rich bronze of her hair which he had seen
<lb n="151217"/> her drying at the fire a few days before. She was in the same
<lb n="151218"/> attitude and seemed unaware of the talk about her. At last she
  <lb n="151219"/> turned towards them and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> saw that there was colour on
<lb n="151220"/> her cheeks and that her eyes were shining. A sudden tide of joy
<lb n="151221"/> went leaping out of his heart.
  <lb n="151222"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>, she said, what is the name of that song you were
<lb n="151223"/> singing?
<lb n="151224"/> <said who="">―</said>It's called <emph>The Lass of Aughrim</emph>, said <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>, but I
<lb n="151225"/> couldn't remember it properly. Why? Do you know it?
<lb n="151226"/> <said who="">―</said><emph>The Lass of Aughrim</emph>, she repeated. I couldn't think of the
<lb n="151227"/> name.
<lb n="151228"/> <said who="">―</said>It's a very nice air, said <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>. I'm sorry you were not
<lb n="151229"/> in voice tonight.
  <lb n="151230"/> <said who="">―</said>Now, <persName xml:id="mj">Mary Jane</persName>, said aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, don't annoy <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>. I
<lb n="151231"/> won't have him annoyed.</p>
<lb n="151232"/> <p>Seeing that all were ready to start she shepherded them to
<lb n="151233"/> the door where goodnight was said:
  <lb n="151234"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, goodnight aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, and thanks for the pleasant
<lb n="151235"/> evening.
  <lb n="151236"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>. Goodnight, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>!
  <lb n="151237"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight, aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>, and thanks ever so much. Goodnight,
  <lb n="151238"/> aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>.
  <lb n="151239"/> <said who="">―</said>O, goodnight, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>, I didn't see you.
  <lb n="151240"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight, <persName xml:id="bda">Mr D'Arcy</persName>. Goodnight, <persName xml:id="ocl">Miss O'Callaghan</persName>.
<lb n="151241"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight, Miss Morkan.
<lb n="151242"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight again.
<lb n="151243"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight all. Safe home.
<lb n="151244"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight. Goodnight.</p>
<lb n="151245"/> <p>The morning was still dark. A dull yellow light brooded
<lb n="151246"/> over the houses and the river and the sky seemed to be
<lb n="151247"/> descending. It was slushy underfoot and only streaks and
<lb n="151248"/> patches of snow lay on the roofs, on the parapets of the quay
<lb n="151249"/> and on the area railings. The lamps were still burning redly in
<lb n="151250"/> the murky air and, across the river, the palace of the <place> <location> <geo> 53.345699 -6.273685 </geo> </location> <placeName> Four
<lb n="151251"/> Courts </placeName> </place> stood out menacingly against the heavy sky.</p>
<lb n="151252"/> <p>She was walking on before him with <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>, her
<lb n="151253"/> shoes in a brown parcel tucked under one arm and her hands
<lb n="151254"/> holding her skirt up from the slush. She had no longer any
  <lb n="151255"/> grace of attitude but <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s eyes were still bright with
<lb n="151256"/> happiness. The blood went bounding along his veins and the
<lb n="151257"/> thoughts went rioting through his brain, proud, joyful, tender,
<lb n="151258"/> valorous.</p>
<lb n="151259"/> <p>She was walking on before him so lightly and so erect that
<lb n="151260"/> he longed to run after her noiselessly, catch her by the shoul=
<lb n="151261"/> ders and say something foolish and affectionate into her ear.
<lb n="151262"/> She seemed to him so frail that he longed to defend her against
<lb n="151263"/> something and then to be alone with her. Moments of their
<lb n="151264"/> secret life together burst like stars upon his memory. A helio=
<lb n="151265"/> trope envelope was lying beside his breakfast cup and he was
<lb n="151266"/> caressing it with his hand. Birds were twittering in the ivy and
<lb n="151267"/> the sunny web of the curtain was shimmering along the floor:
<lb n="151268"/> he could not eat for happiness. They were standing on the
<lb n="151269"/> crowded platform and he was placing a ticket inside the warm
<lb n="151270"/> palm of her glove. He was standing with her in the cold, look=
<lb n="151271"/> ing in through a grated window at a man making bottles in a
<lb n="151272"/> roaring furnace. It was very cold. Her face, fragrant in the cold
<lb n="151273"/> air, was quite close to his and suddenly she called out to the
<lb n="151274"/> man at the furnace:
<lb n="151275"/> <said who="">―</said>Is the fire hot, sir?</p>
<lb n="151276"/> <p>But the man could not hear her with the noise of the furnace.
<lb n="151277"/> It was just as well. He might have answered rudely.</p>
<lb n="151278"/> <p>A wave of yet more tender joy escaped from his heart and
<lb n="151279"/> went coursing in warm flood along his arteries. Like the tender
<lb n="151280"/> fire of stars moments of their life together, that no one knew of
<lb n="151281"/> or would ever know of, broke upon and illumined his memory.
<lb n="151282"/> He longed to recall to her those moments, to make her forget
<lb n="151283"/> the years of their dull existence together and remember only
<lb n="151284"/> their moments of ecstasy. For the years, he felt, had not
<lb n="151285"/> quenched his soul or hers. Their children, his writing, her
<lb n="151286"/> household cares had not quenched all their souls' tender fire. In
<lb n="151287"/> one letter that he had written to her then he had said: <emph>Why is it
<lb n="151288"/> that words like these seem to me so dull and cold? Is it because
<lb n="151289"/> there is no word tender enough to be your name?</emph></p>
<lb n="151290"/> <p>Like distant music these words that he had written years
<lb n="151291"/> before were borne towards him from the past. He longed to be
<lb n="151292"/> alone with her. When the others had gone away, when he and
<lb n="151293"/> she were in their room in the hotel, then they would be alone
<lb n="151294"/> together. He would call her softly:
  <lb n="151295"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>!</p>
<lb n="151296"/> <p>Perhaps she would not hear at once: she would be undress=
<lb n="151297"/> ing. Then something in his voice would strike her. She would
<lb n="151298"/> turn and look at him ....</p>
<lb n="151299"/> <p>At the corner of <place> <location> <geo> 53.344921 -6.27212 </geo> </location> <placeName> Winetavern Street </placeName> </place> they met a cab. He was
<lb n="151300"/> glad of its rattling noise as it saved him from conversation. She
<lb n="151301"/> was looking out of the window and seemed tired. The others
<lb n="151302"/> spoke only a few words, pointing out some building or street.
<lb n="151303"/> The horse galloped along wearily under the murky morning
<lb n="151304"/> sky, dragging his old rattling box after his heels, and <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>
<lb n="151305"/> was again in a cab with her galloping to catch the boat,
<lb n="151306"/> galloping to their honeymoon.</p>
<lb n="151307"/> <p>As the cab drove across <place> <location> <geo> 53.348698 -6.259916 </geo> </location> <placeName> O'Connell bridge </placeName> </place> <persName xml:id="ocl">Miss O'Callaghan</persName>
<lb n="151308"/> said:
<lb n="151309"/> <said who="">―</said>They say you never cross <place> <location> <geo> 53.348698 -6.259916 </geo> </location> <placeName> O'Connell bridge </placeName> </place> without seeing a
<lb n="151310"/> white horse.
<lb n="151311"/> <said who="">―</said>I see a white man this time, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151312"/> <said who="">―</said>Where? asked <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>.</p>
  <lb n="151313"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> pointed to the statue on which lay patches of snow.
<lb n="151314"/> Then he nodded familiarly to it and waved his hand.
<lb n="151315"/> <said who="">―</said>Goodnight, Dan, he said gaily.</p>
  <lb n="151316"/> <p>When the cab drew up before the hotel <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> jumped out
  <lb n="151317"/> and, in spite of <persName xml:id="bda">Mr Bartell D'Arcy</persName>'s protest, paid the driver. He
<lb n="151318"/> gave the man a shilling over his fare. The man saluted and said:
<lb n="151319"/> <said who="">―</said>A prosperous new year to you, sir.
  <lb n="151320"/> <said who="">―</said>The same to you, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> cordially.</p>
<lb n="151321"/> <p>She leaned for a moment on his arm in getting out of the cab
<lb n="151322"/> and while standing at the kerbstone bidding the others good=
<lb n="151323"/> night. She leaned lightly on his arm, as lightly as when she had
<lb n="151324"/> danced with him a few hours before. He had felt proud and
<lb n="151325"/> happy then, happy that she was his, proud of her grace and
<lb n="151326"/> wifely carriage. But now after the kindling again of so many
<lb n="151327"/> memories, the first touch of her body, musical and strange and
<lb n="151328"/> perfumed, sent through him a keen pang of lust. Under cover of
<lb n="151329"/> her silence he pressed her arm closely to his side: and, as they
<lb n="151330"/> stood at the hotel door, he felt that they had escaped from their
<lb n="151331"/> lives and duties, escaped from home and friends and run away
<lb n="151332"/> together with wild and radiant hearts to a new adventure.</p>
<lb n="151333"/> <p>An old man was dozing in a great hooded chair in the hall.
<lb n="151334"/> He lit a candle in the office and went before them to the stairs.
<lb n="151335"/> They followed him in silence, their feet falling in soft thuds on
<lb n="151336"/> the thickly carpeted stairs. She mounted the stairs behind the
<lb n="151337"/> porter, her head bowed in the ascent, her frail shoulders curved
<lb n="151338"/> as with a burden, her skirt girt tightly about her. He could have
<lb n="151339"/> flung his arms about her hips and held her still for his arms
<lb n="151340"/> were trembling with desire to seize her and only the stress of
<lb n="151341"/> his nails against the palms of his hands held the wild impulse of
<lb n="151342"/> his body in check. The porter halted on the stairs to settle his
<lb n="151343"/> guttering candle. They halted too on the steps below him. In
  <lb n="151344"/> the silence <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> could hear the falling of the molten wax
<lb n="151345"/> into the tray and the thumping of his own heart against his
<lb n="151346"/> ribs.</p>
<lb n="151347"/> <p>The porter led them along a corridor and opened a door.
<lb n="151348"/> Then he set his unstable candle down on a toilet table and
<lb n="151349"/> asked at what hour they were to be called in the morning.
  <lb n="151350"/> <said who="">―</said>Eight, said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.</p>
<lb n="151351"/> <p>The porter pointed to the tap of the electric light and began
  <lb n="151352"/> a muttered apology but <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> cut him short.
<lb n="151353"/> <said who="">―</said>We don't want any light. We have light enough from the
<lb n="151354"/> street. And, I say, he added pointing to the candle, you might
<lb n="151355"/> remove that handsome article, like a good man.</p>
<lb n="151356"/> <p>The porter took up his candle again, but slowly, for he was
<lb n="151357"/> surprised by such a novel idea. Then he mumbled goodnight
  <lb n="151358"/> and went out. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> shot the lock to.</p>
<lb n="151359"/> <p>A ghostly light from the street lamp lay in a long shaft from
  <lb n="151360"/> one window to the door. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> threw his overcoat and hat on
<lb n="151361"/> a couch and crossed the room towards the window. He looked
<lb n="151362"/> down into the street in order that his emotion might calm a
<lb n="151363"/> little. Then he turned and leaned against a chest of drawers
<lb n="151364"/> with his back to the light. She had taken off her hat and cloak
<lb n="151365"/> and was standing before a large swinging mirror, unhooking
<lb n="151366"/> her waist. Gabriel paused for a few moments, watching her,
<lb n="151367"/> and then said:
  <lb n="151368"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>!</p>
<lb n="151369"/> <p>She turned away from the mirror slowly and walked along
<lb n="151370"/> the shaft of light towards him. Her face looked so serious and
  <lb n="151371"/> weary that the words would not pass <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s lips. No, it was
<lb n="151372"/> not the moment yet.
<lb n="151373"/> <said who="">―</said>You look tired, he said.
<lb n="151374"/> <said who="">―</said>I am a little, she answered.
<lb n="151375"/> <said who="">―</said>You don't feel ill or weak?
<lb n="151376"/> <said who="">―</said>No, tired: that's all.</p>
<lb n="151377"/> <p>She went on to the window and stood there, looking out.
<lb n="151378"/> Gabriel waited again and then, fearing that diffidence was
<lb n="151379"/> about to conquer him, he said abruptly:
  <lb n="151380"/> <said who="">―</said>By the way, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>!
<lb n="151381"/> <said who="">―</said>What is it?
<lb n="151382"/> <said who="">―</said>You know that poor fellow <persName xml:id="fm">Malins</persName>? he said quickly.
<lb n="151383"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, what about him?
<lb n="151384"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, poor fellow, he's a decent sort of chap after all, con=
  <lb n="151385"/> tinued <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> in a false voice. He gave me back that sovereign
<lb n="151386"/> I lent him and I didn't expect it really. It's a pity he wouldn't
  <lb n="151387"/> keep away from that <persName xml:id="bw">Browne</persName> because he's not a bad fellow at
<lb n="151388"/> heart.</p>
<lb n="151389"/> <p>He was trembling now with annoyance. Why did she seem
<lb n="151390"/> so abstracted? He did not know how he could begin. Was she
<lb n="151391"/> annoyed too about something? If she would only turn to him or
<lb n="151392"/> come to him of her own accord! To take her as she was would
<lb n="151393"/> be brutal. No, he must see some ardour in her eyes first. He
<lb n="151394"/> longed to be master of her strange mood.
<lb n="151395"/> <said who="">―</said>When did you lend him the pound? she asked after a pause.</p>
  <lb n="151396"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> strove to restrain himself from breaking out into
  <lb n="151397"/> brutal language about the sottish <persName xml:id="fm">Malins</persName> and his pound. He
<lb n="151398"/> longed to cry to her from his soul, to crush her body against
<lb n="151399"/> his, to overmaster her. But he said:
<lb n="151400"/> <said who="">―</said>O, at Christmas, when he opened that little Christmas card
<lb n="151401"/> shop in <place> <location> <geo> 53.349388 -6.262605 </geo> </location> <placeName> Henry Street </placeName> </place>.</p>
<lb n="151402"/> <p>He was in such a fever of rage and desire that he did not
<lb n="151403"/> hear her come from the window. She stood before him for an
<lb n="151404"/> instant looking at him strangely. Then, suddenly raising herself
<lb n="151405"/> on tiptoe and resting her hands lightly on his shoulders, she
<lb n="151406"/> kissed him.
<lb n="151407"/> <said who="">―</said>You are a very generous person, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, she said.
<lb n="151408"/> Gabriel, trembling with delight at her sudden kiss and at the
<lb n="151409"/> quaintness of her phrase, put his hands on her hair and began
<lb n="151410"/> smoothing it back, scarcely touching it with his fingers. The
<lb n="151411"/> washing had made it fine and brilliant. His heart was brimming
<lb n="151412"/> over with happiness. Just when he was wishing for it she had
<lb n="151413"/> come to him of her own accord. Perhaps her thoughts had been
<lb n="151414"/> running with his. Perhaps she had felt the impetuous desire that
<lb n="151415"/> was in him and then the yielding mood had come upon her.
<lb n="151416"/> Now that she had fallen to him so easily he wondered why he
<lb n="151417"/> had been so diffident.</p>
<lb n="151418"/> <p>He stood, holding her head between his hands. Then, slip=
<lb n="151419"/> ping one arm swiftly about her body and drawing her towards
<lb n="151420"/> him, he said softly:
  <lb n="151421"/> <said who="">―</said><persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName> dear, what are you thinking about?</p>
<lb n="151422"/> <p>She did not answer nor yield wholly to his arm. He said
<lb n="151423"/> again softly:
  <lb n="151424"/> <said who="">―</said>Tell me what it is, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>. I think I know what is the matter.
<lb n="151425"/> Do I know?</p>
<lb n="151426"/> <p>She did not answer at once. Then she said in an outburst of
<lb n="151427"/> tears:
<lb n="151428"/> <said who="">―</said>O, I am thinking about that song, <emph>The Lass of Aughrim.</emph></p>
<lb n="151429"/> <p>She broke loose from him and ran to the bed and, throwing
  <lb n="151430"/> her arms across the bedrail, hid her face. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persNAme> stood stock=
<lb n="151431"/> still for a moment in astonishment and then followed her. As
<lb n="151432"/> he passed in the way of the cheval glass he caught sight of
<lb n="151433"/> himself in full length, his broad, wellfilled shirtfront, the face
<lb n="151434"/> whose expression always puzzled him when he saw it in a
<lb n="151435"/> mirror and his glimmering giltrimmed eyeglasses. He halted a
<lb n="151436"/> few paces from her and said:
<lb n="151437"/> <said who="">―</said>What about the song? Why does that make you cry?</p>
<lb n="151438"/> <p>She raised her head from her arms and dried her eyes with
<lb n="151439"/> the back of her hand like a child. A kinder note than he had
<lb n="151440"/> intended went into his voice.
  <lb n="151441"/> <said who="">―</said>Why, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>? he asked.
<lb n="151442"/> <said who="">―</said>I am thinking about a person long ago who used to sing that
<lb n="151443"/> song.
<lb n="151444"/> <said who="">―</said>And who was the person long ago? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> smiling.
<lb n="151445"/> <said who="">―</said>It was a person I used to know in <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place> when I was living
<lb n="151446"/> with my grandmother, she said.</p>
  <lb n="151447"/> <p>The smile passed away from <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s face. A dull anger
<lb n="151448"/> began to gather again at the back of his mind and the dull fires
<lb n="151449"/> of his lust began to glow angrily in his veins.
<lb n="151450"/> <said who="">―</said>Someone you were in love with? he asked ironically.
<lb n="151451"/> <said who="">―</said>It was a young boy I used to know, she answered, named
  <lb n="151452"/> <persName xml:id="mf">Michael Furey</persName>. He used to sing that song, <emph>The Lass of Augh=
<lb n="151453"/> rim.</emph> He was very delicate.</p>
  <lb n="151454"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> was silent. He did not wish her to think that he was
<lb n="151455"/> interested in this delicate boy.
<lb n="151456"/> <said who="">―</said>I can see him so plainly, she said after a moment. Such eyes
<lb n="151457"/> as he had, big dark eyes! And such an expression in them - an
<lb n="151458"/> expression! ...
<lb n="151459"/> <said who="">―</said>O, then you were in love with him? said <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151460"/> <said who="">―</said>I used to go out walking with him, she said, when I was in
<lb n="151461"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place>.</p>
<lb n="151462"/> <p>A thought flew across Gabriel's mind.
<lb n="151463"/> <said who="">―</said>Perhaps that was why you wanted to go to <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place> with that
<lb n="151464"/> Ivors girl? he said coldly.</p>
<lb n="151465"/> <p>She looked at him and asked in surprise:
<lb n="151466"/> <said who="">―</said>What for?</p>
  <lb n="151467"/> <p>Her eyes made <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> feel awkward. He shrugged his
<lb n="151468"/> shoulders and said:
<lb n="151469"/> <said who="">―</said>How do I know? To see him, perhaps.</p>
<lb n="151470"/> <p>She looked away from him along the shaft of light towards
<lb n="151471"/> the window in silence.
<lb n="151472"/> <said who="">―</said>He is dead, she said at length. He died when he was only
<lb n="151473"/> seventeen. Isn't it a terrible thing to die so young as that?
  <lb n="151474"/> <said who="">―</said>What was he? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, still ironically.
<lb n="151475"/> <said who="">―</said>He was in the gasworks, she said.</p>
  <lb n="151476"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> felt humiliated by the failure of his irony and by the
<lb n="151477"/> evocation of this figure from the dead, a boy in the gasworks.
<lb n="151478"/> The irony of his mood soured into sarcasm. While he had been
<lb n="151479"/> full of memories of their secret life together, full of tenderness
<lb n="151480"/> and joy and desire, she had been comparing him in her mind
<lb n="151481"/> with another. A shameful consciousness of his own person
<lb n="151482"/> assailed him. He saw himself as a ludicrous figure, acting as a
<lb n="151483"/> pennyboy for his aunts, a nervous wellmeaning sentimentalist,
<lb n="151484"/> orating to vulgarians and idealising his own clownish lusts, the
<lb n="151485"/> pitiable fatuous fellow he had caught a glimpse of in the
<lb n="151486"/> mirror. Instinctively he turned his back more to the light lest
<lb n="151487"/> she might see the shame that burned upon his forehead.</p>
<lb n="151488"/> <p>He tried to keep up his tone of cold interrogation but his
<lb n="151489"/> voice when he spoke was humble and indifferent.
<lb n="151490"/> <said who="">―</said>I suppose you were in love with this <persName xml:id="mf">Michael Furey</persName>, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>,
<lb n="151491"/> he said.
<lb n="151492"/> <said who="">―</said>I was great with him at that time, she said.</p>
  <lb n="151493"/> <p>Her voice was veiled and sad. <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, feeling now how vain
<lb n="151494"/> it would be to try to lead her whither he had purposed,
<lb n="151495"/> caressed one of her hands and said also sadly:
<lb n="151496"/> <said who="">―</said>And what did he die of so young, <persName xml:id="gt">Gretta</persName>? Consumption,
<lb n="151497"/> was it?
<lb n="151498"/> <said who="">―</said>I think he died for me, she answered.</p>
  <lb n="151499"/> <p>A vague terror seized <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> at this answer as if, at that
<lb n="151500"/> hour when he had hoped to triumph, some impalpable and
<lb n="151501"/> vindictive being was coming against him, gathering forces
<lb n="151502"/> against him in its vague world. But he shook himself free of it
<lb n="151503"/> with an effort of reason and continued to caress her hand. He
<lb n="151504"/> did not question her again for he felt that she would tell him of
<lb n="151505"/> herself. Her hand was warm and moist: it did not respond to
<lb n="151506"/> his touch but he continued to caress it just as he had caressed
<lb n="151507"/> her first letter to him that spring morning.
<lb n="151508"/> <said who="">―</said>It was in the winter, she said, about the beginning of the
<lb n="151509"/> winter when I was going to leave my grandmother's and come
<lb n="151510"/> up here to the convent. And he was ill at the time in his
<lb n="151511"/> lodgings in <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place> and wouldn't be let out and his people in
<lb n="151512"/> <place> <location> <geo> 53.43166 -9.319044 </geo> </location> <placeName> Oughterard </placeName> </place> were written to. He was in decline, they said, or
<lb n="151513"/> something like that. I never knew rightly.</p>
<lb n="151514"/> <p>She paused for a moment and sighed.
<lb n="151515"/> <said who="">―</said>Poor fellow, she said, he was very fond of me and he was
<lb n="151516"/> such a gentle boy. We used to go out together walking, you
  <lb n="151517"/> know, <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, like the way they do in the country. He was
<lb n="151518"/> going to study singing only for his health. He had a very good
  <lb n="151519"/> voice, poor <persName xml:id="mf">Michael Furey</persName>.
  <lb n="151520"/> <said who="">―</said>Well, and then? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151521"/> <said who="">―</said>And then when it came to the time for me to leave <place> <location> <geo> 53.273796 -9.05178 </geo> </location> <placeName> Galway </placeName> </place>
<lb n="151522"/> and come up to the convent he was much worse and I wouldn't
<lb n="151523"/> be let see him so I wrote him a letter saying I was going up to
<lb n="151524"/> Dublin and would be back in the summer and hoping he would
<lb n="151525"/> be better then.</p>
<lb n="151526"/> <p>She paused for a moment to get her voice under control and
<lb n="151527"/> then went on:
<lb n="151528"/> <said who="">―</said>Then the night before I left I was in my grandmother's house
<lb n="151529"/> in <place> <location> <geo> 53.273029 -9.057696 </geo> </location> <placeName> Nun's Island </placeName> </place>, packing up, and I heard gravel thrown up
<lb n="151530"/> against the window. The window was so wet I couldn't see so I
<lb n="151531"/> ran downstairs as I was and slipped out the back into the
<lb n="151532"/> garden and there was the poor fellow at the end of the garden
<lb n="151533"/> shivering.
<lb n="151534"/> <said who="">―</said>And did you not tell him to go back? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151535"/> <said who="">―</said>I implored of him to go home at once and told him he would
<lb n="151536"/> get his death in the rain. But he said he did not want to live. I
<lb n="151537"/> can see his eyes as well as well! He was standing at the end of
<lb n="151538"/> the wall where there was a tree.
<lb n="151539"/> <said who="">―</said>And did he go home? asked <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>.
<lb n="151540"/> <said who="">―</said>Yes, he went home. And when I was only a week in the
<lb n="151541"/> convent he died and he was buried in <place> <location> <geo> 53.43166 -9.319044 </geo> </location> <placeName> Oughterard </placeName> </place> where his
<lb n="151542"/> people came from. O, the day I heard that, that he was
<lb n="151543"/> dead! ....</p>
<lb n="151544"/> <p>She stopped, choking with sobs and, overcome by emotion,
<lb n="151545"/> flung herself face downward on the bed, sobbing in the quilt.
  <lb n="151546"/> <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName> held her hand for a moment longer, irresolutely, and
<lb n="151547"/> then, shy of intruding on her grief, let it fall gently and walked
<lb n="151548"/> quietly to the window.</p>
<lb n="151549"/> <p>She was fast asleep.</p>
  <lb n="151550"/> <p><persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>, leaning on his elbow, looked for a few moments
<lb n="151551"/> unresentfully at her tangled hair and half open mouth, listening
<lb n="151552"/> to her deep drawn breath. So she had had that romance in her
<lb n="151553"/> life: a man had died for her sake. It hardly pained him now to
<lb n="151554"/> think how poor a part he, her husband, had played in her life.
<lb n="151555"/> He watched her while she slept as though he and she had never
<lb n="151556"/> lived together as man and wife. His curious eyes rested long
<lb n="151557"/> upon her face and on her hair: and as he thought of what she
<lb n="151558"/> must have been then, in that time of her first girlish beauty, a
<lb n="151559"/> strange friendly pity for her entered his soul. He did not like to
<lb n="151560"/> say even to himself that her face was no longer beautiful but he
<lb n="151561"/> knew that it was no longer the face for which <persName xml:id="mf">Michael Furey</persName>
<lb n="151562"/> had braved death.</p>
<lb n="151563"/> <p>Perhaps she had not told him all the story. His eyes moved
<lb n="151564"/> to the chair over which she had thrown some of her clothes. A
<lb n="151565"/> petticoat string dangled to the floor. One boot stood upright,
<lb n="151566"/> its limp upper fallen down: the fellow of it lay upon its side. He
<lb n="151567"/> wondered at his riot of emotions of an hour before. From what
<lb n="151568"/> had it proceeded? From his aunts' supper, from his own foolish
<lb n="151569"/> speech, from the wine and dancing, the merrymaking when
<lb n="151570"/> saying goodnight in the hall, the pleasure of the walk along the
  <lb n="151571"/> river in the snow. Poor aunt <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName>! She too would soon be a
  <lb n="151572"/> shade with the shade of <persName xml:id="pm">Patrick Morkan</persName> and his horse. He had
<lb n="151573"/> caught that haggard look upon her face for a moment when she
<lb n="151574"/> was singing <emph>Arrayed for the Bridal.</emph> Soon perhaps he would be
<lb n="151575"/> sitting in that same drawingroom, dressed in black, his silk hat
<lb n="151576"/> on his knees. The blinds would be drawn down and aunt <persName xml:id="kt">Kate</persName>
<lb n="151577"/> would be sitting beside him, crying and blowing her nose and
  <lb n="151578"/> telling him how <persName xml:id="jl">Julia</persName> had died. He would cast about in his
<lb n="151579"/> mind for some words that might console her and would find
<lb n="151580"/> only lame and useless ones. Yes, yes: that would happen very
<lb n="151581"/> soon.</p>
<lb n="151582"/> <p>The air of the room chilled his shoulders. He stretched him=
<lb n="151583"/> self cautiously along under the sheets and lay down beside his
<lb n="151584"/> wife. One by one they were all becoming shades. Better pass
<lb n="151585"/> boldly into that other world, in the full glory of some passion,
<lb n="151586"/> than fade and wither dismally with age. He thought of how she
<lb n="151587"/> who lay beside him had locked in her heart for so many years
<lb n="151588"/> that image of her lover's eyes when he had told her that he did
<lb n="151589"/> not wish to live.</p>
  <lb n="151590"/> <p>Generous tears filled <persName xml:id="gc">Gabriel</persName>'s eyes. He had never felt like
<lb n="151591"/> that himself towards any woman but he knew that such a
<lb n="151592"/> feeling must be love. The tears gathered more thickly in his
<lb n="151593"/> eyes and in the partial darkness he imagined he saw the form of
<lb n="151594"/> a young man standing under a dripping tree. Other forms were
<lb n="151595"/> near. His soul had approached that region where dwell the vast
<lb n="151596"/> hosts of the dead. He was conscious of, but could not appre=
<lb n="151597"/> hend, their wayward and flickering existence. His own identity
<lb n="151598"/> was fading out into a grey impalpable world: the solid world
<lb n="151599"/> itself which these dead had one time reared and lived in was
<lb n="151600"/> dissolving and dwindling.</p>
<lb n="151601"/> <p>A few light taps upon the pane made him turn to the win=
<lb n="151602"/> dow. It had begun to snow again. He watched sleepily the
<lb n="151603"/> flakes, silver and dark, falling obliquely against the lamplight.
<lb n="151604"/> The time had come for him to set out on his journey westward.
<lb n="151605"/> Yes, the newspapers were right: snow was general all over
<lb n="151606"/> Ireland. It was falling on every part of the dark central plain,
<lb n="151607"/> on the treeless hills, falling softly upon the <place> <location> <geo> 53.274548 -6.944256 </geo> </location> <placeName> Bog of Allen </placeName> </place> and,
<lb n="151608"/> farther westward, softly falling into the dark mutinous <place> <location> <geo> 52.677631 -8.985443 </geo> </location> <placeName> Shan=
<lb n="151609"/> non waves </placeName> </place>. It was falling, too, upon every part of the lonely
  <lb n="151610"/> churchyard on the hill where <persName xml:id="mf">Michael Furey</persName> lay buried. It lay
<lb n="151611"/> thickly drifted on the crooked crosses and headstones, on the
<lb n="151612"/> spears of the little gate, on the barren thorns. His soul swooned
<lb n="151613"/> slowly as he heard the snow falling faintly through the universe
<lb n="151614"/> and faintly falling, like the descent of their last end, upon all
<lb n="151615"/> the living and the dead.</p>
</div> <!-- End of story -->
